Why the working class?

By Hal Draper

Hal Draper was a 20th century American socialist whose political life spanned the two great eras of upheaval in the 1930s and 1960s. Draper is best remembered today as an author on Marx and Marxism, including his five-volume Karl Marx's Theory of Revolution. He also wrote the pamphlet "The Two Souls of Socialism," which makes the case for "socialism from below."

For a May Day issue of the Labor Action newspaper in the early 1950s, Draper wrote the following article about the centrality of working class struggle to the Marxist tradition. While the shape and structure of the U.S. and world working class has changed with a half-century of historical development, his analysis remains an excellent introduction to the Marxist understanding of class and class struggle. The text here is republished from the Bureau of Counterpropaganda website.

WHY DO socialists believe there is a special connection between their own great goal of a new society and the interests of labor, this one segment of society? Is it because we "idealize" workers as being better, or more clever, or more honest, or more courageous, or more humanitarian, than non-workers?

Isn't it rather true that the workers have time and again followed reactionary courses and leaders, and have by no means shown any invariable affinity for progressive causes? Haven't they been misled and deceived like any other section of society? Aren't they filled with race prejudice in the U.S., sometimes even more so than the upper classes? If it is true that workers are "naturally" pro-socialists, why is it that they have made such a mess of things, voting for reactionaries and fakers and supporters of the status quo?... And so on.

Most of this type of questioning is based on simple misunderstanding of the socialist viewpoint about the working class. Especially in this country, where the socialist movement has always been relatively weak, the most popular anti-socialist notions are most often founded on misinformation about what socialists believe, because their voices have not been loudly heard.

Socialists do not "idealize" workers in any sense whatsoever. Taking them man for man, as individuals, there is no reason to argue whether workers are "better" human beings than others because they are workers. This whole approach, whether pro or con, has nothing to do with the socialist conception.

To underline this in a different way: If we try to view social issues as merely conflicts between Good People and Bad People, then surely we must say that men who insist on starving others are Bad. The present minimum wage is surely a pittance; yet opposition even to this pittance was strong among employers, especially small employers, while virtually absent among workers. Is this tendency among employers because they are Bad Men? On the contrary, these employers are just as likely to be kind fathers, generous friends, indulgent husbands, charity givers--not the type to deliberately run over children in the street. They act one way as individual atoms in the social fabric; they act quite another way as part of their class collectivity.

They explain this, when they do, by saying, "Business is business." This is their way of distinguishing their individual human thoughts and role from their role as a member of the business community--that is, of their class. In the latter case, the conditions of existence and interests of "business" make out of them a social force that has little resemblance to their individual psychologies.

Like every other class or group, the working class is more than the sum of its individual atoms.

Man for man, workers are not "naturally" more pro-socialist than anyone else. It is a question of what direction they are pushed in by the conditions of their existence as a class and by their interests as workers, just as with any other group.

This indeed is one reason why, so often, socialist ideas tend to be initiated in a systematic way not by ideologists from the working class, but by men from the "educated classes," the bourgeoisie and intellectuals, men like Marx and Engels, for example, who were not proletarians themselves--although it should be noted that the impulses to the systemization of such ideas were coming from the working masses' struggles and conditions, not from other sections of society. Individuals were led to align themselves with the working class.

If they were drawn in this direction, it was because here was the dynamic social force which they recognized as the decisive one for putting flesh and blood on ideas.

WHEN A working class is politically and socially undeveloped, it is well nigh inevitable that its members will be filled with all sorts of backward and even reactionary notions. For example, it has often been found in the U.S. that racial intolerance decreases with amount of education: college graduates are less prejudiced, etc. Now, in general, working class children get less schooling than upper-class offspring. So according to this pattern, workers should be far more filled with racism than the middle class. It is instructive to see where this neat pattern does and does not hold.

It holds best where labor is most poorly organized as a class and most recently organized, and where it is organized in the least class-conscious fashion. The South is not only a cauldron of racism, but also a sinkhole of union-busting and open-shoppism. Toward the other end of the scale, racism is combated--as nowhere in middle-class groups--in the more militant mass-production unions that sprang from the CIO upheaval, like the United Auto Workers, not to speak of the socialist movement.

Here anti-racism is not a function of school education; it is a function of class education. In many a mass-production integrated local, the organization is often far more anti-racist than the sum of its members. That is, the dynamics of class needs push it more strongly against racism, which is divisive of the class, than do the individual opinions of its members.

What we have been emphasizing is that the socialist sees no special magic in the "worker" as an atomized individual. The special "advantage" of the working class springs from inherent drives of its class position in society, its ineradicable interests as a group, its conditions of life; and its "advantage" comes into play only insofar as this class organizes itself (as it is inevitably driven to do) and transforms the thinking of its individual components in the course of class experiences.

Now it is this sort of thing that the socialist calls the development of class consciousness. The U.S. is the one modern country in the world where the working class is still at a rather elementary stage of class consciousness. Therefore, it is particularly in this country, and most particularly among academicians, who have no roots in the real social struggle of our times, that the special role of the working class is most persistently questioned.

It is much harder to do so in Great Britain, for example, where this "special role of the working class" is the daily headache of the Tories, and also of the Labour Party leaders themselves. Or in France and Italy, where the strength of the Communist Parties is closely connected precisely with their ability to use and abuse "the special role of the working class." Or in almost any other European country, where the working class is well organized as a class. Or even in leading countries of Asia and Latin America, where working class-based forces play prominent roles out of all proportion to the size of the class.

In this respect, it is the U.S. which is "out of step," which is the exception to the rule; and while American bourgeois ideologists may be grateful for this exceptional position, they have no license to deny the rule.

The "rule" is that all over the world, organized working class struggle is inextricably bound up with every effort toward freedom and human emancipation. Where the working class has been defeated, democracy and progress and humanity have been defeated, too. Where the forces of freedom have fought, in Hungary 1956, as in capitalist Europe, it is the working class forces that have been in the van.

There is no other sector of society of which this or anything like it can be said--not the middle class, not the intellectuals, not the "educated classes," not the students, not the "managers," not anyone else except the organized working class, for good or ill.

What is the "advantage" which the working class possesses, willy nilly, by virtue of the terms of its own existence under capitalism? Here in outline form are the special characteristics inherent in a social class whose individual human components are (remember) no better or worse than the rest.

1) The conditions of life of the working class lead it to organize in the first place—and most solidly as a homogeneous movement.

There is, of course, one other class which rivals the working class in this respect: the capitalists themselves, whose own class consciousness and sense of class solidarity are ever-present models for the workers.

Never has a predominantly agrarian population (farmers or peasants) been able to duplicate the organizational achievements of the working class. The difference is no reflection on the individual farmer. By terms of their life, they live in atomized groups which stress self-sufficiency, separateness, reliance on individual effort; they are not thrown together in crowds and subjected to simultaneous stresses in the heat of social struggles as are workers.

Workers are taught organization not by superior intelligence or outside agitators, but by the capitalists themselves. They are organized on the assembly lines, in the factory gangs, in shifts, in work teams, in the division of labor of capitalism itself. Capitalism cannot live without "organizing" its workers, teaching them the virtues of working together, therefore of solidarity.

It teaches discipline. It enforces the centralization of effort. It hammers home every day the advantages of pooled work, and the subordination of individual self-interest to the needs of a group.

It does not teach this lesson equally to all workers: it is plainer for assembly-line workers in the mass-production industries than (say) for an office secretary who takes dictation from a personal boss, who works with a boss rather than with fellow workers. This is intended only as a simple example of the different degrees of "education" which capitalism's conditions grant to different kinds of workers. This fact links up also with the social views which arise among these different strata of workers--simply on the basis of the first point: class organization.

2) The interests of workers, as a solidarized group organized by capitalism, lead them to struggle.

It must be emphasized that this often takes place quite apart from the conscious desires of and wishes of the labor leaders themselves. Labor leaders, risen from the ranks of lowly workers and aspiring to be accepted as respectable and responsible members of bourgeois society, often want to substitute pleasant and friendly conferences with management for any kind of conflict. Having freed themselves from the conditions of existence to which the mass of workers are condemned, they tend to become "bourgeoisified'; they want to integrate into the ruling class, or at least find as respectable a niche there as a corporation lawyer.

And indeed they could do so (so many do!) if not for the fact that it is the working class they are standing on in order to reach so high. For the working class needs representatives in order to oppose the bosses" interests; but the bosses accept the friendship of these labor leaders only insofar as they "behave." From below these bourgeoisified bureaucrats, there always arises the pressure of mass demands, the unslakable needs of the workers which cannot be wished away with fine talk about class collaboration, the aspirations streaming up from the depths of the class, demanding "delivery of the goods."

Some bureaucrats continue their precarious balancing act for substantial periods, in "normal" times of class quiet, particularly, as everybody knows; but even the most conservative and most bourgeoisified union leader must to some extent satisfy the class needs of his constituent base, or else. This is in the worst case, of course, and there are not a few such "worst" cases in the society-corrupted labor bureaucracy of this country. But whether timidly or militantly, consistently or hesitantly, competently or crudely, even the conservative union leader who does not "believe" in class struggle must be its instrument, to the extent that he functions as a labor leader at all.

3) The direction of the workers' organized struggle inevitably tends to be counter to capitalism—or, more finely, this struggle always tends to go outside the capitalist framework of institutions and ideas.

Steadily the labor movement's insistence on social responsibility for all aspects of life comes in conflict with the capitalist insistence on the rights of private property. For the essence of capitalist private-property relations is that this whole area of man's life--the economic sphere--is to be withdrawn from the rule of social responsibility, and is to be ruled by the unilateral power of capital as its birthright.

Capitalism has been forced into many compromises in this respect, as is well known--mainly this one, that (a) the state is accorded power to intervene as representative of "society" provided (b) that the associated capitalist class retain full control of the intervening state. (This is the process of "stratification" under capitalism in a nutshell.) But whatever the compromises, the working-class movement can never be satisfied--not even the undeveloped union-conscious labor movement of this country.

More militant unions have raised demands like trade-union intervention in the setting of prices or in peering over the capitalist's books to check their profit. In periods of intense class struggle, sit-downers have taken over the factories without a qualm over the rights of private property. The tendency of the unions in politics is to support social controls all the way down the line--over offshore oil, natural gas, prices, health insurance, etc.--in the name of social responsibility vs. private property. Insofar as this support of "stratification" takes place without concomitant insistence on control by a socialized democracy, this is indeed a contribution to the bureaucratization of capitalism rather than its democratization. But given a socialist framework, it is this insistence on social responsibility vs. private property which is the germ of the labor movement's inherent and ineradicable "creeping socialism."

The intuition of the reactionaries is not altogether baseless in this respect, though often exaggerated and viciously directed. Even Samuel Gompers used to argue that his simple slogan of "more!" for the labor movement was a more "revolutionary" slogan than the socialists'." At any rate, it is true that, insofar as labor presses for "more" out of the economic pie even when this is incompatible with capitalist needs--insofar as labor presses for "more" social responsibility and less rule by private profit--insofar as labor presses in this direction without drawing back when the capitalists yell too violently--to this extent labor drives the logic of its own existence outside the bounds of the capitalist framework, and tends to explode it.

Of course, we socialists would maintain, and experience shows, that this does not happen except when the working class movement grows up to adopting socialist leadership and program; but all we are stressing in the present connection is that the class conditions and needs and interests of the workers drive their organized movement, in the course of its struggle, right up against the bounds of the capitalist system.

4) The conditions and interests of the working class not only push it toward organization, toward struggle, and in a direction counter to capitalism, but also lead to special emphasis on a courage and boldness and militancy.

This is not true of any other group in society--only of individuals from other classes, who may decide to throw in their lot with the working-class struggle. It is enlightening, for example, to study the type of political program commonly adopted by non-working-class parties which set out to express protest: radical peasant parties, or urban middle-class reform parties, or farmers" parties in the US.

Peasant parties most typically stop well short of proposing the abolition of capitalism, confining themselves to proposals for improving their class" lot in ways compatible with the rule of private property; for the peasant is a very tenacious small private-property holder himself and does not easily see beyond this class limitation. In a different kind of case, as in the Nazi appeal to middle-class elements, a kind of pseudo-anti-capitalism may be patched up by directing slogans against bank capital as distinct from "good" productive capital; or, as in the case of Henry Wallace's program, supporting "progressive" capitalists against "reactionary" capitalists.

But what is noteworthy is this: only in the case of working-class parties, all over the world, does the program and goal of the movement turn fast or slow towards a basic assault on the fundamentals of the capitalist system itself.

Obviously most Americans will not consider that this is a good thing! But the fact itself is what we point to, as illuminating the "special role of the working class," for the benefit of Americans who cannot see that the working class as a class does play any special role whatsoever.

Now at first blush this may seem to be in contradiction with our earlier statements that workers are not necessarily personally "better" in any sense. Are we now saying that workers are braver and bolder, etc.?

Only with the same qualifications previously explained. We are talking about their potentialities as an organized class--plus, perhaps, for many individuals, whatever carryover takes place from organized behavior as a result of education in struggle and conditioning in life situation. But it is the class behavior we are interested in.

Stereotypes may be bad, but class "stereotypes" contain more than a kernel of truth. Thus, there is the "Timid Professor." We have known many professors who were not at all personally timid; yet the sweeping stereotype contains truth about the impact of academic life and its pressures upon the social psychology of professors.

In his White Collar, a study of the middle class in America, C. Wright Mills (a non-timid professor) drew on a generalized picture of the new middle class which is relevant here. They are the "rearguarders," says Mills, waiting for someone else to move. As a group they have no cohesion, but are on sale to the highest bidder or the most likely winner. "They have no steady discontent or responsible struggle with the conditions of their lives. For discontent of this sort requires imagination, even a little vision; and the responsible struggle requires leadership." As individuals with private positions (Mills continues) "they hesitate, confused and vacillating in their opinions, unfocused and discontinuous in their actions...they have no target on which to focus their worry and distrust. They may be politically irritable, but they have no political passion. They are a chorus, too afraid to grumble, too hysterical in their applause." "In the short run," he concludes, "they follow the panicky way of prestige; in the long run they follow the ways of power.'

This scathing portrait is a picture of a social class, not an insult against middle-class individuals, just as we have been discussing the social potentialities of a class and not "idealizing" workers.

But surely, realizing the truth of this portrait, one can see why middle-class groups simply cannot work up the dynamic drive which is necessary before one can be "courageous and bold and militant."

Take a simple model: A factory worker on a picket line can and often does abuse entering scabs and may even need to be restrained from physical attack; he is not constrained by notions of bourgeois respectability, even though he may be "respectable" and "bourgeois" on normal occasions. He is, in fact, more alienated from class society, no matter what he thinks, or how he thinks. But now go along the scale of workers up (or down) toward more and more "respectable" white-collar workers and employees, to office employees, to bank tellers, to fashion-house fitters, to...college professors. And try to imagine them yelling at scabs on a picket line.

We use this example only as a handy and visualizable token of what is involved: the dynamism of the class in its organized struggle for "something better." History provides a better record--the record of the working class in far more crucial situations than mere strikes: records of the heights of valor and self-sacrifice that have been reached by unknown workers, not named heroes, in revolutionary struggles. But these things are not visualizable for the average American, who after all is himself the product of a society dominated by middle-class mediocrity.

Whatever a historian may say about the role of force in revolutions, it is a Marxist principle that social revolutions are not made by bullets. This is a caricature of socialist revolution spread by certain types of professors. The Marxist socialist believes that when the working class, and its associated allies from other sections of the people, are in their massed majority ready for the abolition of capitalism, it is their social power which will determine the result in the last analysis.

The social power of the class depends not only on its numbers. It depends also on its homogeneity and organizability, as we have discussed--its striking power. It also depends on the indispensibility of the services which it performs in keeping the society's work going.

No other class has its hands so closely on the basic work without which the system grinds to a halt. Not a wheel can turn without them. No other class can precipitate a social crisis by the deliberate decision of its organized cadres as in a large-scale strike. When the working class goes into battle, all of society is embroiled, for all depends on it. Every time the working class stirs, the rest of society quivers. Yet there is debate over its "special role."

After all of the above, there is still a deeper "why" to be asked, a question that goes behind all of the points we have made up to now. Within the confines of this article we can only point to it.

In the last analysis, the "rearguard" character of the middle classes, which Mills pointed to, reflects their political and social blind alley. They cannot give society a lead because there is no social program which effectively corresponds to the special interests of the middle classes. From the conditions of their existence arises no pointer to a way out for all of society.

In contrast, the working class, as the bottom layer of all classes, cannot even stir without pointing to a program, even when it itself rejects it: the abolition of capitalism, its class antagonist, and the assumption of social responsibility by the people democratically organized, regardless of private profit.

At bottom, it is because the interests of the working class, implicit in its struggles, point to a program for basic transformation and reconstruction of society, that this class is pushed to take a vanguard role in every struggle for freedom and emancipation.

WE NEED hardly spend much space affirming how cognizant we are of how often the working class and its interests have been deceived and betrayed by its enemies and false friends. The history of capitalism, from one point of view, is nothing but a history of continued duping of the working class. In fact, deception of the working class is one of the most important conditions for the maintenance of capitalism or any other exploitative system.

It is not really necessary for us to learn all about this from critics who like to argue that socialist "faith" in the working class is misplaced. It is hardly necessary for us to be reminded, also, that today in good part the Communist Parties live by their ability to dupe and deceive the working class in countries like France and Italy. The battle for socialist democracy against both capitalism and Stalinism can even be summed up as the battle to free the working class from its deception by each of these class enemies.

But this is a battle which, by definition, is won as soon as the workers are "undeceived." It is meanwhile a downright irrelevancy in this connection for critics to tell us, as they do regularly, that because the working class has so long been deceived and betrayed, we must conclude that it is hopeless.

We point out only this: It is the working class that is crucial for reaction to deceive, not the middle classes or any of the "rearguarders."

The socialist revolution, once observed Rosa Luxemburg, is a war in which there are necessarily a continuous series of "defeats" followed by only one victory. Nothing can be guaranteed, of course, except the honor and dignity of fighting for a new and better world, rather than the vileness of adapting one's mind and heart to a vile one. We guarantee to no one that the working class is predestined to "behave according to our blueprints" even if we sit by in interested passivity to see whether it carries out its "mission." We offer only a road of struggle and a choice of allies in the only war worth fighting, the battle for a socialist democracy against the rival world blocs of war and exploitation.

Socialism Needs Democracy, Democracy Needs Socialism

By Steve Leigh

The authentic Marxist tradition has always stressed that democracy is fundamental to socialism. Marx defined socialism as the “self-emancipation of the working class.” In the Communist Manifesto, he and Engels said that the first step on the road to socialism and then communism was the need to “win the battle of democracy.”

The fight for socialism is fundamentally about democratically transforming the relations of production and all other social relations. No legislation can grant this transformation. Workers can only achieve power when they take power. This was the essence of what Eugene Debs meant by his classic statement: “If I could lead you into the Promised Land, I would not, because if I could lead you in, someone else could lead you out.” Rosa Luxemburg reinforced this point: “Where the chains of capitalism are forged, there they must be broken.”

The fight for socialism requires workers' democracy

As Marx explained, revolution is needed for two reasons: Those with power will not give it up without a fight; and revolution is the only way workers can become “fit to rule.” It is the only way they can rid themselves of “the muck of ages” (racism, sexism, nationalism, homophobia, and all other forms of bigotry) and win the confidence to run society.

Unfortunately, this link between revolutionary democracy and socialism is rejected by Stalinism and its various offshoots — Maoism, Castroism, and related Third World nationalism. This has undermined the appeal of Marxism across the world. Many workers have looked at the elite dictatorships claiming the mantle of socialism and said, “If that is socialism, I don’t want it.”

Even the collapse of Stalinist states from 1989 onward has not killed off the Stalinist distortion of Marxism. Many young people in the U.S. rightly want to oppose U.S. imperialism and capitalism. They turn to what they think are its enemies: the remnants of the Eastern Bloc and its allies. They become campists, extolling the virtues of the supposedly anti-U.S. camp — China, Russia, Iran, and Assad’s Syria. In many cases this leads them back to support of the gravedigger of the Russian Revolution, Stalin himself.

This is a tragedy and something that actual Marxists must continually confront. We need to explain over and over the direct connection of democracy and socialism. This is a difficult but necessary road, and there are no shortcuts. We cannot sneak someone into power and achieve what we want. We cannot lie to workers or go behind their backs. We cannot move toward socialism by bureaucratically manipulating a union or a coalition to achieve the political stance we want. We cannot substitute ourselves or any would-be leader for the working class. We cannot win things for workers without workers’ direct involvement.

This can cause frustration. Revolutionaries cannot will a revolution into existence. The revolution will come when the working class is ready for it, not when we wish it. Obviously, we need to do everything we can to build the level of struggle and lay the basis for successful revolution. Our main contribution is to build first an organization of revolutionaries, and finally a revolutionary party that can help convince workers to take power in a revolutionary upsurge. Organized revolutionaries do not make the revolution, but they are necessary to make it successful.

Capitalism is undemocratic in its essence

There is another link between democracy and socialism in a negative sense. Capitalism is undemocratic. It is founded on the legal right of the capitalist to control work and the worker. Workplaces are not democracies.

Beyond this, capitalists use their economic power to control government. As Engels said, the economic rulers also become the political ruling class.

Even the limited democratic rights that workers have under capitalism are truncated. Citizens are sometimes allowed to vote on public policy. Money has a large role to play in what even gets on the ballot. The measures that people can vote on are limited by economic conditions. Often the choice before voters is something along the lines of, “Tax yourselves and lower your living standards even more or don’t provide funding for schools.” These limited choices are no real choices at all. There is usually no choice on the ballot to tax the rich to provide social services. Even if there is, the money-backed message is, “If you tax the rich, you’ll kill jobs and put yourself out of work”.

This applies to contests over representatives as well. Too often elitist liberals chastise workers for voting against their interests by which they mean voting against Democrats. In fact, neither Republicans nor Democrats represent the interests of workers. In many periods, and certainly now on many issues, the vast majority are further to the left than the politicians.

Yet, this is not always true. Capitalism distorts the opinions of workers, as it does of the population generally. Calling for power to the working class does not necessarily mean endorsing the current opinion of workers. However, workers struggling for democratic power and for democratic rights under capitalism is part of the process of workers becoming “fit to rule”. Socialists may oppose and organize against reactionary positions held by sections of the working class, but we are always for expansion of workers’ rights and power.

The only real democracy is created when the vast majority has full control of the economy and thus has access to all technologically possible options. This can only happen after workers seize power in a socialist revolution.

Workers’ democracy and the transition to socialism

Beyond this, there is an even deeper interactive relation between democracy and socialism.

A working-class socialist revolution will destroy the bourgeois state apparatus and replace it with the democratic institutions run directly by the working class. Marx and Engels began to lay this out in The Communist Manifesto and elaborated on it in The Civil War in France. Lenin clearly explained this in State and Revolution.

Workers’ democracy is the necessary first step on the road to socialism. Without it the working class cannot concentrate the power needed to transform the economy toward socialism. Workers need political power to take the capital from the capitalists and begin to plan the economy for human needs.

As an aside, this means taking all political power, including the right to vote, from the remaining exploiters. Diluting workers’ power with internal sabotage by the enemy class would retard the transformation to socialism.

Yet, democracy at this stage is limited. Until workers have taken power throughout the world, options facing the working class are constrained. Against its best wishes, the workers’ state must defend itself. It must put a priority on weapons rather than human needs. It is forced to compete with other states for survival. The law of value still imposes itself on the workers’ state. This means that it must prioritize bourgeois efficiency.

To achieve fuller democracy, with more choices of priorities, the economy must be transformed in a socialist direction. As the workers’ revolution spreads internationally, the need for military defense lessens. The competition between states is replaced by cooperation. The law of value begins to lose its grip.

Only when the revolution has spread internationally can the workers’ states have all the choices available to the current state of technology. Only then can it have the fullest possible democracy. The transformation to socialism is a long and complicated process. There will be setbacks. The advance will be in a spiral rather than a straight line.

At the end of the process, what Marx called the higher stage of communism, the need for a repressive apparatus will be gone. When classes have disappeared, there will be no need to keep the capitalist class in check. This is what Marx, Engels and Lenin called the “withering away of the state”.

With the withering away of the state comes the withering away of repressive political democracy — the need for one class to impose its will on another class. However, there will always be the need for economic democracy. The whole population will still need to determine economic plans.

In summary, the relationship of democracy and the transition to socialism is this: workers’ democracy is essential to the transformation of capitalism into communism. Every advance towards socialism increases the strength of workers’ democracy, giving the working class more and more choices. Each positive exercise of these choices moves the society closer to socialism and further strengthens democracy. The full achievement of the highest stage of communism eliminates classes and therefore the need for democratic repression of hostile classes. The workers’ state withers away. With no more hostile classes, society democratically manages its economy without state repression.

Socialists and the rank-and-file strategy

By Sean Petty

In the last year, we have seen some very important developments in the labor movement in the U.S.

Last spring, the teachers of West Virginia, 55 counties strong, kicked off an actual strike wave, the first of its kind in the U.S. in decades. These “red state” teachers’ strikes were led, first and foremost, by pockets of militant rank-and-file teachers who organized a struggle that pushed past anti-union laws and the conservatism of their own union leaderships to directly confront their state governments’ latest criminal devaluation of teachers’ and students’ lives.

A short time later, the U.S. Supreme Court, as expected, dealt the single largest legal blow to unions since the Taft-Hartley Act of 1947, with the Janus v. AFSCME decision, which overturns the requirement that workers in public-sector workers covered by a union contract but not members of the union pay contributions.

Without an ongoing rank-and-file upsurge in the public sector, this decision will fundamentally and critically weaken unions’ institutional ability to protect workers’ wages and working conditions. It will also weaken public sector unions’ ability to fight against the ongoing dismantling of public services — whether in education, health care or the myriad of other necessary social services.

So it is a very good time for socialists and other union and left activists to take a step back and take a deeper look at some of the structures and dynamics of unions under capitalism.

I want to articulate some theoretical guideposts for how we in the ISO, other socialist and radical left activists, and fellow union militants can navigate important questions about how to best rebuild and extend working-class power in this country.

Unions are the main organizational forms resulting from working people’s perpetual struggle to have some control over some of the most important aspects of our lives — namely, our economic well-being and how we are treated at work, the place where we spend a significant amount of our waking lives.

The fight for unions can involve both economic and political demands — meaning the fight for immediate economic improvements from employers, as well as, if we’re lucky, demands on the state to increase rights on the job, tackle particular attacks against sections of workers, and create better conditions in our communities.

Unions under capitalism are a self-limited project, meaning that they exist because socialism doesn’t. They are ultimately necessary because of the exploitative and oppressive working conditions that are necessary for capitalism to exist.

Therefore, unions as institutions don’t have an inherent interest in uprooting the social relations of capitalism. In fact, their existence is built on them. They exist to negotiate the conditions of exploitation and oppression, not to end their root causes. They are organizations designed and developed to reform present conditions.

It takes conscious socialist political organization to overcome the limitations inherent in trade union organization and ultimately push beyond the see-saw of organizing for and winning better conditions, only to have them taken away or conceded years later.

Using strikes and other forms of mass collective working-class struggle and organization to confront capital and the state are the only ways that working people can ultimately shift the balance of power permanently in our favor.

Recognizing this does not mean that socialists should be dismissive of unions in any way. We know that unions are also some of the important schools of struggle, organization and power for working people.

Even smaller battles short of strikes, both inside and outside the workplace, can mightily help advance class consciousness and create the conditions for the development of revolutionary socialist consciousness and organization.

Union struggles can bring many things to light for us and our co-workers — first of all, the true colors of our bosses and our governments. They force us to think about what ideas we need — and what ideas we have to combat — to truly bind ourselves together as working people in order to be stronger and more successful.

Unions have been developing under capitalism since its birth. They now exist in most countries and have for some time.

Most unions, especially in more developed countries, have developed elaborate structures, with full-time officials, elected leaders and paid staff members. Over time, these structures — because of their degree of removal from the life of the rank and file, and because of pressure from capital — become ossified and bureaucratized, meaning they develop and take on interests and a life of their own apart from the objective interests of the rank and file.

How socialists understand this bureaucracy factors heavily into how we develop strategies within union work. To quote British socialists Tony Cliff and Donny Gluckstein, in the second chapter of their book Marxism and Trade Union Struggle: The General Strike of 1926:

The trade union bureaucracy is a distinct, basically conservative, social formation. Like the God Janus it presents two faces: it balances between the employers and the workers. It holds back and controls workers’ struggle, but it has a vital interest not to push the collaboration with employers and state to a point where it makes the unions completely impotent. For the official is not an independent arbitrator. If the union fails entirely to articulate members’ grievances, this will lead eventually either to effective internal challenges to the leadership, or to membership apathy and organizational disintegration, with members moving to a rival union. If the union bureaucracy strays too far into the bourgeois camp it will lose its base. The bureaucracy has an interest in preserving the union organization which is the source of their income and their social status.

There are a number of different ideas to unpack from this passage.

For starters, because of its profound contradictions, nothing is static under capitalism — everything is in constant motion. The voracious needs of capital to constantly increase profits and economic growth clash with the constant struggles and degrees of organization of working people who are trying to fight against this organized theft.

From the standpoint of the bureaucracy, the goal of unions is their continued existence, so this layer is compelled to try and balance this contradiction. Sometimes, this means waging a fight, which involves agitation and increasing expectations and organization. But most of the time, it means dodging a fight, which involves organized passivity, willful ignorance, lowering expectations and even undermining rank-and-file organization.

The polish revolutionary Marxist Rosa Luxemburg was one of the first to recognize the character of this new layer when unions apparatuses became more established in Germany in the 1890s. She wrote in The Mass Strike:

[T]he naturally restricted horizon which is bound up with disconnected economic struggles in a peaceful period, leads only too easily, amongst trade-union officials, to bureaucratism and a certain narrowness of outlook. Both, however, express themselves in...the overvaluation of the organization, which from a means has gradually been changed into an end in itself, a precious thing, to which the interests of the struggles should be subordinated. From this also comes that openly admitted need for peace which shrinks from great risks and presumed dangers to the stability of the trade unions, and further, the overvaluation of the trade-union method of struggle itself, its prospects and its successes. (emphasis added)

We have only to look at the massive bureaucracies of unions like the International Brotherhood of Teamsters or Service Employees International Union to know that there’s not much distance between German in 1890 and the United States in 2018 in this regard.

Luxemburg’s recognition of the bureaucracy’s “narrowness of outlook” is also singling out another conservative influence on trade union officials: that they are compelled to represent the interests of a politically heterogeneous working class in a given workplace or sector of the economy. This creates a political framework that skews their approach toward the lowest common denominator of working-class consciousness in a given time and place.

In addition, professional trade unionists, especially at the higher levels, are at least a significant step removed from the lives of the workers they represent. They are not subject to the same oppression of supervisors, they usually make significantly more money, and they are immune from layoffs and other threats to job security that are routine for the rank and file.

Their degree of distance from rank-and-file life, their role negotiating the terms of exploitation, and their actual lack of control over economic conditions means they take on the characteristics of the middle class under capitalism, which includes attempting temper its central contradictions and vacillating in the wider class contest.

This is just a starting point. There is wide variation in the character of trade unions and among officials within particular trade unions across time and space. But they all operate under this broader dynamic.

There are officials with more left-wing or more right-wing politics. There are smaller union locals where the officials and union structure have a closer connection to rank-and-file interests and/or are more democratically controlled.

And there are important differences between full-time elected officials, elected officials who maintain rank-and-file jobs, senior staff, lower-level staff, etc.

But as Cliff and Gluckstein write:

[T]he bureaucracy is not homogeneous. Union officials in different industries find themselves under varying pressures from below and above. Again, ideologically, union officials are not the same. The division between left- and right-wing union officials is significant. Splits in the bureaucracy — between unions or within a union — can weaken its conservative influence. The fundamental fact, however, overriding all differences between bureaucrats, is that they belong to a conservative social stratum, which, especially at times of radical crisis — as in the 1926 General Strike — makes the differences between left- and right-wing bureaucrats secondary. At such times all sections of the bureaucracy seek to curb and control workers’ militancy.

As long as there have been unions for any length of time, they have developed bureaucracies. And as long as there have been bureaucracies within unions, socialists and revolutionaries have developed strategies to deal with them.

There are at least four major trends in how the left has approached this question, and I will try to touch on each in turn: syndicalism, red unionism, permeationism and the rank-and-file strategy.

Syndicalism is an idea that is rooted in revolutionary working-class anarchism that had significant influence at the turn of the 20th century in places like Russia, Spain and the U.S., among other places. Here in the U.S., syndicalism was organizationally expressed by an incredibly important radical union movement called the Industrial Workers of the World — the IWW, or the Wobblies.

The IWW’s approach to the conservatism of bureaucracy was simply not to have one. The Wobblies organized massive, heroic strikes and trained some of the best working-class radical organizers of the early 20th century. But they intentionally established no formal union structures or permanent contracts between employers and workers.

This solved one problem, but created another. As soon as the level of militancy among rank-and-file activist died down and the IWW left town, the employers quickly regrouped and immediately clawed back most of the gains made in previous strikes.

Red unionism was another response to the political conservatism of union bureaucracies.

This was a policy pushed by different revolutionary socialist and anarchist groups, most famously by the Communist International from 1920 to 1923, when it established the Red International of Labor Unions, and then later, for very different and fundamentally flawed purposes, by the Stalinized Comintern after 1928, during the so-called “Third Period” where all Communist Parties (CP) internationally were directed to pursue a policy of dual unionism.

Syndicalism and revolutionary or dual unionism are two sides of the same coin: They involve abstention from and avoidance of the messy and challenging world of building consistent socialist rank-and-file organization within a broader union movement.

PERMEATIONISM IS a more straightforward idea that is the default practice of reformist socialists throughout the late 19th century up to the present day. But it was also utilized by the Comintern between 1923 and 1928, and then imposed, after the disastrous dual unionism of the Third Period, by Stalin after 1933 and 1935 with the introduction of the Popular Front strategy.

I can’t go into an extended discussion of the Popular Front strategy, but suffice is to say that it was implemented directly out of the needs of Stalin’s foreign policy to build an international alliance with capitalist governments against Nazi Germany.

In the case of the U.S., this meant the Communist Party emphasizing the primacy of building an alliance with the Roosevelt administration and the newly formed industrial union movement called the Congress of Industrial Organizations, or CIO.

Permeationism simply means having socialists insinuate themselves within the union bureaucracy in order to try and shape its politics and practice.

This became the default strategy of the social democratic-led unions within the Second International because there was no contradiction between the vision of reforming existing capitalism through parliamentary means and economic advancement through unions. The bureaucracies of unions were well suited to the idea of focusing uniformly on reforms and developing or winning over reformist organizations to do so.

In Europe, Latin America and elsewhere, unions and labor-based reformist political parties went hand in hand. In the U.S. prior to the Popular Front period, this had an expression early on in the Socialist Party, which had trade unionists who did electoral work within unions.

In the mid-1930s, as Franklin Delano Roosevelt began to implement the New Deal and the CIO was on the rise, the CP oriented heavily on taking the CIO’s top leadership positions, achieving “left-hand man” status to the three leaders of the CIO: John Lewis, Sidney Hillman and Philip Murray. CP members or former members were the chief counsel and publicity director for the entire CIO.

More pervasively, the CP oriented on taking staff jobs in individual CIO unions, winning the leaderships and staffs of CIO locals, with the goal of helping to organize the upsurge in unionism and binding that to the left wing of the Democratic Party.

The CP still had thousands of rank-and-file militants who did amazing work, but ultimately, that work was circumscribed by the larger goals of the Popular Front — and when the Second World War came along, subordinated to winning the war.

The CP and CP union activists supported and enforced the no-strike pledge during the war, defended state repression of Trotskyist labor militants, abstained from important struggles for racial justice and supported Japanese internment. Then, after the war, they were purged out of the labor movement by the McCarthyite witch hunts, as the U.S. ruling class shifted toward the Cold War.

Len De Caux, the former CP member who was publicity director of the CIO, gave an ironically apt description of what the CIO would became in the postwar period after the defeat of the CP’s permeationist strategy, as quoted in Kim Moody’s essay “The Rank and File Strategy”:

Once the CIO won all that capitalism would allow it...sit-downs and mass struggle gave way to union administration, dues collection, labor board briefs, detailed negotiations. The swivel-chair tribe began its own long-lasting sit-down in union office. This tribe rode to office on the broad shoulders of Lewis and the backs of the agitators, the militants, the reds. Once they arrived they turned — dutifully, patriotically, devoutly — to kick in the face those on whom and over whom they had scrambled.

Permeationism continues to this day as a de facto strategy of groups that are the inheritors, in one way or another, of the Socialist and Communist Parties. The modern U.S. labor bureaucracy is chock-full of former and current members of the Communist Party, Maoist groups and social democratic organizations — some of whom have made their peace with the system and others who continue to fight, even if they tend to be boxed in and accept the constraints of their positions at times.

What these left organizations share is a uniform strategy of seeking top-down reform within unions, a more militant business unionism and left realignment within the Democratic Party.

The rank-and-file strategy, by contrast, flows from the vision of the revolutionary socialist transformation of society, a project long abandoned by the CP and never adopted by social democracy.

It is a strategy for how socialists orient within the labor movement and how they build socialist politics and organization within it.

This should first be distinguished from a broader conception of a rank-and-file strategy to rebuild the labor movement. The two are related, but nonetheless distinct.

Many non-socialist union militants are clear that any change in the labor movement must come from the shop floor. They are correct, but the strategy they project within the labor left in the U.S — as exemplified by conferences and projects such as Labor Notes, the Center for Workers Democracy and others — has relatively little to do with building socialist organization directly.

Our more specific conception of the rank-and-file strategy is rooted in an early 1920s project of the Communist Party called the Trade Union Educational League (TUEL).

Led by former syndicalist William Z. Foster, the strategy was based on an uptick in strikes allowing for revolutionary socialists to attempt to build a broad socialist current within the union movement, using socialist politics, workplace struggle, and both rank-and-file and socialist organization.

This strategic orientation was revived most famously by Trotskyists in Minneapolis, who not only helped lead one of the three major general strikes of 1934, but built socialist politics and organization while doing so, which then helped them advance class power within the regional trucking industry.

One of the Trotskyist leaders in Minneapolis, Farrell Dobbs, wrote two important books on the period, Teamster Rebellion and Teamster Power, which provide an invaluable case study in the successful implementation of a socialist rank-and-file strategy.

The socialist rank-and-file strategy was carried through on a much smaller scale throughout the 1950s and early 1960s, mainly through individual socialist militants and the Trotskyist group, the Workers Party, which was the loose predecessor of the International Socialists (IS).

One of that period’s most prominent and successful revolutionary socialist organizers, Stan Weir, has a great book of essays called Single Jack Solidarity, which details the struggles of that era.

Moving into the 1970s, a major rank-and-file upsurge began to take shape as capital began to embark on what is now known as the neoliberal period. This was marked by production speedups and increasing attacks on what remained of shop-floor organization, combined with the near-universal collaboration between big labor and big business.

The International Socialists participated in advancing this rank-and-file rebellion, which is detailed well in the books Rebel Rank and File, edited by Aaron Brenner, Robert Brenner and Cal Winslow, and Rank-and-File Rebellion: Teamsters for a Democratic Union.

The rise and fall of these struggles produced a tension in how socialists should relate to this upsurge.

The IS — drawing from the experience of TUEL, the Minneapolis Teamsters, the Workers Party and the Black-led Revolutionary Union Movements of the late 1960s — initiated or were involved in a number of rank-and-file formations in the Teamsters, United Steel Workers, United Auto Workers and several other unions.

These formations differed in their character, but the IS attempted to develop and win a politically left and socialist orientation in many of these formations.

A similar development was already underway in Britain, where the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) also succeeded in developing a socialist current within the emerging Shop Stewards Movement.

The SWP systematically recruited radicalizing workers and built factory branches that then helped to shape the broader Shop Stewards Movement. This was one significant part of a broader approach to building socialist organization in Britain.

Facing a much greater challenge, given the absolute segregation of the socialist and labor movements from each other, the IS, by and large, chose a strategy of industrialization, which meant that the vast majority of activist work by the early to mid-1970s was within unions, carried out by younger radicals who had hired in to those industries.

A debate emerged within the IS about how open revolutionary socialists should be within this work and how exactly to introduce politics within workplace organizing.

This, among other issues, led to a split in the IS that resulted in the founding of the International Socialist Organization — which favored a more explicit and open approach to being socialists in the union movement.

The remnants of the IS was regrouped with other socialist organizations in a new group called Solidarity. The group retained the IS’s version of the rank-and-file strategy and continued to carry out the Labor Notes project, named after the labor column in the IS’s socialist newspaper Workers Power.

When the momentum of the rank-and-file movements was brought to an abrupt halt by the onset of recession in the late 1970s and early 1980s, radicals remaining in union work found themselves increasingly surrounded by a conservatizing and demobilized working class in the Reagan era — which led to even more intense pressure to play down explicitly socialist politics.

Kim Moody argues in his essay on the rank-and-file strategy that a higher level of class consciousness than exists in the U.S. is required as a precondition for rebuilding a socialist current within unions. Following this lead, many remaining socialists in unions operated on a stage-based approach of building rank-and-file union organization as a necessary step toward a later project of building socialist organization.

The ISO attempted to develop an approach that stressed the centrality of politics, even if the audience for those politics was temporarily shrinking. In the weakened state of the left in the 1980s, the ISO placed a premium on rebuilding revolutionary socialist cadre, and the prospects for that project did not lie primarily in the union movement during that period.

Even so, the ISO carried out important union work as socialists, organizing both inside and outside the workplace — helping to organize unions and build union struggles as open socialists throughout the 1980s and up to the present period.

These debates and divergent strategies continue today. The main difference now, however, is that socialists are on a much stronger footing as the U.S. is experiences the beginnings of most widespread political radicalization since the 1960s. The new radicalization is more class-conscious and socialist-oriented, with the rise of groups like the DSA.

In fits and starts, this radicalization has found an expression in union work, with the Wisconsin Capitol occupation, the Chicago teachers’ strike and, most recently, the “red state” teachers rebellion being prime examples.

The ISO’s work in teachers’ unions, health care and a number of other important areas, combined with political and organizational developments of the labor left, offer new opportunities for revolutionaries to rebuild a socialist current within unions and the broader working-class movement.

We think the theory and practice of an explicitly socialist rank-and-file strategy is the best way to make sure this happens.

Marxism and Oppression

By Paul D'Amato

Over the last few decades, left-wing activists and academics have by and large rejected Marxism and its emphasis on class and class struggle. In particular, Marxism has been attacked for ignoring or downplaying questions of oppression. The idea that society consists of a series of separate but overlapping “identities” based on things such as gender, race, class, sexual orientation, national identity and cultural practices is now widespread. This view of society is akin to the liberal pluralism we learn in school. Society, so the argument goes, consists of different, sometimes competing “interest groups.” No overarching analysis of society can take all of these “differences” into account and unite them into a coherent framework. Marxism is viewed as unable to deal with oppression because it is concerned only with class exploitation. The views of one feminist author writing in 1979 are still widespread: “Marx never questioned the hierarchical sexual ordering of society.”[1]

Marx is similarly attacked for his supposed lack of attention to racism. To quote one academic:

Ethnic and racial conflicts were not subjects to which Marx gave much close attention. Although Marx acknowledged these types of division in society, he does not appear to have been much interested in explaining their dynamics. Obsessed with a supposedly more fundamental category of socioeconomic identity, namely class, Marx slighted race and did not grant it a place of its own in his historical work. In 1849, in response to the query “What is a Negro slave?” Marx wrote: “A man of the black race. The one explanation is as good as the other... A Negro is a Negro.”[2]

The idea that Marx and Engels ignored or downplayed oppression because they “privileged” class is simply wrong. What they (and Marxists since) have argued is that 1) various oppressions cannot be understood separately from capitalism because capitalism shapes and depends upon oppression for its survival, and 2) the most thoroughgoing struggle against oppression cannot be carried out on the basis of separate struggles of the oppressed, each united across class lines. Such a struggle will always be limited by the narrow interests of bourgeois and middle-class elements within the oppressed group who will seek to limit the scope of the struggle within the confines of capitalism. Only the working class (Black, white, Latino, gay, straight, women, men) has both the collective power and the common interest to fight for complete liberation.

The Marxist tradition

Capitalism is a society based on the exploitation of the many by the few. Because it is founded on massive inequality, it requires various means to oppress and keep down the working class and the poor. The ruling classes of the world know the value of “divide and rule,” both as a means to weaken any opposition against them, and as a means to squeeze more profits from the working class.

The working class is not only an exploited class—it is also an oppressed class. Workers receive worse education, worse housing and worse job opportunities than the sons and daughters of the middle class and the rich. Workers are constantly reminded that they do not possess the intelligence or the capabilities of those above them on the social ladder. Workers are disadvantaged at every step, stressed under financial and family constraints, forced to work in dangerous jobs and, therefore, more likely to suffer from various physical and mental ailments. In turn, they are then forced to accept the poorest quality health care—if they can get it at all.

Racial, sexual, national, linguistic and other oppressions interact with this basic class oppression to produce sections within the working class who are doubly or “specially” oppressed. Marx and Engels were clear that capitalism—a system based upon the exploitation of wage labor for profit—was founded on enslavement and oppression from its beginnings:

The discovery of gold and silver in America, the extirpation, enslavement and entombment in mines of the indigenous population of that continent, the beginnings of the conquest and plunder of India, and the conversion of Africa into a preserve for the commercial hunting of black skins are all things that characterize the dawn of the era of capitalist production. These idyllic proceedings are the chief moments of primitive accumulation.[3]_

The treasures captured outside Europe by undisguised looting, enslavement and murder flowed back to the mother-country and were turned into capital there.[4]_

Direct slavery is as much the pivot upon which our present-day industrialism turns as are machinery, credit, etc. Without slavery there would be no cotton, without cotton there would be no modern industry. It is slavery which has given value to the colonies, it is the colonies which have created world trade, and world trade is the necessary condition of large-scale machine industry.[5]_

In fact the veiled slavery of the wage laborers in Europe needed the unqualified slavery of the New World as its pedestal... Capital comes dripping from head to toe, from every pore, with blood and dirt.[6]_

Everyone accepts the idea that the oppression of slaves was rooted in the class relations of exploitation of that system. Fewer recognize that under capitalism wage slavery is the pivot around which all other inequalities and oppressions turn. Capitalism used racism to justify plunder, conquest and slavery, but as Marx pointed out, it also used racism to divide and rule—to pit one section of the working class against another and thereby blunt class consciousness. Marx developed this idea throughout his works, including these two passages about slavery in the U.S. and England's oppression of Ireland:

In the United States of America, every independent workers' movement was paralyzed as long as slavery disfigured part of the republic. Labor in a white skin cannot emancipate itself where it is branded in a black skin.[7]_

Every industrial and commercial center in England now possesses a working class divided into two hostile camps, English proletarians and Irish proletarians. The ordinary English worker hates the Irish worker as a competitor who lowers his standard of life. In relation to the Irish worker he feels himself a member of the ruling nation and so turns himself into a tool of the aristocrats and capitalists of his country against Ireland, thus strengthening their domination over himself. He cherishes religious, social, and national prejudices against the Irish worker. His attitude toward him is much the same as that of the “poor whites” to the “niggers” in the former slave states of the U.S.A. The Irishman pays him back with interest in his own money. He sees in the English worker at once the accomplice and the stupid tool of the English rule in Ireland. This antagonism is artificially kept alive and intensified by the press, the pulpit, the comic papers, in short, by all the means at the disposal of the ruling classes. This antagonism is the secret of the impotence of the English working class, despite its organization. It is the secret by which the capitalist class maintains its power. And that class is fully aware of it. [Marx's italics] [8]

Marx concluded that part of the key to building a successful workers' movement in England was to win English workers to the idea that Ireland had the right to separate from England. Marx's observations on Ireland became the foundation of Vladimir Lenin's position on the self-determination of oppressed nations—in an era when the world's biggest and most powerful capitalist states fought to carve up the world between themselves. Lenin's arguments against Rosa Luxemburg over Poland's right to self-determination in 1914 have become a cornerstone of the revolutionary Marxist tradition:

Successful struggle against exploitation requires that the proletariat be free of nationalism, and be absolutely neutral, so to speak, in the fight for supremacy that is going on among the bourgeoisie of various nations. If the proletariat of any one nation gives the slightest support to the privileges of “its own” national bourgeoisie, that will inevitably rouse distrust among the proletariat of another nation; it will weaken the international class solidarity of the workers and divide them, to the delight of the bourgeoisie. Repudiation of the right to self-determination or to succession inevitably means, in practice, support for the privileges of the dominant nation.[9]_

Nationalism and combating national oppression, for Marx (and later Lenin) were not at all the same thing. On the contrary, it was the duty of socialists, especially those in the large oppressor nations, to combat all forms of national oppression and inequality precisely in order to break down national divisions in the working class and strengthen their struggle against capitalism. Socialists are for the voluntary, free union of peoples and are therefore in principle opposed to any forced retention of any nation within the borders of another. This is the exact opposite of the anti-Marxist caricature that claims that Marxism “ignores” such divisions as a “diversion” from the class struggle.

Marx and Engels on women's oppression

Marx and Engels rejected outright the idea (upheld by conservatives, but also by some feminists) that the low status of women was an unchanging feature of human existence—fixed for all time by human biology or by the ideas in people's heads. Women's position in society has been conditioned by the particular stage of development of the productive forces of society, and, corresponding to that, the given social relations of a particular society. Women's status in society has always been related to the role they have played in—and in the different forms taken by—the family in history.

Women's status, for example, was very different in preclass societies. Engels describes how in the horticultural society of the Iroquois, women's control over agriculture gave them a far higher status than women in later times. Though there was a sexual division of labor, it did not necessarily confer a dominant role to the men:

The division of labor between the two sexes is determined by causes entirely different from those that determine the status of women in society. Peoples whose women have to work much harder than we would consider proper often have far more real respect for women than our Europeans have of theirs. The social status of the lady of civilization, surrounded by sham homage and estranged from all real work, is socially infinitely lower than that of the hard-working woman of barbarism...[10]_

Women's oppression arose and coincided with the rise of the first class divisions in society:

The first class opposition that appears in history coincides with the development of the antagonism between man and woman in monogamous marriage, and the first class oppression coincides with that of the female sex by the male. Monogamous marriage was a great step forward; nevertheless, together with slavery and private wealth, it opens the period that has lasted until today in which every step forward is also relatively a step backward, in which prosperity and development for some is won through the misery and frustration of others.[11]_

Capitalism does not free women, but it creates the conditions in which women can be liberated. Noting how modern industry in the 19th century was drawing women out of the domestic sphere and into the paid workforce, Marx argued:

However terrible and disgusting the dissolution of the old family ties within the capitalist system may appear, large-scale industry, by assigning an important part in socially organized processes of production, outside the sphere of the domestic economy, to women, young persons and children of both sexes, does nevertheless create a new economic foundation for a higher form of the family and relations between the sexes...[The] fact that the collective working group is composed of individuals of both sexes and all ages must under the appropriate conditions turn into a source of humane development, although in its spontaneously developed, brutal, capitalist form, the system works in the opposite direction, and becomes a pestiferous source of corruption and slavery, since here the worker exists for the process of production, and not the process of production for the worker.[12]_

Women's oppression cannot be seen as something separate or parallel to capitalism—capitalism depends upon the “private” family, on women's roles as housewives and mothers for its survival. As a more contemporary Marxist analysis of women's oppression lays out:

Marxists argue that under capitalism, women's oppression is rooted in “privatized reproduction,” or, in women's role within the nuclear family. In the private family, birthing, child-rearing, and food preparation take place as a “service” to capitalism. “Privatized reproduction” within the nuclear family consists of bearing and raising the next generation of workers for capitalism, and of preparing present-day workers to “reproduce” their labor each day. This function of the family has become essential to the existence of capitalism, as a cheap means of maintaining the labor force.[13]_

Because capitalism knows two tendencies—dependence upon women's unpaid labor in the home and the exploitation of women in the paid labor force—it forces women to bear a double burden of work at home and on the job. Nevertheless, Marx's insight remains valid today: the starting point for women's emancipation is their entry into paid labor—a change which breaks women out of their isolation in the home and gives working-class women the collective strength and confidence—alongside the men of their class—to fight for their rights as both women and workers.

Moreover, the wealth and means of production created by capitalism can be used, if collectively seized and placed under workers' control, to socialize household functions such as cooking, cleaning and childcare in order to liberate women completely. In his draft for the Communist Manifesto, Engels wrote:

It [communist society] will transform the relations between the sexes into a purely private matter which concerns only the persons involved and into which society has no occasion to intervene. It can do this since it does away with private property and educates children on a communal basis, and in this way removes the two bases of traditional marriage, the dependence, rooted in private property, of the woman on the man and of the children on the parents.[14]_

Many years later, the Russian revolutionary Leon Trotsky echoed a similar theme:

The problem of women's emancipation, both material and spiritual, is closely tied to that of the transformation of family life. It is necessary to remove the bars from those confining and suffocating cages into which the present family structure drives women, turning her into a slave, if not a beast of burden. This can be accomplished only through the organization of communal methods of feeding and child-rearing.[15]_

Who benefits from oppression?

What most theories of oppression have in common is the idea that working-class unity is impossible because each group benefits from the oppression of some other group. It is now unquestioningly accepted among feminist academics and many activists, for example, that women's oppression stems from “patriarchy,” loosely defined as a system (more or less independent of time and place) whereby all men benefit by keeping all women down. To cite just one recent example from a recent anthology on feminist theory and politics: “The first theme is that women as a social group are oppressed by men as a social group and that this is the primary oppression for women. Patriarchy is the oppressing structure of male domination.”[16]

Likewise, Black nationalists and academics influenced by “identity” politics tend to view racism as a system where all whites benefit from the oppression of Blacks. The same anthology cited above quotes two Latina feminists: “Racism is societal and institutional. It implies power to implement racist ideology. Women of color do not have such power, but white women are born with it and the greater their economic privilege, the greater their power.”[17]

If class is talked about at all, it is “classism,” that is, how the better-off sections of the oppressed (say, middle-class and rich women) need to learn how to be less elitist so that they can unite in solidarity with their poorer oppressed sisters and brothers. Class is not viewed as a fundamental divide in society, whereby a tiny minority exploit for profit the labor of the majority, but simply as something oppressed groups should recognize in order to overcome any friction inside the movement or organization.

But while it is true that individual workers may hold sexist or racist ideas, it is not at all true that workers benefit from it, even if they think that they do. In fact, when one part of the working class is kept down, it helps the bosses to keep the entire class down. Rather than benefiting from oppression, all workers are hurt by it.

Those who argue that male workers have “power” over women, or that white workers have “power” over Black people, have no idea what real power is. In their focus on some particular group oppression, they think that another group has “power.” That is a moral conception of power. The ruling class has the real power—through its control of production, of resources, of the means of destruction and of the means of disseminating ideas. It uses that power to maintain its ability to exploit and make profits unhindered. Workers' power—that is, their ability to change their circumstances and challenge the system—comes from their collective organization and the confidence they draw from it. Atomized and separate, encouraged to go for each other's throats, workers are powerless. So when a male worker abuses his wife, he is acting not out of power, but out of powerlessness, out of weakness. And when a white worker acts in a racist manner toward a Black worker, the white worker is not expressing their own power, but the power of the system over them. In defeat, workers are most susceptible to the prevailing ruling-class ideas—racist, anti-immigrant, anti-woman, homophobic, and so on. In periods of large-scale collective struggle, workers find in class solidarity and hatred of all oppression the basis of their real collective power.

The bosses consciously foster divisions among workers in order to weaken and defeat their struggles for better conditions. This is openly evident in the written instructions to a detective firm on how to help break the 1919 steel strike in Pittsburgh:

We want you to stir up as much bad feeling as you possibly can between the Serbians and the Italians. Spread data among the Serbians that the Italians are going back to work. Call up every question you can in reference to racial hatred between these two nationalities; make them realize to the fullest extent that far better results would be accomplished if they will go back to work. Urge them to go back to work or the Italians will get their jobs.[18]_

The very conditions of capitalist exploitation and competition also help to foster divisions among workers. As Sharon Smith points out:

While capitalism propels workers toward collective forms of struggle, it also forces them into competition. The unremitting pressure from a layer of unemployed workers, which exists in most economies even in times of ‘full employment,' is a deterrent to struggle—a constant reminder that workers compete for limited jobs which afford a decent standard of living. Without the counterweight of the class struggle this competition can act as an obstacle to the development of class consciousness, and encourage the growth of what Marx called ‘false consciousness'—part of which is the ideas which scapegoat other sections of society. The growth of such ideas divides workers, and impedes their ability to focus on the real enemy.[19]_

By oppressing a section of the working class on the basis of its sex, race, sexual orientation, language or national origin and driving those workers' conditions of existence down, capitalism is able to drive the conditions of all workers down. A white worker may perceive that their conditions of work and pay are better because of the lower pay received by Black workers. The reality, however, is that the bosses use the conditions of the lowest paid workers to drive the conditions of all workers down. The worse the pay and conditions of the most oppressed workers, the more the bosses can lower the pay of all workers. Conversely, when the conditions of the most oppressed sections of the working class are improved, the conditions of all workers improve. This explains why in the South, where rampant racism has been used to divide workers and keep unionization rates extremely low, the pay of white workers, though better than that of their Black counterparts in the region, is historically lower than the pay of Black workers in the North.[20]_

Clinton's gutting of welfare disproportionately hurts Black people because Blacks are disproportionately poor. However, a majority of people on welfare is white, as are the majority of poor people. Politicians used racial stereotyping in order to whip up anti-welfare sentiment—in order to attack both poor Blacks and poor whites. This attack has repercussions for all workers, who will not only suffer from less access to social aid in times of economic distress, but who will also face employers' attempts to use the cheap labor of former welfare recipients to drive employees' conditions down.

Likewise, some male workers may perceive that they benefit from women's oppression—they don't have to do as much housework, for example. But the relative advantage a man gets from this setup doesn't compare either to the benefit capitalism receives from women's unpaid labor in the home, or to the gain for both working-class men and women if the conditions of women's double burden were lifted. Male workers suffer from the fact that women's wages are still on average lower than theirs—both because it drives down the wages of all workers, and because it lowers the financial resources of working-class families. The prime beneficiary of women's role in the privatized family is the capitalist class, who does not have to pay for taking care of today's and tomorrow's generation of workers.

Even in instances where men and women do equally share housework, workers are still stuck in private households, forced to carry a difficult burden that allows no leisure time. One could only laugh at a man who proclaimed his pleasure at the fact that his wife was treated as a sex object at work, could not afford an abortion, could not take paid maternity leave, had trouble finding quality affordable childcare or received low wages.

It is true that oppression—such as racism or sexism—affects all classes in society. But the character and intensity of the oppression is very much shaped by the class you come from. An unemployed white autoworker in Flint, Michigan, for example, is far more oppressed than Gen. Colin Powell (if indeed he is oppressed at all), who is part of the American ruling class. Moreover, a Black autoworker in Flint, Michigan, shares much more in common, in terms of social status, living and working conditions, with a white autoworker than he does with Colin Powell or a Black businessman. More than that, Colin Powell actually benefits from the existing social order. Therefore, whatever Colin Powell's personal views on discrimination or racism, he has a stake in a system that depends upon discrimination and racism.

Likewise, there is a wide gulf between the oppression experienced by a wealthy woman who can afford maids, cooks and nannies, and the woman who works for her as a maid or a nanny. They stand apart from each other across a yawning class divide. The wealthy woman has no need to fight for all of the things that would free working women from their oppressed condition—such as free and available abortion (and other health care), equal pay, childcare, and so on—because she can pay for these services and hire working-class women to perform these tasks. In fact, complete liberation for all women hurts the interests of her own class, which depends upon women's unpaid labor in the home, the low pay of immigrant workers who tend their lawns, cook their food and work in their factories, fields and hospitals.

Building women's “unity” means, in practice, subordinating the interests of working-class women to bourgeois and middle-class women. “The sisterhood of woman,” wrote the socialist Elizabeth Gurley Flynn in 1915, “like the brotherhood of man, is a hollow sham to labor. Behind all its smug hypocrisy and sickly sentimentality loom the sinister outlines of the class war.”[21]

Rejection of revolution

But the class war is just what many on the left have rejected. The same sections of the left who have rejected Marxism and accepted some form of identity politics have also, since the collapse of Stalinism and the much-touted “triumph” of free-market capitalism, completely rejected the idea that society can be fundamentally transformed. This can be seen even in the case of left-wing writers who consider themselves socialists. Manning Marable, for example, wrote in the February 1993 issue of the Progressive:

We must accept and acknowledge the reality that, for the foreseeable future, the essential debate will not be about “capitalism versus socialism” but about the character and content of the capitalist social order... This means advancing a politics of radical, multicultural democracy, not socialism. It means, in the short run, that tactical electoral alliances with centrists like Clinton, within the Democratic Party, are absolutely necessary if we are to push back the aggressive, reactionary agenda of the far right.

Urvashi Vaid, director of the Policy Institute of the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force (NGLTF), is quoted in a recent South End Press book, ironically titled Talking About a Revolution:

For many years, I thought that we would have a revolution that would overthrow existing structures and replace them with the new thing. I don't believe that now, and I haven't for a long time... But I really believe that we can make capitalism more responsive, accountable, environmentally sound. We can make it fairer, non-discriminatory. We can take the benefits of the economic system and spread them out, so they can benefit more people rather than the five owners of everything... This is a pragmatic formulation.”[22]

Even when unity between different oppressed groups is discussed, the basis of unity is not class, but only some vague sense that oppressed groups cannot achieve their liberation alone. The result is pro-Democratic Party reformism, represented by the quotations above, combined with an argument for cross-class unity. Vaid argues,

I really value identity... And yet, I very much believe I can link up and find common ground with a heterosexual mother who lives in the suburbs. I think I can link up and find common ground with a straight white businessman who's working in a big corporation. I really believe that.”[23]

The working class is completely absent from this equation. It is ironic that, in this view, workers cannot unite across racial and sexual lines, yet Vaid (a nonwhite lesbian) thinks nothing of proclaiming her ability to unite with a “straight white businessman.” The middle class can unite, workers cannot.

Marable at least recognizes that there has been a growing class polarization among Blacks in the U.S.:

Despite the legal and political gains African-Americans have achieved, and despite the growth of a Black middle class, the reality is that the basic conditions for the vast majority of Black people—and youth especially—have become strikingly worse in the past 15 years.”[24]

Marable also points out that the number of Black political officials in office has risen dramatically since 1965, from 100 to more than 8,000, at the very same time that conditions for the majority of Blacks have worsened.

But Marable doesn't use these facts to challenge the idea of an undifferentiated “Black community,” or to explain that class interest pits poor and working-class Blacks against middle-class and rich Blacks. Instead he argues: “If the Black Community is going to move forward into the next century, we must take aggressive steps, and quickly, to bridge this generation gap.”[25] By describing what is a growing class gap as simply a generational difference, Marable is then able to argue for all Blacks to unite. Instead of linking the struggle of ordinary Black people against racism and exploitation with the struggle of other workers who face inequality and exploitation, Marable calls for a new fight for “Black empowerment” that unites Blacks across the class divide. “We must also search for common ground—the basic unity of interests that bring together people of different backgrounds, genders, sexual orientations, languages and social classes to advance the ideals of democracy.”[26]

The Polish-born German revolutionary Rosa Luxemburg answered Marable well a century ago in her polemic against reformism. The bourgeoisie, she argues, has long ago abandoned any commitment to real democracy out of fear of any struggle from below:

We must conclude that the socialist movement is not bound to bourgeois democracy, but that the fate of democracy is bound with the socialist movement. We must conclude from this that democracy does not acquire greater chances of life in the measure that the working class renounces the struggle for its emancipation, but that on the contrary, democracy acquires greater chances of survival as the socialist movement becomes sufficiently strong to struggle against the bourgeois desertion of democracy. He who would strengthen democracy should want to strengthen and not weaken the socialist movement. He who renounces the struggle for socialism renounces both the labor movement and democracy.[27]_

Centrality of the working class

The working-class struggle cannot be successful unless workers are able to throw off the yoke of oppression that divides them. That is why, as a class, workers not only do not benefit from oppression, but also have a common class interest in fighting oppression. Capitalism would have no need for dividing workers if there were not another dynamic at work—the tendency for capitalism to compel workers to collectively fight back against the various aspects of their oppression and exploitation. Writes Hal Draper, using a quotation from Marx:

Capital “assembles the bourgeois and the proletarians in large cities, in which industry can be carried on most profitably, and by this herding together of great masses in one spot makes the proletariat conscious of their power”... The interests of workers, as a group organized by capital, lead them to struggle. To engage in class struggle it is not necessary to “believe in” the class struggle any more than it is necessary to believe in Newton in order to fall from an airplane. The working class moves toward class struggle insofar as capitalism fails to satisfy its economic and social needs and aspirations... There is no evidence that workers like to struggle any more than anyone else; the evidence is that capitalism compels and accustoms them to do so. [Draper's italics] [28]

It is in the course of struggle that the ideas used to divide workers begin to break down, and workers see in practice who the real enemy is. But because capitalism both divides and unites workers, it is necessary to build an organization—a revolutionary socialist party—that brings together the most class-conscious workers and fights to link every small battle against exploitation and oppression in the system with the struggle to overthrow the system as a whole. Writes Tony Cliff:

For any oppressed group to fight back there is need for hope. And that is to be found, not in the isolation of oppression—the housewife trapped in the home, the gay in the closet, the Jews in the ghetto—but in the collective strength of the working class. For Marxists the notion that the working class, by liberating itself, will liberate the whole of humanity, is central. Which is why the revolutionary socialist party must support struggles against all forms of oppression, not only of the working class but of any downtrodden section of society.[29]_

Lenin argued that working-class consciousness could not be considered full class consciousness until workers were trained to combat all forms of oppression:

Working-class consciousness cannot be genuine political consciousness unless the workers are trained to respond to all cases of tyranny, oppression, violence, and abuse, no matter what class is affected... Socialists should conduct propaganda that exposes the horrors and abuses of the system, so that the most backward worker will understand, or will feel, that the students and religious sects, the peasants and the authors are being abused and outraged by those same dark forces that are oppressing and crushing him at every step of his life. Feeling that, he himself will be filled with an irresistible desire to react, and he will know how to hoot the censors one day, on another day to demonstrate outside the house of a governor who has brutally suppressed a peasant uprising, on still another day to teach a lesson to the gendarmes in surplices who are doing the work of the holy inquisition.[30]_

There has long been a false dichotomy posed on the left: either you choose to focus on class questions, to the detriment of issues of oppression; or you focus on fighting oppression. In reality, the only way to effectively challenge oppression and ultimately to destroy it is to link the two together. Where oppression and class intersect, it is only the working class who has an interest in sweeping away all forms of oppression and exploitation, that is, to stand for the complete liberation of the oppressed.

The need for revolution

Revolutions are festivals of the oppressed and the exploited. At no other times are the masses of the people in a position to come forward so actively as the creators of a new social order. —Lenin[31]_

What all of the critics of genuine Marxism have in common is the idea that somehow oppression can be ended without ending capitalism. This is essentially the standpoint of middle-class and bourgeois radicalism. Bourgeois as well as middle-class sections of the oppressed always seek to limit the scope of the struggle, to keep it within the bounds acceptable to their class. Their cries for “unity of the oppressed” are ultimately calls for the working-class sections of the oppressed to not “break ranks” by asking for too much. The middle class—professionals, managers, engineers, and so on—seeks merely to improve their status within the framework of the existing system. As Rosa Luxemburg put it, “Instead of taking a stand for the establishment of a new society they take a stand for surface modification of the old society.”[32]

There have been some improvements over the last few decades for middle-class Blacks, Latinos and women—gains that have been partially eroded, but not eliminated. As the class divide has widened, middle-class women and Blacks have moved rightward along with the Clinton Democrats, offering not the slightest challenge to Clinton's rollback of welfare spending and the increasing brutalization of young, predominantly poor Black and Latino men in the criminal justice system. For the majority of working-class and poor people, conditions have worsened. Real liberation must be linked to a class struggle for better pay, housing, education, more jobs, more social spending, against police brutality and so on. And those struggles must be linked to a fight to destroy the system that feeds on oppression. A revolution in the U.S. would fuse together struggles against police brutality and the criminal injustice system, struggles of women for equal pay, struggles against immigrant- and gay-bashing, and so on, with the struggle of ordinary workers to seize the reigns of production.

At the heart of any real revolution is the transformation of the economic relations in society—the socialization of the means of production by the working class in order to produce for human need. But that doesn't mean at all that revolution consists simply of a change in the economic relations of society. Revolution is about a total transformation of all aspects of society. “The history of a revolution,” wrote Leon Trotsky in his masterful History of the Russian Revolution, “is for us first of all a history of the forcible entrance of the masses into the realm of the rulership over their own destiny.”[33] Revolutions bring forward all the downtrodden, the oppressed and the mistreated. They awaken what is best in humanity, that collective spirit of solidarity in which all forms of oppression are laid bare and challenged openly.

This happened in the Russian Revolution of 1917. At the heart of the 1917 October Revolution was the seizure of the factories by the workers and the seizure of the land by the peasants. But the revolution did far more than that. Oppressed nationalities were offered the right to secede from Russia. Homosexuality was legalized. Divorce was made free and easily available to either party, and Soviet Russia became the first country to grant women the right to vote. More importantly, efforts were made to establish the means by which women could be freed from household slavery and dependence in the husband: access to jobs and education and to communal kitchens, laundries and childcare services. The Bolsheviks created a special “Women's Department,” which sought to draw millions of women into active social life, combat illiteracy and challenge men's resistance, especially in the countryside, to women's freedom.

And in a country where anti-Jewish pogroms had recently been commonplace, Jews rose to positions of leadership in the revolutionary government. Kamenev and Zinoviev, both Jews, were prominent leaders in the new government. Trotsky, a Jew, became first commissar of foreign affairs, and then, months later when the revolution was under attack, he became commander of the Red Army, which beat back attacks from 14 different armies.

Isolated and economically backward, the Russian Revolution ultimately failed. But though socialism could not be achieved in Russia, the revolution remains the highest achievement of humanity in this century, showing us all the way to fight for and build a society free from all oppression and misery. The Russian revolution gave us a glimpse of what a society run by workers would mean—for all the oppressed.

[1]

Zillah Eisenstein, “Developing a Theory of Capitalist Patriarchy,” from Eisenstein, ed., Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case for Socialist Feminism (Monthly Review, 1979), p. 9.

[2]

Clarence E. Walker, Deromanticizing Black History: Critical Essays and Reappraisals, (University of Tennessee, 1991), pp. 4-5. Walker engages in what is typical for anti-Marxist hacks: he misquotes out of context. The quote from Marx comes from two sources: a series of speeches he made in 1849, which was published as a pamphlet entitled “Wage Labor and Capital,” and also from a footnote in Capital in reference to an argument that capital is “not a thing, but a social relation between persons.” Here is Marx's full 1849 quote: “A negro is a negro. He only becomes a slave in certain relations. A cotton-spinning jenny is a machine for spinning cotton. It becomes capital only in certain relations. Torn from these relationships it is no more capital than gold in itself is money or sugar the price of sugar.” In this comment there is not the slightest hint of racism. On the contrary, Marx's comment implicitly challenges the prevailing ideology justifying the enslavement of Africans.

[3]

Karl Marx, Capital (New York: Vintage, 1977), p. 915.

[4]

Capital, p. 918.

[5]

Karl Marx, “Marx to Annenkov, December 28, 1846,” Collected Works, Volume 38 (New York: Progress Publishers, 1982), pp. 101-02.

[6]

Quoted in Ahmed Shawki, “Black Liberation and Socialism in the United States,” International Socialism 47 (Summer 1990), p. 8.

[7]

Capital, p. 414.

[8]

Karl Marx and Frederick Engels, Ireland and the Irish Question (New York: International Publishers, 1972), pp. 293-94.

[9]

V.I. Lenin, “The Right of Nations to Self Determination,” Questions of National Policy and Proletarian Internationalism (Moscow: Progress, 1970), p. 74.

[10]

Hal Draper, “Marx and Engels on Women's Liberation,” International Socialism 44 (old series) (July/August 1970), p. 23.

[11]

Frederick Engels, The Origin of the Family, Private Property and the State (New York: International Publishers, 1985), p. 129.

[12]

Capital, pp. 620-621.

[13]

Sharon Smith, Deborah Roberts and Celia Petty, Women's Liberation and Socialism (Bookmarks: Chicago, 1987), p. 61.

[14]

Quoted in Draper, p. 22.

[15]

Leon Trotsky, Women and the Family (New York: Pathfinder, 1986), p. 29.

[16]

Quoted in Chris Weedon, Feminism, Theory and the Politics of Difference (Malden, Mass.: Blackwell, 1999), p. 27.

[17]

Quoted in Weedon, p. 176.

[18]

Quoted in Jeremy Brecher, Strike! (Boston: South End Press, 1972), p. 125.

[19]

Sharon Smith, “Mistaken Identity—or Can Identity Politics Liberate the Oppressed,” International Socialism 62 (Spring 1994), p. 39.

[20]

See Shawki, p. 97.

[21]

Quoted in Philip Foner, Women and the American Labor Movement, Volume I (New York: The Free Press, 1979), p. 412.

[22]

South End Press Collective, eds., Talking About a Revolution (Boston: South End Press, 1998), pp. 108-09.

[23]

Talking About a Revolution, p. 102.

[24]

Manning Marable, Black Liberation in Conservative America (Boston: South End Press, 1997), p. 246.

[25]

Marable, p. 248.

[26]

Marable, p. 248.

[27]

Rosa Luxemburg, Reform or Revolution (New York: Pathfinder, 1980), p. 76.

[28]

Hal Draper, Karl Marx's Theory of Revolution, Volume 3: the Politics of Social Classes (New York: Monthly Review, 1978), pp. 41-42.

[29]

Tony Cliff, Class Struggle and Women's Liberation (London: Bookmarks, 1984), p. 237.

[30]

Quoted in Cliff, Class Struggle and Women's Liberation (London: Bookmarks, 1984), p. 238.

[31]

Quoted in Cliff, p. 139.

[32]

Luxemburg, p. 78.

[33]

Trotsky, History of the Russian Revolution (Pluto Press, London, 1997), p. 17.

Fighting back on Turtle Island: Indigenous sovereignty, the working class and anti-capitalism

By Brian Champ and Michelle Robidoux

As 2020 began, a struggle by Indigenous Wet'suwet'en people against attempts to push a natural gas pipeline through their unceded territory sparked a spectacular wave of solidarity across Canada.1 For almost a month, freight and passenger railway traffic ground to a halt as the #ShutDownCanada movement spread across the country.2 The dynamic of Indigenous resistance to encroachments on their sovereignty and mass solidarity by non-Indigenous people---including organised workers---captured the imagination of thousands looking for a strategy in the face of an accelerating climate crisis.

This movement takes place in a global context of struggles confronting the destructive practices of extractive industries. As Martin Upchurch has noted in a previous edition of this journal, "Many protests have succeeded against the power of the oil companies because of the development of militant tactics and mass support... The number of such protests appears to be growing on a global scale, with more than 3,100 so far reported on the 'Global Atlas of Environmental Justice'".3 These struggles target key "chokepoints" of the capitalist economy, blockading pipeline construction, highways, railways and ports. Indigenous people are at the forefront of these struggles, from Australia to South America and Africa. On Turtle Island---the name given by some Indigenous peoples to the North American continent---this is visible in the battle at Standing Rock against the Dakota Access Pipeline, the successful fight against Enbridge's Northern Gateway Pipelines, the mass opposition to the Energy East pipeline, and the victory of the Inuit people of Clyde River against seismic testing for oil in the Arctic.

These struggles have transformed the landscape, raising hopes of stopping rapacious megaprojects and the climate chaos they bring. They also outline a path along which a powerful movement uniting Indigenous peoples and non-Indigenous settlers in countries like Canada could strike at the roots of capitalism itself.

Yet with every advance in stopping such projects, right-wing forces attempt to widen divisions between Indigenous peoples, climate activists and the broader multi-racial working class. Those divisions, underpinned by centuries of colonialism that has structured the relationships between Indigenous people and settlers, can suddenly explode. In mid-September, when Mi'kmaq fishers exercised their treaty rights by placing lobster traps in the Bay of Fundy, they were set upon by non-Indigenous fishers who rammed their boats, cut their traps, destroyed their vehicles and set fire to a lobster pound. Fuelling these attacks was the claim that Indigenous fishers threaten the sustainability of lobster stocks.4 This false claim has been allowed to stand by the federal government because it suits them to divide fishers. In reality, although the ten Sipekne'katik lobster licences authorise only 50 traps per licence, a single commercial harvester can deploy up to 400 traps.5 The federal government has sat back and let this rendition of colonial violence play out, as police watch it unfold. Tragically, most of the non-Indigenous fishers carrying out these attacks are French-speaking Acadians, whose ancestors only survived hunger, disease, a harsh climate and the British scorched-earth policy because of assistance from the Mi'kmaq.

The Wet'suwet'en struggle and that of the Mi'kmaq community of Sipekne'katik reflect the polarisation that accelerating climate chaos, economic crisis and the Covid-19 pandemic have intensified. The ongoing attacks on Indigenous peoples are a daily reminder that the colonial violence and cruelty that Canada was founded upon continues today. Any movement that hopes to transform society must confront the racism baked into the entire structure of capitalist Canada. The ruling class's deployment of age-old colonial tactics reflects the reality of their limited options as these crises bear down. Even as millions around the world are fighting for a Green New Deal and a "just recovery" from the Covid-19 crisis, the Canadian state has doubled down on tar-sands oil. This can only mean confrontation---with Indigenous peoples whose sovereignty is an obstacle to hydrocarbon developments, and with the vast majority of Canadians who see a move away from fossil fuels as necessary.6 Anti-Indigenous racism is used to justify ongoing Canadian colonialism, scapegoating Indigenous people for the horrific conditions they face. Understanding the dynamics at play, their historic roots and the means by which Indigenous resistance and workers' struggles can link up is crucial for the success of both. This article hopes to contribute to that understanding.

Settler colonialism on Turtle Island

The settler-colonial states of Canada, the United States, Australia and New Zealand, as they exist today, share a majority Anglo-European culture because colonialism decimated the Indigenous populations that have existed for thousands of years. Even as new waves of immigration change the make up of the Canadian population, the result of historic and ongoing genocidal policies mean that Indigenous peoples are now a small minority on their ancestral lands. As Roxanne Dunbar-Ortiz writes:

Nearly all the population areas of the Americas were reduced by 90 percent following the onset of colonising projects, decreasing the targeted Indigenous populations of the Americas from one hundred million to ten million. Commonly referred to as the most extreme demographic disaster---framed as natural---in human history, it was rarely called genocide until the rise of Indigenous movements in the mid-20th century forged questions.7

Yet despite facing fierce oppression, Indigenous people have played an enormous role in key environmental battles, defending their land against destructive megaprojects. Through centuries of resistance, Indigenous people have won forms of land tenure and legal standing within the colonial framework. Corporations or governments that want to set up a mine, build a pipeline or engage in logging on Indigenous land can't ignore this standing. On Turtle Island, militant ecologism is an organic part of many Indigenous struggles. This outlook stems partly from a continuing relationship to the land, as many Indigenous peoples still rely on hunting, fishing and other subsistence activities. However, although many still retain strong connections to the land, over half of Indigenous people in Canada live in urban centres. The brutal policies of dispossession that created and maintain the Canadian state have severed many Indigenous people's relationship to the land. Organic community memory of the ideas of egalitarianism and reciprocity that characterised pre-colonial Indigenous societies has been reinforced and reinvigorated through struggle. The assertion of traditions and cultures that stand in stark contrast to capitalism inspires many activists who reject the unchecked destruction produced by capitalism and view decolonisation and solidarity as key to challenging this.8

“Shut Down Canada”

The electrifying movement to #ShutDownCanada arose in response to the invasion of Indigenous lands in the north of the province now called British Columbia by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police (RCMP). The police violently arrested Wet'suwet'en matriarchs and supporters. At issue was Indigenous resistance to Coastal GasLink's construction of a multi-billion-dollar pipeline that would channel fracked gas from the interior of British Columbia to export facilities on the Pacific coast. The Wet'suwet'en people have inhabited their territory for at least 10,000 years, and Wet'suwet'en territory encompasses 22,000 km2 of northern British Columbia. For years, energy corporations have sought to build pipelines from Alberta through this area of British Columbia in order to ship their products to lucrative markets. The Wet'suwet'en hereditary chiefs have consistently opposed these projects---from the now-defeated Northern Gateway Pipeline to the Pacific Trails Pipeline and the Coastal GasLink project.

On New Year's Eve, 2019, the British Columbia Supreme Court granted Coastal GasLink an injunction to access Wet'suwet'en land in order to continue pipeline construction. Coastal GasLink had signed agreements for the pipeline with five of six Wet'suwet'en band councils, whose leaders are chosen by democratic elections on individual reserves. However, the Wet'suwet'en hereditary chiefs have never ceded their territory, and band councils, which have a limited role in governing six reserves totalling just 35 km2, have no authority over Wet'suwet'en territory.9

In response to the Coastal GasLink injunction, the hereditary chiefs invoked their own law and evicted Coastal GasLink employees. This was despite the looming threat of police violence; indeed, a year earlier, the RCMP had deployed snipers as they surrounded land defenders while attempting to enforce another injunction.10 The chiefs called for provincial construction permits to be revoked and for nation-to-nation talks with social-democratic British Columbia premier John Horgan, Liberal Party prime minister Justin Trudeau, and the commissioner of the RCMP. The British Columbia government, a coalition of the Labour-style New Democratic Party and the Green Party, had just become the first in North America to pass legislation that implemented the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous People (UNDRIP). These rights include the requirement of "free, prior and informed consent" from Indigenous peoples before any project affecting their lands or territories is approved. The ink was not even dry on that legislation when the British Columbia government claimed the situation was out of their hands because the RCMP were enforcing a court-issued injunction. A leaked letter later revealed that the British Columbia Solicitor General had called in the RCMP by declaring a provincial emergency.11

For his part, Justin Trudeau, who since his election in 2015 repeated that "no relationship is more important to Canada than the relationship with Indigenous people", instead called for the "rule of law", a demand from colonial power that echoes through the generations.12 As the hereditary chiefs stated:

Anuc 'nu'at'en (Wet'suwet'en law) is not a "belief" or a "point of view". It is a way of sustainably managing our territories and relations with one another and the world around us, and it has worked for millennia to keep our territories intact. Our law is central to our identity. The ongoing criminalisation of our laws by Canada's courts and industrial police is an attempt at genocide, an attempt to extinguish Wet'suwet'en identity itself.13

On 6 February, RCMP began arresting land defenders. Within hours, the British Columbia legislature was occupied and ports, railways and highways were blocked across the country. This shut down Canadian National Railways's eastern network, bringing freight traffic from Halifax to Toronto to a halt. A solidarity blockade on Tyendinaga Mohawk Territory stopped travel between Montreal and Toronto, one of the busiest rail corridors in the country. Similar actions took place on Listuguj First Nation territory in Quebec, Kahnawake Mohawk territory south of Montreal, and near New Hazelton, British Columbia.14

On 8 February, protesters blockaded the access road to the Deltaport container terminal, staying overnight. This port, located in Greater Vancouver, sees $1 billion worth of goods transported through it yearly. The 300 members of International Longshore and Warehouse Union Local 502 who arrived for the morning shift treated the blockade as a picket line and refused to cross, shutting down the port.15 On 10 February, police enforcing an injunction arrested 14 protesters. Another 43 were arrested in order to reopen the Port of Vancouver.16 Mass solidarity actions were organised in cities across the country; 15,000 joined a march in Toronto, and there were bridge, port and road shutdowns in Vancouver.

Two weeks into the shutdown, the Canadian Manufacturers and Exporters body estimated that $425 million in goods were being stranded daily. The business lobby spoke in increasingly frenzied terms of "catastrophe" for the economy. By 21 February, the Atlantic Container Line was diverting shipments from Halifax to New York and Baltimore. "In Montreal, some 4,000 containers sit immobilised on the docks and bulk agricultural products such as grain can no longer reach the port".17 In Vancouver, goods waiting to be shipped east led to a backlog of 50 ships unable to unload their cargoes.18

As solidarity actions rippled across the country and internationally, politicians pleaded with---and threatened---Indigenous land defenders and their supporters. Trudeau warned, "The situation as it currently stands is unacceptable... Canadians have been patient. Our government has been patient, but it has been two weeks and the barricades need to come down now... The injunctions must be obeyed".19 The hereditary chiefs responded, "We heard Prime Minister Trudeau just a little while ago talking about the inconvenience Canada has suffered. However, there is a difference between inconvenience and injustice".20

As these threats accumulated, statements of solidarity with the Wet'suwet'en hereditary chiefs rolled in from the British Columbia Government Employees Union (BCGEU), the Canadian Union of Public Employees, the British Columbia Teachers' Federation, postal workers and nurses' unions.21 Canadian Union of Public Employees (CUPE) national president Mark Hancock stated, "We would never accept this kind of RCMP behaviour towards striking workers on a picket line. Protest is a fundamental right, and the Wet'suwet'en people have a right to protect their unceded territory." BCGEU advised that "members who encounter a picket line at their worksite are expected to exercise their collective agreement and Charter rights to respect that picket line".22 Ontario CUPE wrote:

While the epicenter of this struggle takes place in this country's westernmost province, we are witnessing and partaking in solidarity actions across the nation. Here in Ontario, allies are blocking rail lines, collecting funds and organising local events to raise awareness. Respecting Indigenous sovereignty and the fight for environmental justice is fundamental for all Canadians.23

The British Columbia Teachers' Federation stated on behalf of its 45,000 union members:

We stand in solidarity with the Wet'suwet'en peoples and demand that the governments of British Columbia and Canada uphold their responsibilities as laid out in the Supreme Court's Delgamuukw-Gisday'wa decision of 1997. We stand as witnesses at this historic moment when our governments must make a choice to uphold this court decision or continue the ongoing legacy of colonisation.24

This points to a key contradiction confronting the Canadian settler-colonial state. In its landmark decision, the Supreme Court recognised the Wet'suwet'en hereditary chiefs as the rightful decision makers on their traditional territories, or "yin'tah". The case of Delgamuukw versus the Queen found that aboriginal title in British Columbia was never extinguished. As Christopher Roth explains:

British Columbia is a land, for the most part, without treaties... This lack of indisputable cession has been significant in Canadian law because of the Royal Proclamation of 1763, in which King George III declared that title to Indian territory was not to be considered extinguished or transferred merely by conquest or occupation but only through voluntary cession... Under this dispensation, British Columbia is the one area of what was called British North America where treaties were utterly neglected as an instrument of colonisation.25

The Delgamuukw ruling, he continues, "amounts to a finding that what we know as British Columbia has not been ceded to the Crown and is thus not part of Canada... But if so-called British Columbia is not Canada, then what kind of territory is it? What lies 'underneath', to borrow the geological metaphors of the legal jargon, can only be aboriginal title".26

The 1997 Delgamuukw decision provoked panic among corporations and their political facilitators:

According to one memo, detailing a meeting that took place one day after the Delgamuukw ruling, the then vice-president of the British Columbia Council of Forest Industries, Marlie Beets, remarked that she had spent the previous hour "trying to calm" the chief executives she represented. "Delgamuukw has only created more uncertainty and we are very concerned by how governments will react to the court's findings," Beets said. "The decision makes the need for certainty through surrender all the more clear. We see no other alternative".27

This has been the continuous response to legal recognition of aboriginal title by Canada's courts: corporate demands that politicians obtain Indigenous peoples' "surrender" and cession to counter "investment uncertainty". The Coastal GasLink injunction was granted as if the constitutional question of Wet'suwet'en aboriginal title did not exist. This is a pattern repeated across the country. Indigenous peoples' sovereignty over their lands is trampled, and industries rely on state violence to ensure access to resources.

As Karla Tait, a Unist'ot'en activist arrested on 10 February, stated:

The violence of Canada and the emptiness of its commitments to us as Indigenous people were laid bare in their actions, and their forcible removal of us in the midst of a ceremony... The events we experienced leading up to February 10 are another culmination of the efforts of Canada to discredit and criminalise us for simply existing on our land as we always have---for defending our rights to our landbase and our historic economy, our ways of empowering ourselves---because of the threat to the capitalist economy.28

Canada’s colonial past and present

This refusal to recognise Indigenous sovereignty is embedded in Canada's foundations, beginning with the "doctrine of discovery". As Jennifer Reid explains:

The doctrine of discovery was the legal means by which Europeans claimed rights of sovereignty, property and trade in regions they had allegedly discovered during the age of expansion. These claims were made without consultation with the resident populations in these territories---the people to whom, by any sensible account, the land actually belonged. The doctrine of discovery is a critical component of historical relations between Europeans, their descendants and Indigenous peoples... It is not simply an artifact of colonial history. It is the legal force that defines the limits of all land claims to this day and, more fundamentally, the necessity of land claims at all. To call it into question, even now, would change the rules of the argument entirely. As one journalist put it, "It is the federal and provincial governments of Canada who are trying to make a claim to land, a claim based on the doctrine of discovery".29

A vast array of measures was deployed to enforce this framework in the interests of Canadian capitalism as it expanded westward through the Prairies region and into what is now British Columbia. By the mid-1800s, "US expansion had begun to alarm the leaders of British North America." The US and Canadian colonists had already squabbled over territory in the War of 1812, but "now the Americans were pushing west, threatening to swallow up the bulk of North America. The colonial elite in London and Canada became increasingly obsessed with the idea of connecting the Canadian colonies to British Columbia and asserting their claim to all of the territory in between".30

The development of a transcontinental Canada depended on breaking Indigenous peoples' connection to the land: "As long as the Plains Indians remained strong, and capable of defending their rights and their lands, they presented, together with the Métis, a formidable opposition to the imperialist dreams of Ottawa and London".31 John A Macdonald, Canada's first prime minister, was also the longest serving Minister of Indian Affairs and the architect of Canada's "Indian" policy, embodied in the 1876 Indian Act. As he wrote, "Indian matters and the land granting system form so great a portion of the general policy of the government that I think it necessary for the prime minister, whoever he may be, to have that in his own hands".32 He only gave up this portfolio in 1888, once the Canadian Pacific Railway was built, mass settlement of the West was underway, and Indigenous peoples had been decimated, their nations dismembered and confined to tiny allotments of land known as reserves. This was accomplished through horrific violence, starvation, unscrupulous treaty-making, the creation of the cruel residential schools network, the theft of Indigenous children, the imposition of a tyrannical pass system, and the destruction of Indigenous governance structures and spiritual practices. These methods, which Dene scholar Glen Coulthard describes as a "genocidal exclusion/assimilation double", sought to destroy Indigenous communities as distinct peoples.33

Resistance to this assault was continuous and fierce. To enforce its policies, the newly founded Canadian state established the North-West Mounted Police, a permanent occupation force modelled on the Royal Irish Constabulary.34 The forerunner of today's RCMP, it was instrumental in suppressing ceremonies such as the Thirst Dance in the Prairies and the Potlatch on the Pacific coast. These ceremonies played an important role in redistributing surplus among members of Indigenous societies. Government officials "objected to the fact that they undermined the accumulation of private property, took people away from agricultural pursuits, brought together bands that they were trying to keep separate, and strengthened the status of traditional leaders and elders".35

As Indian commissioner Hayter Reed wrote in 1889, "the policy of destroying the tribal or communist system is assailed in every possible way." This included the creation of residential schools where, as Bishop Vital Grandin said in 1875, "We instil in them a pronounced distaste for the Native life so that they will be humiliated when reminded of their origin. When they graduate from our institutions, the children have lost everything Native except their blood." Over the course of a century, an estimated 150,000 First Nations, Inuit and Métis children passed through the residential school system. The 2015 report of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC) reads like an encyclopedia of sadism. Established in 2008 to record the history and impacts of the residential schools, the TRC documented the deaths of over 6,000 students. The report concluded that the brutality deployed to suppress Indigenous language and culture constitutes "the darkest, longest, and most chilling chapter in the history of the colonisation of Aboriginal peoples".36

As Tyler Shipley notes:

The development of Canada fits the predictable patterns of a settler colony born out of European expansion between the 15th to 19th centuries. Though it gradually took on a uniquely Canadian character, many of the same basic patterns are found in studies of the US or Australia, or in more modern cases that follow similar logics, from South African apartheid to Israel's occupation of Palestine.37

Considering the catastrophe that befell Indigenous peoples on Turtle Island, the degree to which their communities have survived and are today resurgent is a testament to their centuries of resistance. Yet this catastrophe is not something of the past. It is embodied in state policies deployed today. As Coulthard explains:

Settler-colonial formations are territorially acquisitive in perpetuity... In the specific context of Canadian settler colonialism though, the means by which the colonial state has sought to eliminate Indigenous peoples in order to gain access to our lands and resources have varied over the last two centuries. These range from violent dispossession to the legislative elimination of First Nations legal status under the sexist and racist provisions of the Indian Act, as well as the "negotiation" of what are still essentially land surrenders under the present comprehensive land claims policy. The ends have always remained the same: to shore up continued access to Indigenous peoples' territories for the purposes of state formation, settlement, and capitalist development.38

The consequences of colonialism

Indigenous peoples in what is today called Canada constitute 4.5 percent of the overall population and are linguistically, culturally and geographically diverse. The Canadian state's attempt to eradicate Indigenous people is not merely a historic phenomenon---it is a colonial present that manifests in myriad ways. This was captured by the government's 2018 Public Health Agency report, Key Health Inequalities in Canada---A National Portrait.39 Key findings of the report include:

life expectancy for people from Inuit, First Nations and Métis communities is 69.7, 70.5 and 74.8 years respectively, compared to the national average of 81.8 years;

infant mortality rates are 2 to 4 times the national average;

the suicide rate in Inuit communities is 6.5 times higher than the national average---a testament to the hopelessness that many Indigenous people feel;

rates of arthritis, asthma, diabetes and disability are significantly higher than the national average, as are rates of infectious disease;

First Nations reserves are chronically underserved by health services; and,

Indigenous peoples in Canada experience the highest levels of poverty. Some 25 percent live in poverty, including a staggering 40 percent of Indigenous children.

In 2019, the UN special rapporteur on adequate housing found that:

In Canada, close to half of all First Nations people live on reserves, and more than 25 per cent of them live in overcrowded conditions, constituting approximately seven times the proportion of non-Indigenous people nationally. More than 10,000 on-reserve homes in Canada are without indoor plumbing, and 25 percent of reserves in Canada have substandard water or sewage systems. In a country with more fresh water than anywhere else in the world, 75 per cent of the reserves in Canada have contaminated water.40

As of September 2020, 63 reserves have a long-term public health directive that drinking water should be boiled. Lack of clean water, chronic shortage of decent housing and overcrowding have dire consequences. In a pandemic, they are deadly.

This mass of statistics does not begin to tell the story of the deeply rooted systemic racism towards Indigenous peoples in every aspect of Canadian society. The RCMP, founded to suppress Indigenous resistance on the Plains, continue their brutal and often murderous persecution of Indigenous people. In Saskatchewan, 62.5 percent of people who have died from police encounters were Indigenous, despite being only 11 percent of the population.41 From 2017 to June 2020, almost 40 percent of people killed by police were Indigenous. In 2016, Indigenous people represented 25 percent of the national male prison population and 35 percent of the female prison population.42 But it goes beyond police and prisons. On 28 September 2020, Joyce Echaquan, a 37-year-old Atikamekw woman, broadcast her dying moments from her hospital bed in Joliette, Quebec as she suffered racist abuse by hospital staff. In July 2017, Barbara Kentner, a 34-year-old Anishinaabe woman, died from injuries sustained after she was hit by a trailer hitch thrown from a passing truck. She heard her assailant yell "I got one!" as the truck drove away. This racism, built into the foundations of Canada, is systematically promoted from the top of society.

From Idle No More to #ShutDownCanada

In November 2012, resistance to legislation under Conservative Party prime minister Stephen Harper sparked a resurgence of Indigenous activism. The legislation threatened Indigenous treaty rights by dismantling environmental protection laws. Idle No More erupted on the political scene, with flash-mob round dances occupying malls and government buildings, city centres and highways. It emerged in the context of a global wave of mass movements challenging the status quo. Janaya Khan, a founder of Black Lives Matter Toronto, writes that "Idle No More played a pivotal role in normalising the language of 'Indigenous sovereignty' across leftist and movement cultures, academia and non-Indigenous communities".43 The movement emerged in the context of growing calls for an inquiry into missing and murdered Indigenous women; between 1980 and 2012, Indigenous women and girls represented 16 percent of all female homicides, despite making up only 4 percent of the female population in Canada.44 In Saskatchewan, 55 percent of all murdered women are Indigenous. As the Mi'kmaq lawyer and activist Pam Palmater notes, "The insidious ways in which racism and sexism combine to target Indigenous women and girls for disproportionate levels of abuse, neglect, exploitation, sexualised violence, disappearances and murders is a national crisis that requires a priority emergency response".45 Idle No More also emerged as the Truth and Reconciliation Commission conducted hearings across the country. It shaped the terrain on which the findings of the TRC were received in June 2015, when a poll by Angus Reid Institute found that 7 out of 10 agreed that the treatment of Indigenous children at residential schools amounted to "cultural genocide".46

Harper was defeated in the October 2015 federal election and his successor, Trudeau, centred his "brand" on the promise of a new nation-to-nation relationship with Indigenous peoples, as well as a commitment to tackling climate change. After years of Harper, there was a palpable sense of relief that the climate change-denying Conservatives were gone, and that the days of overt assimilationist policies were over. Yet as journalist Martin Lukacs writes:

The transformation underway among the Liberal Party, government institutions and the broader establishment was less a sea change than a shape shift. Faced with an Indigenous uprising unlike anything in Canadian history, they were prepared to accept, and even help construct, a new public consensus---making a taboo of overt racism, cleansing our public squares of ugly tokens of our past, embracing the resurgence in Indigenous cultural expression, and adopting the language of Indigenous liberation. But within this consensus, there were several great unmentionables: land, resources and power, and the sharing of any of them.47

The contradiction between Trudeau's brand and the reality of Canadian capitalism's commitment to extractive megaprojects was soon impossible to hide. At a 2017 energy conference in Houston, Trudeau declared:

No country would find 173 billion barrels of oil in the ground and just leave them there. The resource will be developed. Our job is to ensure that this is done responsibly, safely, and sustainably.48

In June 2019, the Liberal government passed a non-binding motion declaring that Canada is in a climate emergency. The next day, it approved the Trans Mountain tar-sands pipeline, which it had purchased the previous year for $4.5 billion CAD (ballooning to $16 billion by February 2020) and which, if completed, would carry 890,000 barrels of oil a day from Alberta to British Columbia. "Trudeau's pipeline" runs through unceded Indigenous territories. First Nations leaders have said it will not be built.49 His stated commitment to establishing a "new relationship" with Indigenous peoples, and meeting Canada's emissions target under the Paris Climate Agreement, is on a collision course with his material support for extracting and marketing tar-sands oil.

Paths of resistance

The struggle of Wet'suwet'en people struck a powerful chord of solidarity that succeeded in shutting down Canada---destabilising the "conditions of certainty" demanded by investors. This solidarity did not come out of the blue. It has been built over years, and a series of initiatives seeking to create a common framework of struggles around climate issues, Indigenous sovereignty and workers' rights moved it forward. The Leap Manifesto, created by Indigenous, climate, labour, faith and social justice organisations, was launched in September 2015, attempting to pressure the reformist New Democratic Party to adopt a bold platform for the upcoming elections. It stated:

We start from the premise that Canada is facing the deepest crisis in recent memory. The Truth and Reconciliation Commission has acknowledged shocking details about the violence of Canada's near past. Deepening poverty and inequality are a scar on the country's present. And Canada's record on climate change is a crime against humanity's future... Climate scientists have told us that this is the decade to take decisive action to prevent catastrophic global warming. That means small steps will no longer get us where we need to go. So we need to leap. This leap must begin by respecting the inherent rights and title of the original caretakers of this land. Indigenous communities have been at the forefront of protecting rivers, coasts, forests and lands from out-of-control industrial activity. We can bolster this role, and reset our relationship, by fully implementing the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples.50

In the summer of 2019, the Pact for a Green New Deal was launched, building on the Leap Manifesto. It declared that cutting Canada's emissions in half in 11 years, and ensuring no one is left behind in this transition, "means beginning with the foundational rights and sovereignty of Indigenous communities and implementing the UN Declaration." On 27 September, the global climate strike drew 500,000 people on the streets of Montreal, and 100,000 in Vancouver. Toronto saw 50,000 people turn out, including students, Indigenous activists, union members and many more. They were joined by a contingent of auto workers who were worried about the impending closure of the General Motors plant in Oshawa, Ontario. These workers had developed the Green Jobs Oshawa (GJO) campaign, calling for nationalisation of the plant and its conversion into a factory for electric vehicles. A representative of GJO subsequently spoke at the November climate strike in Toronto, where protests targeted the financial backers of the Coastal GasLink pipeline. This built deeper connections between climate, social justice and Indigenous activists, preparing the ground for the direct action of the new year. The sense of possibility was building, as climate actions took place around the world. Yet in spite of this broad support for a Green New Deal, it proved too "radical" for the New Democratic Party. Further protests in January 2020 against the impending invasion of Wet'suwet'en territory prepared the ground for the blockades of February.

In early March, the last railway blockades came down. Then the coronavirus pandemic hit. The railway was shut down again, but this time by Covid-19. As governments began rolling out economic support measures, the #JustRecoveryforAll initiative was launched. Over 150 organisations signed on, demanding that recovery efforts support a just transition, strengthen the social safety net, "uphold Indigenous rights, and include the full and effective participation of Indigenous peoples, in line with the standard of free, prior, and informed consent".51

Canada's history of lies and denial of the impact of colonisation on Indigenous people has been exploded by Indigenous resistance, which has elicited solidarity from millions of non-Indigenous people. The scale of support for the Wet'suwet'en struggle shows the potential for defending Indigenous sovereignty and challenging hydrocarbon megaprojects---but also, to challenge capitalism itself. As Glen Coulthard writes, "For Indigenous nations to live, capitalism must die".52 This echoes Métis activist and scholar Howard Adams, who wrote in Prison of Grass:

It is quite impossible for Indians and Métis in their present condition to experience any real liberation within the present capitalist society in terms of gaining control of reserves and communities, being free from discrimination and racism, obtaining full employment, acquiring a decent standard of living, or becoming free and equal people. We need to liberate ourselves from the courts, ballot boxes, school system, churches, and all other agencies that command us to stay in "our colonised place". This oppression of the Native people is so deeply rooted in the capitalist system that it cannot be completely eliminated without eliminating capitalism itself.53

Anti-Indigenous racism permeates the fabric of Canadian society and is enmeshed in the operation of the settler state as a whole. Even if the Canadian state were to settle land claims, halt pipeline projects and shift the entire energy grid to renewables, this racism would not end. The very existence of Indigenous peoples exposes Canada's dirty secret: that it is built on stolen land. The ongoing poverty and shocking conditions of life faced by Indigenous people in one of the richest countries in the world is a daily rebuke to the Liberal Party's pretences of "reconciliation".

Striking at the roots of Indigenous oppression requires overturning capitalism. This would simultaneously challenge the basis of environmental destruction, poverty and exploitation. Amid the multiple crises gripping the world, and the resistance summoned by them, this is a concrete question. The struggles today can begin to lay the basis for a movement powerful enough to tear up the whole system.

A revolutionary strategy looks to the power of Indigenous mobilisations against colonialism and racism allied with the power of the broader working class to shut down the system. United resistance by Indigenous peoples across Canada highlights the shared conditions created by the colonial-capitalist state and provides concrete opportunities for working-class solidarity with Indigenous people. It has brought the struggle into the consciousness of millions and has shown that the racism produced by the system can be challenged by Indigenous and non-Indigenous together.

Zach Wells, a shop steward on the VIA passenger rail network, publicly spoke out in support of the Wet'suwet'en struggle despite the layoffs it caused in his industry:

I wanted to make clear that solidarity can't begin and end with our co-workers. The labour movement is weakened enormously if it doesn't extend solidarity to broader social justice issues. We have more common cause with First Nations than we do with the Liberal Party of Canada, Canadian National Rail and Coastal GasLink.54

The longshore workers at Deltaport were putting this view into practice when they refused to cross the picket line and shut down the port---inflicting real economic damage on the bosses. Trade unionists also joined blockades of rail lines across the country. These are glimpses of what is possible. Workers need to be won to defending Indigenous peoples' rights if they are to combat the legacy of colonial racism, and Indigenous people need to be won to the power of the working class in order to overturn capitalism.

A strategy that articulates this approach is needed to counter the efforts by the ruling class to weaponise racism against Indigenous people. This necessarily means working through the question of national oppression as it applies to Canada, a country founded on dispossession of Indigenous peoples and the conquest of the French colony of New France. The idea that non-Indigenous working class people could be won to political recognition of the equal national rights of Indigenous peoples, let alone to the revolutionary overthrow of capitalism, may sometimes seem implausible because of the grip of racist and colonial attitudes. However, Indigenous lands were not stolen because of racism; rather, racism was required for the theft of Indigenous lands. As Chris Harman wrote:

Racism did not emerge all at once as a fully formed ideology... The early attitude to the native inhabitants of North America tended to be that they differed from Europeans because they faced different conditions of life. Indeed, one problem facing the governors of Jamestown, Virginia was that Indian life had a considerable attraction for white colonists, and "they prescribed the death penalty for running off to live with Indians".55

As capitalism developed, many of the people who made up the settler population were driven from their land through the enclosure of commons. As Dunbar-Ortiz explains:

The institutions of colonialism and methods for relocation, deportation and expropriation of land had already been practiced, if not perfected, by the end of the 15th century. The rise of the modern state in Western Europe was based on the accumulation of wealth by means of exploiting human labor and displacing millions of subsistence producers from their lands.56

She continues:

Denied access to the former commons, rural subsistence farmers and their children had no choice but to work in the new woollen textile factories under miserable conditions---that is, when they could find such work, as unemployment was high. Employed or not, this displaced population was available to serve as settlers in the North American British colonies, many of them as indentured servants, motivated by the promise of land. After serving their terms of indenture, they were free to squat on Indigenous land and become farmers again. In this way, surplus labor created not only low labor costs and great profits for the woolens manufacturers but also a supply of settlers for the colonies, which was used as an "escape valve" for the home country, where impoverishment might lead to uprisings of the exploited.57

Settler-colonial capitalism continues to rely on the concept of terra nullius, the idea that land was unowned before colonisation, and the doctrine of discovery to justify its historic and continued oppression of Indigenous people. Although governments and corporations proclaim their commitments to "reconciliation", they simultaneously reproduce racist structures and the ideology that sustains them. However, common struggles can challenge the hold of these ideas.58 Describing the struggle against Dakota Access Pipeline at Standing Rock, Lakota scholar and activist Nick Estes writes:

Political elites and corporate media have frequently depicted poor whites and poor Natives as irreconcilable enemies, lacking common ground and competing for scarce resources in economically depressed rural areas. Yet the defence of Native land, water and treaties brought us together. Although not perfect, the Oceti Sakowin camp was a home to many for months. And the bonds were long lasting, despite the horrific histories working against them.59

Imagining a world beyond capitalism

The Canadian philosopher James Tully has written:

Practices of reconciliation are doomed to failure if they attempt to change Indigenous-settler relations without dismantling vicious economic relations or if they attempt to change global economic systems without addressing the exercise of colonial power over Indigenous peoples worldwide... Yet this is unfortunately the approach offered in British Columbia and elsewhere in Canada by mainstream models of Indigenous-settler reconciliation, with their "business as usual" imperative.60

This approach has been embraced by all mainstream political parties in Canada, including the New Democratic Party. The right-wing government of Alberta, the heart of the tar-sands industry, has invested billions in pipeline development despite corporate investment drying up with the collapse of oil prices. This includes $1.5 billion of public funds invested in the Keystone XL pipeline, whose construction US president Joe Biden has now cancelled. Alberta premier Jason Kenney has introduced laws criminalising blocking "critical infrastructure" and used Covid-19 emergency measures to suspend labour and environmental legislation. These investments and laws protect the oil companies, the forces of death on a planetary scale. As well, far-right groups increasingly threaten Indigenous land defenders and pipeline opponents. This adds to the importance of building solidarity among the wider population, including workers. In the midst of the pandemic, the Alberta government launched a major attack on healthcare workers, announcing 11,000 job losses through outsourcing laundry, food services, housekeeping and laboratory jobs. Despite Covid-19 conditions, wildcat strikes swept through 49 worksites in 39 cities and towns on 26 October. This is the type of action needed to resist the unfolding disasters of capitalism.

That is why initiatives like the Leap Manifesto, the Green New Deal and #JustRecoveryforAll are so critically important. They link demands for Indigenous self-determination with those for a just transition for workers. Such bold proposals can provide an alternative to working-class identification with the settler-colonial state, towards solidarity with Indigenous people. Workers building pipelines and working in the tar sands and refineries need a concrete alternative to the dead end of fossil fuel production. Indigenous peoples need solidarity from working-class people to win their struggles. This counters the false dichotomies between jobs, Indigenous sovereignty and the environment.

The deep economic, environmental and social crises confronting humanity raise the question of what Karl Marx and Frederick Engels describe in the Communist Manifesto as a fight that ends "either in a revolutionary reconstitution of society at large, or in the common ruin of the contending classes". They advance a vision of socialism where the vast majority---the "associated producers"---wrests control of society away from the minority ruling class in order to democratically and cooperatively organise the economy to meet human need instead of corporate greed.

In Marx's Ecology, John Bellamy Foster writes:

The most important problem facing the society of associated producers, Marx emphasised again and again in his work, would be to address the problem of the metabolic relation between human beings and nature under the more advanced industrial conditions prevailing in the wake of the final revolutionary crisis of capitalist society. To this end, it was clearly necessary to learn more about the human relation to nature and subsistence, through the development of property forms, over the great span of ethnological time. Marx was thus driven back, by the materialist precepts of his analysis, to a consideration of the origins of human society and the human relation to nature---as a means for envisioning the potential for a more complete transcendence of an alienated experience.61

In the last years of his life Marx was captivated by the study of Indigenous societies.62 In his Ethnological Notebooks, he carefully pored over writings in the new field of anthropology, including those of Lewis Henry Morgan. As Frank Rosemont writes:

On page after page Marx highlights passages wildly remote from what are usually regarded as the "standard themes" of his work. Thus we find him invoking the bell-shaped houses of the coastal tribes of Venezuela; the manufacture of Iroquois belts "using fine twine made of filaments of elm and basswood bark"; "the Peruvian legend of Manco Cápac and Mama Ocllo, children of the sun"; burial customs of the Tuscarora; the Shawnee belief in metempsychosis; "unwritten literature of myths, legends and traditions"; the "incipient sciences" of the village Indians of the South West; the Popul Vuh, sacred book of the ancient Quiché Maya; the use of porcupine quills in ornamentation; Indian games and "dancing as a form of worship".63

The Ethnological Notebooks reveal his deep interest in the concrete experience of societies not distorted by the ravages of capitalism. Indigenous peoples have suffered most acutely from these ravages. However, they have never stopped resisting the system's genocidal logic and through that resistance have held on to ways of life, systems of law, forms of social organisation and cultures that possess a relationship to the natural world that is in sharp contrast to the logic of capitalism. Their continued existence is a testament to longstanding struggles against attempts to assimilate and eradicate them. Importantly, today there is much wider support for these struggles.

Continuing to build links between workers' struggles in the workplace and the ongoing resistance of Indigenous people to the colonial state is crucial for building a path forward for both. They are linked because they are both directed against the capitalist system, suggesting a potential revolutionary convergence that can overthrow capitalism in the context of settler-colonial states. And the battles that gesture towards the need for this type 0f unity are multiplying.

Brian Champ is a climate justice and anti-racist activist in Toronto and a member of the International Socialists.

Michelle Robidoux is a Toronto-based activist and member of the International Socialists.

Notes 1 Unceded territory refers to lands that Indigenous people never ceded or legally signed away to the Crown or to Canada.

Notes

1 Unceded territory refers to lands that Indigenous people never ceded or legally signed away to the Crown or to Canada.

2 This article is dedicated to the memory of Philip Murton, a socialist and trade-union activist who died as this article was being written. Thanks to Merv King, member of the Bear Clan of Timiskaming First Nation and activist in the United Steelworkers, and many others for comments on the original draft. All errors and omissions are ours.

3 Upchurch, 2020.

4 Edwards, 2020.

5 APTN National News, 2020.

6 Abacus Data, 2020.

7 Dunbar-Ortiz, 2014, p39.

8 See Lukacs, 2020.

9 For a brief overview of Wet'suwet'en governance structure, see Unist'ot'en Camp website at https://unistoten.camp/about/governance-structure

10 Dillon and Parrish, 2019.

11 British Columbia Civil Liberties Association, 2020.

12 Hyslop, 2020.

13 Rubin, 2020.

14 Forester, 2020.

15 Boynton, 2020.

16 Jacques, 2020.

17 Borneo Bulletin, 2020.

18 Reynolds, 2020.

19 Connolly, 2020.

20 Scherer and Ljunggren, 2020.

21 See Unist'ot'en Camp, 2020.

22 British Columbia Government Employees Union, 2020. Legal rights are codified in Canada's Charter of Rights and Freedoms.

23 CUPE Ontario, 2020.

24 British Columbia Teachers' Federation, 2020.

25 Roth, 2002, p150. The Royal Proclamation was itself in response to resistance by the Indigenous confederacy led by Odawa chief Obwandiyag (Pontiac) that briefly seized ten British military posts in the Great Lakes area in the spring of 1763.

26 Roth, 2002, p144.

27 Lukacs and Pasternak, 2020.

28 Brown and Bracken, 2020.

29 Reid, 2010.

30 Shipley, 2020, p33.

31 Adams, 1989, p60. The Métis are a distinct Indigenous people in Canada and parts of the US, originally the offspring of Indigenous women and European fur traders.

32 Hopper, 2018.

33 Coulthard, 2014, p6. The Dene are an Indigenous group in Canada's arctic and boreal regions.

34 Tellingly, "these colonial troops actively compared Indigenous people to the Irish, one declaring to the raucous laughter of his mates that the Sioux 'sound exactly like the Irish'. He followed it up with a mockery of the two accents mashed-up. Ireland, of course, was one of Britain's earliest colonial projects, and the Irish were engaged in a very serious struggle against British colonialism, which was spilling over into Canada."---Shipley, 2020, p53.

35 Truth and Reconcilation Commission of Canada, 2015, p130.

36 Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada, 2015, p131. Far from being limited to residential schools, this policy was in force through the "Sixties Scoop", in which Indigenous children were removed from their families and placed in foster care, and continues in child welfare policies today.

37 Shipley, 2020, p91.

38 Coulthard, 2014, chapter 4.

39 Public Health Agency of Canada, 2018.

40 United Nations General Assembly, 2019.

41 Palmater, 2020, p76.

42 Flanagan, 2020.

43 Khan, 2020, p123.

44 Shipley, 2020, p84.

45 Palmater, 2020, p272.

46 Angus Reid Institute, 2015.

47 Lukacs, 2019, p137.

48 Maclean's, 2017.

49 Beaumont, 2019.

50 See https://leapmanifesto.org/en/the-leap-manifesto. For a discussion of the global movement of Indigenous peoples that led to the UN Declaration, see Dunbar-Ortiz, 2016, p84.

51 See https://justrecoveryforall.ca

52 Coulthard, 2014, conclusion.

53 Adams, 1989, p176.

54 Robidoux, 2020.

55 Harman, 1999, p253. For a fuller discussion of the early encounters of settlers and Indigenous peoples in North America, see Empson, 2014, pp58-81.

56 Dunbar-Ortiz, 2014, p33.

57 Dunbar-Ortiz, 2014, p35.

58 On Marxism and the national question, see Karl Marx, The Irish Question and Lenin's The Right of Nations to Self-Determination. See also Crouch, 2003.

59 Estes, 2019, p7.

60 Tully, 2020, p402.

61 Foster, 2000, p221.

62 See Anderson, 2010; also Foster, Clark and Holleman, 2020.

63 Rosemont, 1989, p205.

References Abacus Data, 2020, "Energy Transition a Widely Accepted Concept; Canadians Want Governments to Work on It, not Against It" (3 January), https://abacusdata.ca/energy-transition-government-canada-support-polling-abacus Adams, Howard, 1989, Prison of Grass: Canada from a Native Point of View (Fifth House Publishers). Anderson, Kevin, 2010, Marx at the Margins: On Nationalism, Ethnicity, and Non-western Societies (University of Chicago Press). Angus Reid Institute, 2015, "Truth and Reconciliation: Canadians see Value in Process, Skeptical about Government Action" (9 July), http://angusreid.org/aboriginal-truth-and-reconciliation APTN National News, 2020, "The Facts Behind Mi'kmaw Fishing Rights", www.aptnnews.ca/national-news/the-facts-behind-mikmaw-fishing-rights Borneo Bulletin, "Rail Blockades Have to End: Canadian PM" (23 February), https://borneobulletin.com.bn/rail-blockades-end-canadian-pm British Columbia Civil Liberties Association, 2020, "Wet'suwet'en, BCCLA, and UBCIC Release Explosive Letter Revealing BC Solicitor General Authorizing RCMP Deployment, Contradicting Public Statements" (6 March), https://bccla.org/news/2020/03/release-wetsuweten-bccla-and-ubcic-release-explosive-letter-revealing-bc-solicitor-general-authorizing-rcmp-deployment-contradicting-public-statements Beaumont, Hilary, 2019, "Canada Declares Climate Emergency, Then Approves Massive Oil Pipeline Expansion", Vice (18 June), https://tinyurl.com/18p5885u Boynton, Sean, 2020, "Deltaport Shut Down by Protesters Supporting Wet'suwet'en as Blockades Continue in BC", Global News (9 February), https://globalnews.ca/news/6527933/wetsuweten-protests-deltaport-vancouver British Columbia Government Employees Union, 2020, "An Important Message for BCGEU Stewards and Officers", 11 February 2020, www.bcgeu.ca/an_important_message_for_bcgeu_stewards_and_officers British Columbia Teachers' Federation, 2020, "Solidarity Statement in Support of Unist'ot'en Camp and the Wet'suwet'en Nation", https://tinyurl.com/2ogc64t7 Brown, Alleen, and Amber Bracken, 2020, "No Surrender", The Intercept (23 February), https://theintercept.com/2020/02/23/wetsuweten-protest-coastal-gaslink-pipeline Connolly, Amanda, 2020, "Trudeau Says Wet'suwet'en Solidarity Blockades 'Need to Come Down Now'", Global News (21 February), https://globalnews.ca/news/6580215/justin-trudeau-railroad-blockade Coulthard, Glen Sean, 2014, Red Skin, White Masks: Rejecting the Colonial Politics of Recognition (University of Minnesota Press). Crouch, Dave, 2003, "Bolsheviks and Islam: Religious Rights", Socialist Review, issue 280 (December), http://socialistreview.org.uk/280/bolsheviks-and-islam-religious-rights CUPE Ontario, 2020, "CUPE Ontario Stands in Solidarity with the Wet'suwet'en Nation" (14 February), https://cupe.on.ca/cupe-ontario-stands-in-solidarity-with-the-wetsuweten-nation Daschuk, James, 2013, Clearing the Plains (University of Regina Press). Dillon, Jaskiran, and Will Parrish, 2019, "Exclusive: Canada Police Prepared to Shoot Indigenous Activists, Documents Show", Guardian (20 December), www.theguardian.com/world/2019/dec/20/canada-indigenous-land-defenders-police-documents Dunbar-Ortiz, Roxanne, 2014, An Indigenous Peoples' History of the United States (Beacon Press). Dunbar-Ortiz, Roxanne, 2016, "The Relationship between Marxism and Indigenous Struggles and Implications of the Theoretical Framework for International Indigenous Struggles", Historical Materialism, volume 24, issue 3. Edwards, Danielle, 2020, "'Not a Conservation Concern': N S Mi'kmaq Won't Deplete Lobster Stock, says Expert", CTV News (25 September), https://atlantic.ctvnews.ca/not-a-conservation-concern-n-s-mi-kmaq-won-t-deplete-lobster-stock-says-expert-1.5120296 Empson, Martin, 2014, Land and Labour: Marxism, Ecology And Human History (Bookmarks). Estes, Nick, 2019, Our History is the Future: Standing Rock Versus the Dakota Access Pipeline and the Long Tradition of Indigenous Resistance (Verso). Flanagan, Ryan, 2020, "Why are Indigenous People in Canada So Much More Likely to Be Shot and Killed By Police?", CTV News (19 June), www.ctvnews.ca/canada/why-are-indigenous-people-in-canada-so-much-more-likely-to-be-shot-and-killed-by-police-1.4989864 Forester, Brett, 2020, "Rail Disruptions 'Overblown' by Rail Companies, Politicians Says Parliamentary Budget Officer", APTN News (13 March), www.aptnnews.ca/national-news/rail-disruptions-overblown-by-rail-companies-politicians-says-parliamentary-budget-officer Foster, John Bellamy, 2020, Marx's Ecology: Materialism and Nature (Monthly Review Press). Foster, John Bellamy, Brett Clark and Hannah Holleman, 2020, "Marx and the Indigenous", Monthly Review, volume 71, number 9 (February). Harman, Chris, 1999, A People's History of the World (Bookmarks). Hopper, Tristin, 2018, "Here is What Sir John A Macdonald Did to Indigenous People", National Post (August 28), https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/here-is-what-sir-john-a-macdonald-did-to-indigenous-people Hyslop, Katie, 2020, "Wet'suwet'en Crisis: Whose Rule of Law?", The Tyee (14 Feb), https://thetyee.ca/News/2020/02/14/Wetsuweten-Crisis-Whose-Rule-Law Jacques, Ian, 2020, "Deltaport Re-opened After DPD Arrest Protesters", Delta Optimist (10 February), https://tinyurl.com/58wh2que Khan, Janaya, 2020, "Organizing Direct Action in the Digital Age", in Rodney Diverlus, Sandy Hudson and Syrus Marcus Ware (eds), Until We Are Free: Reflections on Black Lives Matter in Canada (University of Regina Press). Lukacs, Martin, 2019, The Trudeau Formula: Seduction and Betrayal in an Age of Discontent (Black Rose Books). Lukacs, Martin, 2020, "The Long Road to this Winter of Protests", The Tyee (March 27), https://thetyee.ca/Analysis/2020/03/27/The-Long-Road-This-Winter-Protests Lukacs, Martin, and Shiri Pasternak, 2020 "Industry, Government Pushed to Abolish Aboriginal Title at Issue in Wet'suwet'en Stand-off, Docs Reveal", The Narwhal (7 February), https://thenarwhal.ca/industry-government-pushed-to-abolish-aboriginal-title-at-issue-in-wetsuweten-stand-off-docs-reveal Maclean's, 2017, "Justin Trudeau's Speech in Houston: Read a Full Transcript" (10 March), www.macleans.ca/economy/justin-trudeaus-speech-in-houston-read-a-full-transcript Palmater, Pam, 2020, Warrior Life: Indigenous Resistance and Resurgence (Fernwood Publishing). Public Health Agency of Canada, 2018, Key Health Inequalities in Canada: A National Portrait, https://tinyurl.com/1p4gbn55 Reid, Jennifer, 2010, "The Doctrine of Discovery and Canadian Law", Canadian Journal of Native Studies, volume 30, issue 2, http://caid.ca/CanDocDis2010.pdf Reynolds, Christopher, 2020, "Blockade Trips Up Canada's Biggest Ports as Shippers Steer Clear of Rail Closure", The Canadian Press (February 21), https://globalnews.ca/news/6579757/blockade-trips-up-canadas-ports Robidoux, Michelle, 2020, "Via Worker on Why He Stands with Wet'suwet'en", Socialist Worker (Canada) (9 March), www.socialist.ca/node/4040 Rosemont, Franklin, 1989, "Karl Marx and the Iroquois", in Arsenal: Surrealist Subversion, by Nelson Algren et al. Black Swan, https://libcom.org/files/Franklin_Rosemont_Karl_Marx_and_the_Iroquois.pdf Roth, Christopher, 2002, "Without Treaty, Without Conquest: Indigenous Sovereignty in Post-Delgamuukw British Columbia", Wíčazo Ša Review, volume 17, number 2. Rubin, Erin, 2020, "Sacred Fires Lit to Evict Pipeline: We Are All the Answer", Nonprofit Quarterly (8 January), https://nonprofitquarterly.org/sacred-fires-lit-to-evict-pipeline-we-are-all-the-answer Scherer, Steve, and David Ljunggren, 2020, "Trudeau Says Rail Blockades Must End, Indigenous Protesters Remain Defiant", https://tinyurl.com/3vdpunv3 Shipley, Tyler, 2020, Canada in the World: Settler Capitalism and the Colonial Imagination (Fernwood Publishing). Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada, 2015, Final Report of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada: Canada's Residential Schools, part 1, volume 1, Winnipeg, 2015. www.trc.ca/assets/pdf/Volume_1_History_Part_1_English_Web.pdf Tully, James, 2020, "On Resurgence and Transformative Reconciliation", in Nancy J Turner (ed), Plants, People and Places: The Roles of Ethnobotany and Ethnoecology in Indigenous Peoples' Land Rights in Canada and Beyond (McGill-Queens University Press). Unist'ot'en Camp, 2020, "Solidarity Statements" (5 March), https://unistoten.camp/support-us/solidarity-statements United Nations General Assembly, 2019, "Adequate Housing as a Component of the Right to an Adequate Standard of Living, and the Right to Non-discrimination in This Context" (17 July), https://undocs.org/en/a/74/183 Upchurch, Martin, 2020, "Is There a New Extractive Capitalism?", International Socialism 168 (autumn).

References

Abacus Data, 2020, "Energy Transition a Widely Accepted Concept; Canadians Want Governments to Work on It, not Against It" (3 January), https://abacusdata.ca/energy-transition-government-canada-support-polling-abacus

Adams, Howard, 1989, Prison of Grass: Canada from a Native Point of View (Fifth House Publishers).

Anderson, Kevin, 2010, Marx at the Margins: On Nationalism, Ethnicity, and Non-western Societies (University of Chicago Press).

Angus Reid Institute, 2015, "Truth and Reconciliation: Canadians see Value in Process, Skeptical about Government Action" (9 July), http://angusreid.org/aboriginal-truth-and-reconciliation

APTN National News, 2020, "The Facts Behind Mi'kmaw Fishing Rights", www.aptnnews.ca/national-news/the-facts-behind-mikmaw-fishing-rights

Borneo Bulletin, "Rail Blockades Have to End: Canadian PM" (23 February), https://borneobulletin.com.bn/rail-blockades-end-canadian-pm

British Columbia Civil Liberties Association, 2020, "Wet'suwet'en, BCCLA, and UBCIC Release Explosive Letter Revealing BC Solicitor General Authorizing RCMP Deployment, Contradicting Public Statements" (6 March), https://bccla.org/news/2020/03/release-wetsuweten-bccla-and-ubcic-release-explosive-letter-revealing-bc-solicitor-general-authorizing-rcmp-deployment-contradicting-public-statements

Beaumont, Hilary, 2019, "Canada Declares Climate Emergency, Then Approves Massive Oil Pipeline Expansion", Vice (18 June), https://tinyurl.com/18p5885u

Boynton, Sean, 2020, "Deltaport Shut Down by Protesters Supporting Wet'suwet'en as Blockades Continue in BC", Global News (9 February), https://globalnews.ca/news/6527933/wetsuweten-protests-deltaport-vancouver

British Columbia Government Employees Union, 2020, "An Important Message for BCGEU Stewards and Officers", 11 February 2020, www.bcgeu.ca/an_important_message_for_bcgeu_stewards_and_officers

British Columbia Teachers' Federation, 2020, "Solidarity Statement in Support of Unist'ot'en Camp and the Wet'suwet'en Nation", https://tinyurl.com/2ogc64t7

Brown, Alleen, and Amber Bracken, 2020, "No Surrender", The Intercept (23 February), https://theintercept.com/2020/02/23/wetsuweten-protest-coastal-gaslink-pipeline

Connolly, Amanda, 2020, "Trudeau Says Wet'suwet'en Solidarity Blockades 'Need to Come Down Now'", Global News (21 February), https://globalnews.ca/news/6580215/justin-trudeau-railroad-blockade

Coulthard, Glen Sean, 2014, Red Skin, White Masks: Rejecting the Colonial Politics of Recognition (University of Minnesota Press).

Crouch, Dave, 2003, "Bolsheviks and Islam: Religious Rights", Socialist Review, issue 280 (December), http://socialistreview.org.uk/280/bolsheviks-and-islam-religious-rights

CUPE Ontario, 2020, "CUPE Ontario Stands in Solidarity with the Wet'suwet'en Nation" (14 February), https://cupe.on.ca/cupe-ontario-stands-in-solidarity-with-the-wetsuweten-nation

Daschuk, James, 2013, Clearing the Plains (University of Regina Press).

Dillon, Jaskiran, and Will Parrish, 2019, "Exclusive: Canada Police Prepared to Shoot Indigenous Activists, Documents Show", Guardian (20 December), www.theguardian.com/world/2019/dec/20/canada-indigenous-land-defenders-police-documents

Dunbar-Ortiz, Roxanne, 2014, An Indigenous Peoples' History of the United States (Beacon Press).

Dunbar-Ortiz, Roxanne, 2016, "The Relationship between Marxism and Indigenous Struggles and Implications of the Theoretical Framework for International Indigenous Struggles", Historical Materialism, volume 24, issue 3.

Edwards, Danielle, 2020, "'Not a Conservation Concern': N S Mi'kmaq Won't Deplete Lobster Stock, says Expert", CTV News (25 September), https://atlantic.ctvnews.ca/not-a-conservation-concern-n-s-mi-kmaq-won-t-deplete-lobster-stock-says-expert-1.5120296

Empson, Martin, 2014, Land and Labour: Marxism, Ecology And Human History (Bookmarks).

Estes, Nick, 2019, Our History is the Future: Standing Rock Versus the Dakota Access Pipeline and the Long Tradition of Indigenous Resistance (Verso).

Flanagan, Ryan, 2020, "Why are Indigenous People in Canada So Much More Likely to Be Shot and Killed By Police?", CTV News (19 June), www.ctvnews.ca/canada/why-are-indigenous-people-in-canada-so-much-more-likely-to-be-shot-and-killed-by-police-1.4989864

Forester, Brett, 2020, "Rail Disruptions 'Overblown' by Rail Companies, Politicians Says Parliamentary Budget Officer", APTN News (13 March), www.aptnnews.ca/national-news/rail-disruptions-overblown-by-rail-companies-politicians-says-parliamentary-budget-officer

Foster, John Bellamy, 2020, Marx's Ecology: Materialism and Nature (Monthly Review Press).

Foster, John Bellamy, Brett Clark and Hannah Holleman, 2020, "Marx and the Indigenous", Monthly Review, volume 71, number 9 (February).

Harman, Chris, 1999, A People's History of the World (Bookmarks).

Hopper, Tristin, 2018, "Here is What Sir John A Macdonald Did to Indigenous People", National Post (August 28), https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/here-is-what-sir-john-a-macdonald-did-to-indigenous-people

Hyslop, Katie, 2020, "Wet'suwet'en Crisis: Whose Rule of Law?", The Tyee (14 Feb), https://thetyee.ca/News/2020/02/14/Wetsuweten-Crisis-Whose-Rule-Law

Jacques, Ian, 2020, "Deltaport Re-opened After DPD Arrest Protesters", Delta Optimist (10 February), https://tinyurl.com/58wh2que

Khan, Janaya, 2020, "Organizing Direct Action in the Digital Age", in Rodney Diverlus, Sandy Hudson and Syrus Marcus Ware (eds), Until We Are Free: Reflections on Black Lives Matter in Canada (University of Regina Press).

Lukacs, Martin, 2019, The Trudeau Formula: Seduction and Betrayal in an Age of Discontent (Black Rose Books).

Lukacs, Martin, 2020, "The Long Road to this Winter of Protests", The Tyee (March 27), https://thetyee.ca/Analysis/2020/03/27/The-Long-Road-This-Winter-Protests

Lukacs, Martin, and Shiri Pasternak, 2020 "Industry, Government Pushed to Abolish Aboriginal Title at Issue in Wet'suwet'en Stand-off, Docs Reveal", The Narwhal (7 February), https://thenarwhal.ca/industry-government-pushed-to-abolish-aboriginal-title-at-issue-in-wetsuweten-stand-off-docs-reveal

Maclean's, 2017, "Justin Trudeau's Speech in Houston: Read a Full Transcript" (10 March), www.macleans.ca/economy/justin-trudeaus-speech-in-houston-read-a-full-transcript

Palmater, Pam, 2020, Warrior Life: Indigenous Resistance and Resurgence (Fernwood Publishing).

Public Health Agency of Canada, 2018, Key Health Inequalities in Canada: A National Portrait, https://tinyurl.com/1p4gbn55

Reid, Jennifer, 2010, "The Doctrine of Discovery and Canadian Law", Canadian Journal of Native Studies, volume 30, issue 2, http://caid.ca/CanDocDis2010.pdf

Reynolds, Christopher, 2020, "Blockade Trips Up Canada's Biggest Ports as Shippers Steer Clear of Rail Closure", The Canadian Press (February 21), https://globalnews.ca/news/6579757/blockade-trips-up-canadas-ports

Robidoux, Michelle, 2020, "Via Worker on Why He Stands with Wet'suwet'en", Socialist Worker (Canada) (9 March), www.socialist.ca/node/4040

Rosemont, Franklin, 1989, "Karl Marx and the Iroquois", in Arsenal: Surrealist Subversion, by Nelson Algren et al. Black Swan, https://libcom.org/files/Franklin_Rosemont_Karl_Marx_and_the_Iroquois.pdf

Roth, Christopher, 2002, "Without Treaty, Without Conquest: Indigenous Sovereignty in Post-Delgamuukw British Columbia", Wíčazo Ša Review, volume 17, number 2.

Rubin, Erin, 2020, "Sacred Fires Lit to Evict Pipeline: We Are All the Answer", Nonprofit Quarterly (8 January), https://nonprofitquarterly.org/sacred-fires-lit-to-evict-pipeline-we-are-all-the-answer

Scherer, Steve, and David Ljunggren, 2020, "Trudeau Says Rail Blockades Must End, Indigenous Protesters Remain Defiant", https://tinyurl.com/3vdpunv3

Shipley, Tyler, 2020, Canada in the World: Settler Capitalism and the Colonial Imagination (Fernwood Publishing).

Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada, 2015, Final Report of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada: Canada's Residential Schools, part 1, volume 1, Winnipeg, 2015. www.trc.ca/assets/pdf/Volume_1_History_Part_1_English_Web.pdf

Tully, James, 2020, "On Resurgence and Transformative Reconciliation", in Nancy J Turner (ed), Plants, People and Places: The Roles of Ethnobotany and Ethnoecology in Indigenous Peoples' Land Rights in Canada and Beyond (McGill-Queens University Press).

Unist'ot'en Camp, 2020, "Solidarity Statements" (5 March), https://unistoten.camp/support-us/solidarity-statements

United Nations General Assembly, 2019, "Adequate Housing as a Component of the Right to an Adequate Standard of Living, and the Right to Non-discrimination in This Context" (17 July), https://undocs.org/en/a/74/183

Out of the Voting Booth, Into the Streets: Revolutionaries and Electoral Politics

By James Radek

According to the dominant view on the broad liberal-left, to achieve progressive change we must elect officials with progressive politics. Liberalism claims we can eliminate the problems inherent in capitalism without eliminating capitalism itself, and by using the system created by capitalists to maintain their rule.

Social democracy (or “democratic socialism”) takes this naïve error even further. Social democrats believe we can eliminate capitalism itself within the legal and political framework of capitalism. No systemic rupture is required — we simply need to elect a critical mass of socialists to legislate a critical mass of reforms.

Revolutionary socialism holds that we must fight for reforms, but the most important part is the fight — and the organization required to mount it — not the reforms themselves.

We view all popular grievances — like poverty, war, ecological collapse, racial, national, sexual, and gender oppression — as interconnected, sharing a common source: capitalism. So the goal of Marxists is to change the global mode of production, the way we make things, from capitalism to socialism.

Marxists are champions of democracy. But only a highly circumscribed, sham democracy is possible under capitalism, where political power flows solely from economic power.

Marxists understand the state to be, in Engels’s words, “nothing but a machine for the oppression of one class by another, and indeed in the democratic republic no less than in the monarchy.” And “the executive of the modern state,” according to The Communist Manifesto, “is but a committee for managing the common affairs of the whole bourgeoisie.”

Our view of the capitalist state informs the strategies and tactics of Marxists. We see it as a weapon in the hands of the capitalist class, an antagonistic force that must be fought and ultimately smashed, not gradually improved, strengthened, or integrated with by winning office.

This may be more apparent when it comes to presidents and congresspeople, but local and regional politics offer no alternative. Every mayor is a servant of real-estate developers and whatever corporate enterprises dominate their city. The job of governors in states like Colorado is to manage the extraction of fossil fuels.

We are in the minority with this view, even among socialists. The Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) is directing radicals into an imperialist party. We’re trying to do the opposite. As Trotsky said, “Social Democracy considers itself the democratic doctor of capitalism, we are its revolutionary gravediggers.” Social-democratic ideas are providing grave misleadership to the current socialist movement by redirecting discontent, grassroots struggles, and the rising interest in socialism into the Democratic Party and electoral politics more broadly.

The Democratic Party is a capitalist and imperialist party

The Democratic Party is an irredeemably undemocratic tool of the capitalist class that cannot be reformed, utilized, or taken over by the working class and oppressed. On the contrary, it remains an impediment to working-class consciousness and organization, not in spite of, but due to the growth of a so-called socialist wing within it. The Democrats’ historic role as “the graveyard of social movements” has not changed. Its role is to absorb and neutralize discontent by rerouting it into an arena controlled by capital, where it can do no harm.

As the parties of the liberal bourgeoisie have done throughout history, the Democrats tend to the longer-term interests of the system by making minor concessions and major rhetorical appeals to our interests. Franklin Delano Roosevelt, for instance, was class-conscious of his role in granting the New Deal, which staved off revolts and revolution, while advancing the US imperial project and maintaining the racist regime of capital. As he once said, “I am the best friend the profit system ever had.”

Whether conscious of it or not, contemporary left Democrats play a similar role in disorienting would-be militants. Bernie Sanders, the Squad, and other democratic socialists didn’t popularize socialism. They gained popularity by associating themselves with socialism. And they distorted its meaning beyond recognition in the process. Now loads of random liberals are declaring themselves socialists just to get the DSA to campaign for them.

The urgency of class independence

While most of the liberal-left in the US seeks advance through the Democratic Party and the electoral system more broadly, Marxists point to class struggle as the motor force of history. Specifically this means mass, independent, militant, working-class action. Independent means class- independent — independent of the big and petty bourgeoisies. It means not sharing organizations with them, and not taking money from them, as does the Democratic Party and the NGO-industrial complex that surrounds it.

Class struggle is primarily advanced through strikes, protests, occupations, and uprisings, and the organizational forms required to cohere the class and take such actions, like trade unions, tenants’ unions, workers’ councils, and revolutionary organizations. It must not be limited by what is legal, as the law flows from and protects the profit system. Everything we do in the here and now should be in the service of the future emergence of such class coherence, organization, and combativity.

We cannot advance toward revolution unless an increasing number of workers engage in mass, independent, militant action and organize themselves accordingly. Integral to this process are: political education and experience in struggle — struggle against our enemies and amongst our allies.

How is progressive change achieved under bourgeois democracy?

Social progress occurs when the working class and oppressed make temporary advances in their irreconcilable conflict with the capitalist class. All major social reforms in US history have been the product of mass, militant struggle: from labor rights, unemployment compensation, welfare, and overtime pay in the 1930s to civil rights, abortion rights, environmental protection, affirmative action, and Medicare in the 1960s and 70s.

As Trotsky wrote, “The general Marxist thesis, ‘Social reforms are only the by-products of the revolutionary struggle,’ has in the epoch of the decline of capitalism the most immediate and burning importance. The capitalists are able to cede something to the workers only if they are threatened with the danger of losing everything.” By contrast, in Lenin’s words, “Reformist tactics are the least likely to secure real reforms.”

As the parties of the liberal bourgeoisie have done throughout history, the Democrats tend to the longer-term interests of the system by making minor concessions and major rhetorical appeals to our interests. Franklin Delano Roosevelt, for instance, was class-conscious of his role in granting the New Deal, which staved off revolts and revolution, while advancing the US imperial project and maintaining the racist regime of capital.

A ruling class may grant reforms when threatened, but it may also be willing to dispense with the façade of democracy altogether when necessary. “The constitutional road is cut by trenches held by fascist bands,” as Trotsky wrote.

The 1973 coup against Salvador Allende’s democratically-elected socialist government in Chile is a case in point. As any ruling class around the world would do when threatened by a rise in class struggle, Chilean capitalists dropped the democratic façade, slaughtered and jailed thousands, erased the gains made under Allende and before, and restored the economy to its role as their profit-making machine. The working class movement was systematically destroyed by the Pinochet regime, perhaps most dramatically via the mass internment, torture, and execution of its suspected political enemies at the National Stadium of Santiago.

The electoral road to socialism ends in a Chilean soccer stadium. Reformist socialists have not learned this lesson.

What can we learn from the history of the socialist left's approach to elections?

The Marxist political tradition warns us against what Engels called “parliamentary cretinisism” — the tendency to place all hope for social change in parliamentary institutions. But even socialists trained in Marx have shown they are not immune.

Before 1900, when many dozens of German socialists won election to parliament, Engels became increasingly alarmed at the rise of reformist tendencies. Karl Kautsky, leading member of the German Social Democratic Party (SDP) and once known as the “Pope of Marxism,” went so far as to call parliamentary activity “the most powerful lever that can be utilized to raise the proletariat out of its economic, social and moral degradation.”

At the turn of the century, Rosa Luxemburg railed against such tendencies:

People who pronounce themselves in favor of the method of legislative reform in place and in contradistinction to the conquest of political power and social revolution, do not really choose a more tranquil, calmer and slower road to the same goal, but a different goal. Instead of taking a stand for the establishment of a new society they take a stand for surface modifications of the old society.

The history of socialists’ attempts to reform the state and vote socialism into power has resulted in socialists adapting to nationalism, becoming managers of austerity and imperialism, disorienting and disorganizing the working class, and making no advance toward overturning the reign of capital. This is true across the history of European socialism — from the Second International’s betrayal of the international working class by supporting “their own” national bourgeoisies in World War I, to the eurocommunism of the 1970s and 80s, all the way up to SYRIZA in 2015.

In the 1930s, under the influence of Stalin, the Communist Party in the US pursued a class-collaborationist policy that led them to support FDR and the Democrats. This undermined the possibilities for a militant workers’ movement, significant reforms, the popularizing of left-wing politics, or the emergence of an independent labor party in the United States. Today, the DSA is doing the same thing, squandering the rising interest in socialism.

Many other US socialists in the early to mid-20th century, including James Cannon, Hal Draper, and Eugene Debs, upheld the Marxist principle of class independence.

In 1948, James Cannon offered this defense of class independence that is worth quoting at length:

It has been argued here that ‘we must go through the experiences with the workers.’ That is a very good formula, provided you do not make it universal. We go with the workers only through those experiences which have a class nature. We go with them through the experiences of strikes, even though we may think a given strike untimely. We may even go with the workers through the experience of putting a reformist labor party in office, provided it is a real labor party and subject to certain pressures of the workers, in order that they may learn from their experience that reformism is not the correct program for the working class.

But we do not go through the experience of class collaboration with the workers. There we draw the line. We did not go through the experience of the workers when they supported the imperialist war. We drew back when they went through the experience of people’s fronts in Europe. We stood on the side and we told them they were wrong. We did not compromise ourselves. If another man takes poison, you do not have to join him in the experiment. Just tell him it is no good. But don’t offer to prove it by your personal example.

What does a revolutionary socialist approach to elections look like?

While Marxists do not consider the capitalist state to be a vehicle for socialist transformation, we also oppose abstentionism. We don’t counterpose elections to strikes, protests, occupations, and uprisings. Rather, we seek to integrate all forms of struggle into a comprehensive strategy for revolution. While we decry the limitations of bourgeois democracy, we prefer it to the alternatives under capitalism, such as authoritarianism and fascism. Political freedoms, like the right of assembly, association, free speech, and a free press, are valuable gains of past struggle that help us further our own class interests.

For Marx and Engels, electoral victories were subordinate to independent working-class political action. As an example, in 1850, they gave an address to the Communist League in London that, 50 years later, Lenin found so compelling that he memorized it, enjoyed reciting it, and fought for it to become the core of Bolshevik electoral strategy. Here’s a key passage from that address:

Even when there is no prospect whatever of their being elected, the workers must put up their own candidates in order to preserve their independence, to count their forces and to lay before the public their revolutionary attitude and party standpoint. In this connection they must not allow themselves to be bribed by such arguments of the democrats as, for example, that by doing so they are splitting the democratic party and giving the reactionaries the possibility of victory. The ultimate purpose of all such phrases is to dupe the proletariat. The advance which the proletariat party is bound to make by such independent action is infinitely more important than the disadvantage that might be incurred by the presence of a few reactionaries in the representative body.

To break this down, first of all: winning isn’t everything! The point of a revolutionary socialist electoral campaign is not to get elected. We don’t want to become managers of austerity and imperialism for the capitalist state. We want to overthrow it. We don’t want to dedicate our lives to tweaking the system or winning tiny concessions that can be swept away with the stroke of a pen by the next elected official.

The history of socialists’ attempts to reform the state and vote socialism into power has resulted in socialists adapting to nationalism, becoming managers of austerity and imperialism, disorienting and disorganizing the working class, and making no advance toward overturning the reign of capital.

We do want to “lay before the public our revolutionary attitude and party standpoint” — in other words to propagate socialist politics and build revolutionary organization. Electoral campaigns and elected offices can serve as big platforms to expose the system and encourage struggle against it.

And the insistence on class independence, even when it may lead to right-wing victories, is another important position that is sadly unpopular on the liberal-left, where safe-state strategies and lesser-evilism dominate. In 2020, for instance, the Party for Socialism & Liberation (PSL) ran its own candidate for president — but if Bernie Sanders had won the Democratic nomination, they committed to not running their candidate in swing states to avoid splitting the vote.

In 1906, Lenin addressed the matter of socialists forming blocs with liberals to stave off reactionaries in this way:

We would undermine the principles and the general revolutionary significance of our campaign for the sake of gaining a seat of the Duma for a liberal! We would be subordinating class policy to parliamentarism instead of subordinating parliamentarism to class policy. We would deprive ourselves of the opportunity to gain an estimate of our forces. We would lose what is lasting and durable in all elections — the development of the class consciousness and solidarity of the socialist proletariat. We would gain what is transient, relative and untrue — superiority of the Cadet over the Octobrist.

Nowhere in Marx and Engels’s 1850 address do they mention changing the system from within. The focus is always on the self-activity of militant workers. Lenin warned that socialists elected to the First Duma should “avoid getting sucked into the minutia of law making” — what Engels called “project-mongering” — and focus on making appeals to the people. This approach was later generalized by the Third International in 1920, which resolved that, “The Communist Party does not enter these institutions [bourgeois governments] in order to carry out organic work there [reforms], but in order to help the masses from inside parliament to break up the state machine and parliament itself through action.”

For Marxists, class struggle is both the way to win reforms now and the basis for the future revolutionary transformation of capitalism into socialism. Marxists assess electoral campaigns according to how they impact class struggle. When workers break away from support for capitalist parties and run their own working-class candidates against them, this advances class consciousness and can lay the basis for an increase in class struggle. This is why Marxists agitate for the formation of a working-class political party. We do not think that electing a labor party to office within the capitalist electoral system can bring about socialism — that will require revolution.

Conclusion

So, where does all of this leave us? Should we support the lesser evil? Hal Draper, then of the Independent Socialist Club, one of our predecessor organizations, dealt with this question in the late 60s:

So who was really the Lesser Evil in 1964 [Lyndon Johnson or Barry Goldwater]? The point is that it is the question which is a disaster, not the answer. In setups where the choice is between one capitalist politician and another, the defeat comes in accepting the limitation to this choice.

We stand in that political tradition. Lesser-evilism has no bottom, no lower limit to the politics one must support by its logic, as “Genocide Joe” Biden has proven in recent months. It only lowers our horizons and keeps us fixated on electoral solutions.

Should we support left candidates outside of the two dominant capitalist parties? That was the practice of the International Socialist Organization , which many of us came out of. The ISO was so fixated on breaking with the Democrats that it ended up supporting and running candidates through the Green Party, a horribly confused, politically eclectic, petit-bourgeois formation. That is not what is meant by independent.

There is a crisis of legitimacy around elections and, while most socialists try to assuage people’s concerns and urge them back to the ballot box, we have chosen to affirm the crisis.

What is the point of supporting a candidate from an organization you are not a member of and do not wish to build? Just to relate to people excited by their campaign? We don’t need to join a campaign to do that.

This orientation also resulted in a critique of electoralism that didn’t go far enough. It seems the ISO was uncomfortable with lacking an answer on who to vote for.

In Prisoners of the American Dream, the late, great Mike Davis wrote:

In no other capitalist country is mass political abstentionism as fully developed as in the United States, where a ‘silent majority’ of the working class has sat out more than half the elections of the last century. Arguably, this mute, atomized protest is the historical correlative of the striking absence of an independent political party of the proletariat in the country that once invented both the labor party and May Day.

Identifying with mass abstentionist instincts doesn’t mean we have to become abstentionists though. Whether we run our own candidates is not a question of principle, but tactics. For now, we are far too small to devote the enormous energy it would take to mount electoral campaigns that would serve our goals. The electoral arena is also dangerous territory to enter for a revolutionary organization that is not unwaveringly committed to the Marxist approach I’ve tried to outline here. The siren song of reformism can be very tempting. And to run for office while declaring that bourgeois democracy only veils the rule of capital is a tricky needle to thread from a messaging standpoint.

When questions about what to do at the ballot box arise, revolutionary socialists must get comfortable answering there is no one to vote for . There are no electoral solutions to the problems we face. Our promise and power lie elsewhere.

Why Socialists Don't Vote for Our Enemies

By Max Jay

Joe Biden's withdrawal from the presidential race and the candidacy of Kamala Harris has changed the character of the coming election. Instead of just another in the endless, monotonous slog of election cycles, with the same two candidates reprising the previous contest, this election now has an air of excitement to it. Suddenly the Democratic Party is actually interested in campaigning.

This new situation provides both an opportunity and a challenge for revolutionary socialists in testing our approach to electoral politics. Our view of elections is not the same as those of liberals or progressives, in which individual voters express their politics by choosing between the available options. Socialist politics are necessarily a collective effort, struggling together to free humanity from oppression and exploitation. We therefore have to make all our strategic decisions collectively and then implement them, with the aim of winning liberation.

“You got to make a distinction”

A key component of revolutionary working-class politics is consistently supporting the working class in opposition to the capitalist class. We cannot build up one side by giving our support to the other. Fred Hampton once said:

But when I leave, you can remember I said, with the last words on my lips, that I am a revolutionary, and you're going to have to keep on saying that. You're going to have to say that I am a proletarian. I am the people. I am not the pig. You got to make a distinction, and the people are going to have to attack the pig. The people are going to have to stand up against the pig.

(emphasis mine)

Not long after delivering this speech, Hampton was assassinated in a coordinated effort between the Nixon administration, the Chicago Police Department, and the FBI. A brief thought experiment seems appropriate. Imagine a ballot with three candidates: Fred Hampton of the Black Panther Party, the Chicago Police Department, and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. In this election, it should be a no-brainer for socialists to support and vote for Hampton and the Panthers.

But what if there were only two candidates on the ballot? Would socialists endorse the CPD or the FBI? Those two organizations are certainly not the same, and arguments could conceivably be made that one or the other is less harmful. However, they are obviously both part of the repressive apparatus of the capitalist state, and we as socialists have to make a distinction.

Foundations of a Marxist approach to elections

In their 1850 “Address of the Central Committee to the Communist League,” Marx and Engels, writing in the aftermath of the revolutions of 1848, take up the question of political organization and elections—particularly in the context of the rise to power of the German bourgeoisie.[1]_ They acknowledge that the working class is not the only class oppressed by the state. The petty bourgeoisie and the peasantry are likewise in opposition, so the question of who to run in elections, and who if anyone to join forces with, is an important one.

Marx and Engels argue that:

Workers' candidates [must be] nominated everywhere in opposition to bourgeois-democratic candidates. As far as possible they should be League members and their election should be pursued by all possible means. Even where there is no prospect of achieving their election the workers must put up their own candidates to preserve their independence, to gauge their own strength and to bring their revolutionary position and party standpoint to public attention.

The goal of getting workers' candidates elected is certainly there, but the point is that elections can also serve as an opportunity to present socialist politics to broader layers of the working class, and to gauge what kind of support exists for them. You'll notice that Marx and Engels are not concerned here with “splitting the vote” by undermining a bourgeois-democratic candidate and leaving the door open for something worse; the focus is on building working-class politics and organization through elections.

Just what exactly “something worse” might look like became clear when Lenin and the Bolsheviks took up these basics decades later.[2]_ In the 1906 elections to the Duma, the Russian parliament, Russian Marxists had to decide how to address the threat of the violently ultranationalist Tsarist group the Black Hundreds. The Mensheviks (the Bolsheviks' more moderate Marxist rivals) argued that Marxists should form electoral alliances with liberal groups, specifically the Cadets, a liberal monarchist party, to keep the Hundreds out of the Duma. This would have entailed supporting Cadet candidates and avoiding “splitting the vote” by fielding candidates in opposition to the Cadets.

Imagine a ballot with three candidates: Fred Hampton of the Black Panther Party, the Chicago Police Department, and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. In this election, it should be a no-brainer for socialists to support and vote for Hampton and the Panthers. But what if there were only two candidates on the ballot? Would socialists endorse the CPD or the FBI?

Lenin identified three problems with this approach. Firstly: would this alliance have actually reduced the danger of the Black Hundreds? Despite their differing politics, both the Hundreds and the Cadets recognized the authority of the Tsar and the legitimacy of the Tsarist state. With the Hundreds frequently waging bloody anti-Jewish pogroms with either the tacit or explicit approval of the Tsar, it would have been foolish to expect the Cadets to consistently and directly oppose the Hundreds. Making an electoral alliance would have sent the message to the working class that the Cadets could actually be trusted. It would have been misleading the working-class movement.

The second problem is that this would have effectively surrendered leadership of the movement to the Cadets. The Cadets were certainly going to be running their candidates, regardless of what the Marxists did, so avoiding splitting the vote would, in practice, have entailed Marxists standing down and endorsing Cadet candidates. Having acquired the support of the political forces to their left, the Cadets would have been able to masquerade as the voice of the working class and oppressed. As Lenin wrote at the time, “Why should the Cadets get to pretend to be democrats?” Rather than taking the opportunity to put forward communist politics, the alliances favored by the Mensheviks would have ceded leadership and political influence to the Cadets.

The last problem is that placing primary emphasis on Duma elections as a strategy for opposing the Black Hundreds would itself have been a mistake and misunderstands the role of parliament. Keeping proto-fascists out of office does not mean you have defeated them. Rather, they have to be defeated politically and in the streets by a mass working-class movement.

Lesser-evilism

US socialist Hal Draper took this approach into the late 20th century in his pamphlet “Who's going to be the lesser-evil in 1968?”[3] It's an enduring and decisive argument that deserves to be revisited in its entirety by socialists every election year.

Draper begins with what he calls the “classic case” of lesser-evilism, the appointment of Hitler to the position of chancellor in 1933 by President Hindenburg, the very person who had defeated him in the election. In this situation, we can see the proof of Lenin's argument regarding the Black Hundreds above; not only did voting for a lesser evil not stop the rise of fascism, it didn't even slow it down. As Draper famously put it, “the people voted for the Lesser Evil and got both.”

The US in 1967 was a very different situation than Germany in 1932, of course, but this is exactly the point. Germany was facing a social crisis the existing government had no way to resolve, and the choice in the immediate term was revolution or fascism. These are the highest stakes imaginable, but even here, falling back and voting for a conservative to fight back fascism didn't work. So why, in 2024, when the threat of an immediate fascist takeover of the state is not on the table, would the strategy be any more advisable?

Germany was facing a social crisis the government had no way to resolve, and the choice in the immediate term was revolution or fascism. These are the highest stakes imaginable, but even here, falling back and voting for a conservative to fight fascism didn't work. So why, in 2024, when the threat of an immediate fascist takeover is not on the table, would the strategy be any more advisable?

Draper gives the example of the 1964 election, in which “people convinced themselves that Lyndon Johnson was the lesser evil as against Goldwater, who was going to do Horrible Things in Vietnam, like defoliating the jungles.” In reality the liberal Johnson did exactly that, widely deploying Agent Orange and inflicting devastating damage to public health in Vietnam; the deadly herbicide continued to kill people for decades after the formal end of the war.

Some of Johnson's former supporters complained that he “actually carried out Goldwater's policy,” but this is actually unfair to Goldwater, who never proposed anything on the scale of Johnson's violence. Draper attributes this to Johnson's ability to “hypnotize the liberals with ‘Great Society' rhetoric”—that is, holding up all of the progressive domestic reforms to cover for their continuing maintenance of empire and capital.

This classic liberal maneuver means that liberal supporters come into every election claiming that the fascists are coming and everyone needs to vote for the lesser evil. Democrats therefore know that they have the liberal vote in their back pocket and don't need to do anything to win it. Instead, what they do have to do is appease the forces to their right. This process has forced politics in the US to “move steadily right-right-right—until even a Lyndon Johnson could look like a lesser evil.”

Hopefully this sounds familiar. It didn't stop with the Johnson administration and hasn't stopped yet. While there are key differences between Draper's time and ours, supporting the lesser evil over multiple election cycles undercuts any ability for the left to actually fight the far right.

Draper was writing in 1967, in the context of the postwar American economy, and he argues that both liberals and conservatives were at the time converging under “bureaucratic-statified capitalism,” the system of capitalism that existed in the US at the time. He gives the example of Truman vetoing Taft-Hartley, an anti-union bill, and then invoking it against striking workers. Liberals always have to make use of repressive measures that conservatives advocate, and conservatives at the time were forced to maintain the welfare state, because that was what the maintenance of the system demanded. No electoral choice on offer was in any way willing to challenge the established structure of the state.

Commonalities

We can see the common shape of the revolutionary socialist approach to elections emerging from these writers. Each of them views the question as one for a revolutionary organization, or for the entire movement—not for the individual.

When we talk about voting in the US, the framing of the discussion is often, “Who should I vote for?” or “Who should I feel bad about voting for?” or “Who can I stomach voting for?” as though we're shopping for the least-expired carton of milk in the supermarket. Socialists need to approach elections differently, as a political event into which we seek to intervene collectively. We need to aim to make strategic decisions as a group.

Additionally, there is a focus in the revolutionary tradition on political dynamics on a much longer scale than one election cycle. Everyone on the left has, at one point or another, become frustrated with the mysterious amnesia that afflicts liberals every two to four years, enabling them to treat each election as a new crisis out of the blue, requiring new concessions every time. This is both a cause and an effect of what Draper describes as politics moving “right-right-right.” If both “lesser” and “greater” evils are further to right every election, it is necessary for liberals to forget what their own candidates from a few years ago said and did. At the same time, this rightward march means that each cycle brings new horrors from segments of the right that were not long ago completely outside the mainstream, to which liberals respond with their cries about impending fascism.

Socialists need to take a longer view so we can understand the political and economic dynamics that shape society, and plan our strategy accordingly. After all, Draper would never have been able to formulate his diagnosis of lesser-evilism if he limited his observations to one election cycle.

That said, socialists should view every election as a political opportunity to put forward our politics and win people to them. The guiding principle is to orient the working class toward confrontation with capitalism. As was the case with Lenin versus the Cadets, we can never afford to concede political leadership to the capitalist class, or worse, provide them with cover from the left.

The capitalist state and the executive under neoliberalism

Our situation is different from 1967. For one thing, we no longer live under the system of statified capitalism described by Draper. That postwar boom, which constituted the longest period of growth and stability in the history of capitalism, and was the only time the US had anything like a functioning welfare state due to economic expansion and an established labor movement, doesn't exist anymore.

The economic crisis of the 1970s led the capitalist class to look for new solutions, and what it arrived at is neoliberalism. Rather than the fairly large form of capitalist state that compels liberals and conservatives alike to act to maintain it, neoliberalism introduced rampant privatization and financialization. Under neoliberalism, the US and other countries began hacking off parts of the state to sell to private enterprise, furthering control of the market by financial institutions and weakening the ability of the state to intervene economically. At the same time, massive attacks on organized labor and shifts toward more casual and precarious forms of employment further weakened the working class.

Ideologically, neoliberalism is usually accompanied by rhetoric about small government and personal responsibility, such as Margaret Thatcher's famous statement: “There is no such thing as society.” The idea here is that there isn't any large collectivity, only rationally self-interested individuals and the nuclear family. Everything should be privatized.

But if there is no society, what is the function of the state? Thatcher, naturally, was lying. She and Ronald Reagan and the generations of neoliberal politicians who have followed them have had no actual interest in dismantling or shrinking the capitalist state. The question is which pieces they wish to preserve.

When we talk about voting in the US, the framing of the discussion is often, “Who should I vote for?” or “Who should I feel bad about voting for?” or “Who can I stomach voting for?” as though we're shopping for the least-expired carton of milk in the supermarket. Socialists need to approach elections differently, as a political event into which we seek to intervene collectively.

The Marxist conception of the state is that it is the means by which one class imposes its will on another. The capitalist state aims to stabilize and maintain profit extraction in the interests of the capitalist class as a whole. Despite all the privatization of neoliberalism, these repressive functions of the state persist and have indeed expanded. We can't have healthcare, but the army, the police, public banking institutions, and other state bodies continue to repress the working class and keep the bosses' interests secure.

The president serves as the captain of the capitalist state, and always has. This is both an extremely powerful position and an extremely limited one that does not allow for experimentation or any but the most surface-level reforms. The job of the president is to maintain the neoliberal state, no more or less—just as it was to maintain the postwar bureaucratic state in Draper's era.

Imagine our best, most politically unwavering, and charismatic communist—say, for instance, this author. If I were somehow elected to the presidency right now, in the absence of an extremely formidable mass working-class movement, I would have the choice to either serve the interests of capital or to be quickly and probably violently removed.

We have seen this throughout the history of capitalism, perhaps most clearly in the doomed presidency of Salvadore Allende in Chile in 1973.

Neoliberalism has been afflicted by crises of its own, especially after the global financial collapse of 2008. The credibility of governments worldwide has been severely damaged, contributing to the rise of the far right. The committed parties of neoliberalism, like the Democrats, are at a loss for ways to resolve these crises, and the far right is putting forward its solutions.

This instability is no reason to fall back to supporting Democrats, however. If we are to make any headway under whatever economic order may supplant neoliberalism, we will need our political independence more than ever.

Lesser-evilism since Draper

The exploits of the Democrats in their steady march “right-right-right” since Draper's essay could fill and have filled books. But to briefly recap:

The Clinton administration destroyed such welfare as existed in the US and decisively removed the idea of even basic responsibility toward the poor on the part of the government from official political respectability. These attacks on welfare were met with virtually no pushback from liberal organizations, as might have been expected had Reagan or George H. W. Bush attempted such a move. Clinton also imposed brutal sanctions on Iraq; in defense of this policy, Madeleine Albright famously claimed of the 500,000 Iraqi children who died by starvation, “We think the price is worth it.”

Liberal supporters come into every election claiming that the fascists are coming and everyone needs to vote for the lesser evil. Democrats therefore know that they have the liberal vote in their back pocket and don't need to do anything to win it. Instead, what they do have to do is appease the forces to their right. This process has forced politics in the US to “move steadily right-right-right.”

After the widely reviled administration of George W. Bush, characterized by the invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq and the expansion of the federal repressive apparatus, including the PATRIOT Act, Barack Obama took office on the crest of a wave of liberal optimistic fervor. It is easy to forget the degree to which liberals felt this was a decisive political and cultural shift in their favor. The antiwar movement, which had grown under Bush, very nearly disappeared, in no small part because major organizations believed Obama would end the wars and close the US torture prison at Guantanamo Bay. He did neither of these things, and in fact expanded the so-called War on Terror (with a new fervor for drone-bombing), the repressive powers of the PATRIOT Act, and the repression of social movements like Occupy. He also became known as “Deporter-in-Chief” for his draconian policies towards immigrants. We should remember that the Black Lives Matter movement and the Standing Rock pipeline opposition originated under and were militarily attacked by the Obama administration.

True to form, our most recent “lesser evil,” Joe Biden, has expanded many of the repressive measures of his predecessor, from attacks on antiracist organizers to the maintenance of the US's southern concentration camps. He pleaded powerlessness as the right to abortion was overturned, and preemptively broke a railroad strike, outlawing the strike before the authorization vote could even be held. Most importantly, he has continued the US's direct facilitation of the genocide in Palestine, which began in 1948 but reached horrifying new levels of mass violence in 2023 and 2024. In backing genocide, Biden has pushed the idea of “lesser” evil to its theoretical limits.

What is different with Harris?

The nomination of Kamala Harris after Biden's decision to withdraw has changed the shape of the upcoming election. While lesser-evilism has not changed at its core, the difference between the two Democrats and their approaches has thus far been striking.

Perhaps most importantly for socialists in our work organizing face-to-face during an election year, we can expect much more enthusiasm from the Democratic base. Democrats finally have someone they actually want to campaign for now, in contrast to the grimmer lesser-evilism that was reluctantly mobilized to defend Biden. Appallingly, this will require Harris supporters to tacitly accept the genocide in Palestine.

We should also expect a renewed strength of pseudo-anti-oppression arguments to rally votes. The Democrats were already attempting this, with various editorials and astroturfed social-media presences claiming it was racist to demand Biden step down—the argument being that all Black people supported Biden—but they had, at best, limited success with this. Having lucked into a candidate who is both Black and a woman, the attempts to frame support for the Democratic candidate as not actually a lesser evil but rather a progressive champion will only grow in strength.

Socialists should view every election as a political opportunity to put forward our politics and win people to them. The guiding principle is to orient the working class toward confrontation with capitalism. We can never afford to concede political leadership to the capitalist class, or worse, provide them with cover from the left.

We must also, however, be prepared to oppose racist and sexist attacks on Harris from the right. The worst reactionaries will attempt to mobilize on this basis, and will no doubt see her nomination as an avenue for projecting their politics. As much as we resolutely oppose Harris and the Democrats on principle, socialists have to fight racism and sexism everywhere it occurs.

The campaign for Harris will capitalize on people's sense of relief at being rid of Biden. The political impact of this is not to be underestimated; despite nearly the entire Democratic apparatus supporting him well into the campaign, and Harris being the sitting vice president, the campaign appears to be revitalized from its moribund near-acceptance of defeat only a couple of months ago.

The weirdo GOP goblins who have moved from the darker fringes of the internet to the center of the Republican Party appear to have no clear idea of how to deal with a Harris candidacy. They will probably get their shit together eventually, but for the time being, this has led to a very confident Democratic campaign.

Lastly, the Democrats will use Harris's record as a prosecutor as a selling point. It fits perfectly with the established Democratic messaging about how Donald Trump is a convict. We have already seen her hammer a law-and-order narrative in her remarks at the Democratic National Convention, establishing Trump as a criminal and Harris as the law. Tellingly, Harris makes use of this narrative to argue that she will be even tougher on border “security” than Trump.

On the other hand, we should also expect the student intifada to be targets of this security-mindedness, along with any other oppositional left-wing movement.[4]_

The socialist approach to the Harris campaign

So, does the candidacy of Kamala Harris present socialists with a situation in which we need to abandon our longstanding opposition to both parties of capital?

In short, no. We have a different political terrain in front of us than we did recently, but the renewed enthusiasm for the party of union-busting, repression of protest, and genocide does not mean we should change our political orientation.

Unlike those political currents that would see such a shift toward the Democrats as a call to turn to the right to gather easy supporters, we should see it as a confirmation of the importance of maintaining our political independence, and only ever granting political support to the opponents of capitalism.

We must also be prepared to oppose racist and sexist attacks on Harris from the right. The worst reactionaries will attempt to mobilize on this basis, and will no doubt see her nomination as an avenue for projecting their politics. As much as we resolutely oppose Harris and the Democrats on principle, socialists have to fight racism and sexism everywhere it occurs.

The new confidence of the Harris campaign masks the chaos that led to it. The Democratic Party has fumbled and bumbled its way to a candidate who is genuinely popular. This in no way addresses the actual problems faced by the working class, which persist across and between election years.

We should keep in mind that, for a lot of our audience, this is going to be a difficult concept to grasp, let alone act on, especially with the left as historically weak as it is. People aren't seeing convincing socialist candidates being put forward, or any socialist organizations capable of doing that, so it's our job to continue to build these organizations so that we can begin to act in the electoral sphere and pose a reasonable alternative one day in the future.

More importantly, we have to win people to the idea that an electoral campaign is not the ultimate expression of politics, nor even a primary battleground, and to convince them to work with us to build social movements, labor struggles, and revolutionary organizations that can fight back. To do this, we have to stand outside of the Democratic Party and in direct political opposition to it, not least when it has a popular candidate. Our long-term goal is the construction of a revolutionary party that can lead the struggle to overthrow capitalism; every decision we make in the electoral arena must be in service of this goal.[5]_

Kamala Harris is a former prosecutor and current cheerleader for genocide. We can expect that, should she win, her administration will be another in the long line of Democrats moving “right-right-right.” There is nothing to be won by the working class helping her get the job.

The conclusion that all this should lead us to, and that we need to be prepared to argue for in an election year, is that we grant no support for any party of capital. We will not be supporting our oppressors, even if our candidates are not yet on the ballot. These are the principles that will best enable us to build a robust socialist left.

[1]

Karl Marx and Frederick Engels, “Address of the Central Committee to the Communist League,” 1850.

[2]

See V. I. Lenin, “The Elections to the Duma and the Tactics of the Russian Social-Democrats,” 1906.

[3]

Hal Draper, “The Lesser of Two Evils,” 1967.

[4]

See “Advances, Limits and Lessons of the Student Intifada,” Firebrand, June 2024.

[5]

See “In Defense of Revolutionary Organization,” Firebrand, June 2023.

Chile '73: Was victory possible?

By Pablo Torres and Dauno Tótoro

The “Chilean road” to socialism—that is, the electoral road—is not only the predominant strategy of Chile's Communist Party and the Frente Amplio, but also a central reference point for reformist organizations like the DSA in the United States.

On September 4, 1970, Salvador Allende was elected president of Chile. The victory of the Unidad Popular (UP) marked the beginning of a pre-revolutionary era—one that would last one thousand days until the coup d'état.

The election was a political earthquake that surprised every social class in the country. In factories and workplaces, in cities and towns, and even among troops and noncommissioned officers in the barracks, celebrations broke out after Allende's triumph. Tens of thousands joined the festivities in the streets that night. In business circles, rich neighborhoods, and right-wing political parties, as well as among officers of the armed forces, the fury and tension were palpable.

Confusion reigned among Chilean capitalists after the results were announced. How could they prevent Allende's victory from being proclaimed by the congress? How could they prevent him from taking office?[1]_ The country's reactionary forces immediately began planning to keep him from assuming the presidency, or overthrow him if he did.

The counterrevolutionary bloc would be led by an alliance of right-wing politicians and big capitalists, along with U.S. imperialism and its corporations. The CIA and Agustín Edwards (owner of the newspaper El Mercurio) developed two different plans for a coup: a “constitutional” (or parliamentary) plan and a “military” plan. But the first coup failed after the defeat of a military maneuver carried out by a group of extreme-right militants who murdered the army's commander-in-chief, “constitutionalist” René Schneider. The event shook the nation, and the backlash that ensued would facilitate the proclamation of Allende's victory by the congress.

Chile was undergoing not only a revolutionary process, but also a counterrevolutionary one that would be decisive in the country's political dynamics. After Chile's independence in 1810, its national ruling class, composed of a landed oligarchy born out of conquest and colonization, underwent a process of bourgeoisification through its alliances with imperialist (English and then U.S.) commercial and financial capital. But with nineteenth-century capitalist development, a new national bourgeoisie arose—a partner of both the old oligarchy and the commercial-financial sector. Chilean capitalism developed on the basis of the dominance of foreign capital, i.e. as a semicolony, while the old colonial or precapitalist agrarian structure remained intact.

Chile's ruling class never hesitated to use force when its interests were threatened, not only against external forces, but also against challenges to the social order coming from the nation's own exploited and oppressed people. The Left (mainly the Communist and Socialist Parties) was dominated by a pacifist vision and a strategy of institutional “maneuvers” in order to avoid waging battle against big capital.

This strategy was rooted in a theory of Chilean “exceptionalism.” According to this theory, Chile's “advanced” democracy and democratic traditions (the rule of law and parliamentarism), along with its active civil society and system of stable institutions, constituted an “integral state.” That is to say, conditions made it possible to carry out a revolution “democratically,” thereby avoiding the threat of civil war. The retreat of the armed forces after the Great Depression reinforced the view of a supposedly constitutional military. But this “democratic” regime had outlawed the Communist Party for ten years (1948–58), imprisoning communists in modern Chile's first detention camp, Pisagua, in the northern desert.

The Bourgeoisie on the Defensive

The failure of the first coup attempt isolated the Right, infusing broad swathes of the masses with a democratic spirit. The Right, facing widespread rejection, was forced to retreat.

Shored up by this sentiment, Allende and the UP established a pact with the Christian Democratic Party (DC), whose votes gave Allende the absolute majority he needed to be proclaimed president. The DC, which had not supported the coup attempt, helped broker the agreement with the UP so that it could moderate tendencies toward radicalization and intensifying class conflict. The result was the Pact of Constitutional Guarantees, in which the DC imposed a “programmatic” agreement on the UP so that the latter would reaffirm its respect for the liberal order. This agreement, without which Allende would not have become president, allowed the DC to enforce certain “guarantees” for the protection of public order: the defense of the state's monopoly on weapons, the prohibition on unofficial armed forces, and the protection of property rights by limiting the Social Property Area proposed by Allende.

The pact with the DC went hand-in-hand with the dissolution of the Popular Unity Committees (CUP), which were formed to promote the election campaign in factories, neighborhoods, schools, hospitals, and universities. There were, according to some authors, as many as fifteen thousand CUPs. All of them were subordinated to the UP's National Command, composed of leaders from the main member parties. According to the CUPs' initial program, they “would be interpreters and fighters for the immediate demands of the masses and, above all, would prepare to exercise people's power.” Yet they played the role of electoral committees, not organizations of social struggle and action. After Allende's victory, they were dissolved. Under a revolutionary leadership, these committees would have been the foundation for developing bodies of mass self-organization that could confront any counterrevolutionary coup attempts.

From the Celebration to the Right-Wing Offensive

With the retreat of the disoriented Right, the UP grew stronger. It moved forward with its program of nationalizations (with compensation) of copper and iron mines and the banking system, and it embarked on a path toward nationalizing 91 strategic industries, pursuing an agrarian reform, and so on.

Allende's victory took place in the context of rising struggles of workers, peasants, and poor people. Although the newly formed government sought to channel these struggles into bourgeois institutions, it created openings for the class struggle, which eventually surpassed the limits of the UP.

Shortly after Allende took office, in December 1970, there was a surge in land occupations in the southern region of Panguipulli, where thirty-four estates were taken over by workers, peasants, and the indigenous Mapuche people. The land occupations forced the government to accelerate its implementation of the agrarian reform.

Meanwhile, there was a similar rise in struggles in the cities. In 1969, there were 977 strikes, while in 1972 there were 3,526. Factory occupations were practically nonexistent in 1969, when only 24 took place, but the number rose to 378 in 1971. In just the first five months of 1972, 299 factories were occupied.

In April 1971, the UP won slim majorities in the municipal elections across the country. After the opposition's electoral defeat, both the DC and the National Party (PN) sought to change their strategy. The Right adopted a mixed strategy that involved not only political struggle in congress, but also a struggle to take over the streets.

Around this time, the first signs of an economic crisis appeared, with shortages and inflation. The Right seized the opportunity to rear its head again, seeking to win hegemony over the middle classes by combining parliamentary and extra-parliamentary struggles. The Right launched its first major street action with the “march of pots and pans” on December 1, 1971, seeking to engage women in politics.

In by-elections held in January 1972, the DC and the PN ran together, defeating the UP in the provinces of O'Higgins, Colchagua, and Linares. These electoral alliances were the foundations of what would become a strategic coalition.

The right-wing offensive and these first tactical alliances between the DC and the PN, in the context of growing signs of an economic crisis, began to strain the UP. Allende, the Communist Party, and a minority of the Socialist Party (PS), defended the UP's alliance with the DC and a strategy of “consolidation to move forward.” Another sector of the PS and the Popular Unitary Action Movement (MAPU) wanted the government to “radicalize” the process, breaking out of the bourgeois legal framework to establish “people's power.” They argued for the establishment of alliances with the Revolutionary Left Movement (MIR).

The strain on the UP was a distorted reflection of the growing tensions between its social base—workers, peasants, poor people, and their vanguard, who sought to achieve their revolutionary goals through class struggle—and its leadership, which sought to reform the system and achieve a kind of “state capitalism,” which would limit the people's growing revolutionary aspirations.

Protests and street clashes increased in the context of economic sabotage, shortages, and inflation, in addition to “strikes” by merchants and truck drivers, which were mobilized and organized by the Right. The opposition's offensive called for “civil resistance.” In August 1972, 125,000 stores closed after a lockout was called. Fascist brigades blocked traffic with barricades and launched attacks. In October 1972, the truck drivers led a new leap forward in the reactionary offensive: the “insurrection of the bourgeoisie,” shown in the documentary La Batalla de Chile by Patricio Guzmán. Companies were closed, roads were blocked, and acts of sabotage were carried out, resulting in economic chaos and a relative dismantling of the state apparatus. This left the government virtually suspended, with no real ability to respond.

But there was one force that actually managed to resist the reactionary offensive: the self-organized workers, peasants, and poor people. Factory occupations confronted the bosses' sabotage, transport companies were taken over, and workers and peasants coordinated efforts for the production, exchange, and distribution of all kinds of products, for the defense of factories and neighborhoods, and so on. It was a sign of the great energy and fighting spirit of the working class and the masses. At the forefront of this process were the cordones industriales (literally “industrial belts”), the coordinating committees of worker-occupied factories. These emerged as seeds of dual power and bodies of workers' self-organization. They were the vanguard of the resistance to the reactionary offensive.

Cordones Industriales: Spontaneity or Conscious Planning?

At their peak, the cordones industriales brought together about one hundred thousand workers throughout Chile, organized in sixty to one hundred cordones from Arica in the north to Punta Arenas in the south. They began to emerge as seeds of workers' power, with the potential to become organs of mass self-organization.

There was both spontaneity and conscious planning in this dynamic. The cordones did not emerge out of a specific plan developed by a political organization; rather, they were a response by sectors of the working class to the bosses' offensive. But it is undeniable that thousands of organized workers spearheaded this process. Many were members of the PS and leaders of the party's National Trade Union Department (DENAS).

The PS thus played a key role. Carlos Altamirano was the main leader of DENAS.[2]_ From the position of “the left of the UP,” using slogans like “advance without compromise,” he arbitrated between the cordones and the government. After October 1972, the government not only tried to hold back the masses' revolutionary aspirations, but also increasingly expressed support for the military as one of the pillars of its power.

But beyond incendiary rhetoric, no sector of the PS developed a consistent strategy. Such a strategy would have required seeing the cordones industriales as the potential foundation of a workers' government.

The PC and the leadership of the PS, along with Allende, constantly sought to limit the cordones' development. They denounced them for dividing the official unions, and sought to keep them within certain limits. Allende advocated an “institutionalized people's power” that would be subordinated to the central government.

The MIR, outside of the government coalition, disregarded the cordones at first, then partially adopted the PC's policy, calling them “divisive.” Finally, the MIR worked within the cordones to place them under the control of its own “communal commands,” which did not, and could not, take on a strategic role. As Franck Gaudichaud put it, “The MIR's position seems to be that of an organization which, due to its weak structures in the workers' movement, seems to have decided that the revolution would come from elsewhere.”[3] The MIR had no policy for uniting revolutionaries and the workers' vanguard to form a true revolutionary party.

Workers' Vanguard and Pre-Bonapartism

The cordones industriales emerged as a response to the counterrevolution, ensuring the production and distribution of goods in a context of high unemployment. They coordinated their work with the Committees of Supply and Prices (JAP), which also grew massively after October. The strength of these bodies slowed the bourgeoisie's plans for a coup, but in no way defeated them. Neither the cordones nor the JAPs had a strategy to build a workers' government, so the power they gained in October was handed over to the existing government, in accordance with the policy adopted by the parties of the UP.

It was in this context that Allende's government began to take on a pre-Bonapartist character, acting as an “arbiter” in response to the growing confrontation between the revolution and the counterrevolution. The Civil-Military Cabinet reflected the government's weakness in its attempt to hold back this process, over which it was quickly losing control.

The Civil-Military Cabinet had two central policies: the Prats-Millas Plan for the return of occupied companies to their previous owners (more than five hundred of them) and the Arms Control Law, which gave the army “extraordinary” powers. The government and the military could maintain this “truce” because it was based on the repression of the workers' vanguard and on a Bonapartist strengthening of the state in order to control the situation with an increasingly powerful army.

The bourgeoisie, lacking the strength to impose its will on all of society, took to the streets. The proletariat, for its part, established new bodies of struggle and self-organization, won over other parts of the population, and sought ways to control production and distribution. But the working class failed to go on the offensive to disarm the bourgeoisie and defeat it in the streets. The workers did not centralize their forces in the cordones to take steps toward establishing their own government.

In December 1972, the Civil-Military Cabinet attempted its first offensive against the workers' vanguard in the cordones, which was resisting the Prats-Millas Plan. Several cordones managed to maintain their occupations, even though a number of companies were returned to their former owners. While the government became stronger, the bodies of self-organization began to retreat, although they would reemerge with renewed strength after another coup attempt in mid-1973.

The Coup Was Not a Bolt from the Blue

The Confederation of Democracy, formed by the right-wing parties and the DC, planned to win two-thirds of the seats in parliament in the elections of March 1973, which would have allowed them to overthrow Allende constitutionally. They failed, however, and then adopted a new strategy of extra-parliamentary struggles and an “institutional blockade,” accompanied by an escalation of attacks by far right groups.

On June 29, one army unit drove tanks to La Moneda, the government palace. This tanquetazo (tank putsch) was put down by the military high command. It was more of a sign of premature despair on the part of a few reactionary officers than a definitive step toward a strategic offensive by the ruling class. But it served to “measure forces.”

After the tanquetazo, hundreds of companies were occupied by their workers, who began to discuss how to confront the danger of a coup, preparing self-defense and distributing weapons. Almost a million people in Santiago (which had just over three million inhabitants) poured into the streets. But in this context, the military gained strength. Allende praised the military leadership as the main force responsible for beating the coup.

The power of the workers and the masses who had risen up again to confront the reaction was held back by Allende and the UP. They called on the people to wait and place their trust in the military and in a “political solution” (i.e. further maneuvers). In failing to launch a strategic offensive, disarm the pro-coup forces, arm the workers, and demand that the government dissolve the Civil-Military Cabinet, the working class and the cordones industriales were unable to use this new favorable situation. After this brief revolutionary resurgence, the strength of the workers and the masses began to disintegrate under the influence of the UP.

From mid-July onwards, the military, which was already the decisive force in the government, began to enforce the Arms Control Law more actively. Occupied companies were raided daily, and troops were sent to repress workers, poor masses, and peasants. In July and August, the military sought to take over, using the UP as a cover. Hundreds of low-ranking naval officers who were planning a defense against a coup were arrested and tortured. Finally, on September 11, 1973, troops led by Augusto Pinochet took over government buildings. Allende escaped to La Moneda, where he committed suicide.

The new coup offensive was launched after the defeat of the workers' vanguard. It began in late July with the last major lockout, carried out by merchants, truckers, professional associations, right-wing parties, and the DC, which called for the intervention of the military against what it deemed an “unconstitutional” government.

The cordones, a “semi-power” (neither centralized nor armed), did not become the “soviets” of the Chilean revolution. But they could have grown if they had had a strategy aimed at establishing a workers' government based on bodies of self-organization. All the power they gained in October 1972 and June 1973 began to disintegrate when they handed it over to a government that had been critically weakened by the reactionary offensives and relied increasingly on the military apparatus, the historical protagonist of the counterrevolution.

There was no such strategy among the left-wing parties. The PC and the PS had a policy of collaboration with the parties of the bourgeoisie in the name of a “democratic” (i.e., electoral) road to socialism. Allende's “democratic revolution” showed that the resistance of the counterrevolutionary forces cannot be defeated via liberal democratic institutions.

Nonetheless, Allende's strategy is still a reference point for the vast majority of the Left today. In the United States, Allende serves as an example of “how to wield the power of the democratic capitalist state that we now could enter, via [Bernie] Sanders.”[4] In his view, “perhaps the most important lesson” of the Chilean example is that “like in Chile, Sanders's ultimate success or failure in the face of these challenges will depend on the extent to which the working class mobilizes to support his positions.”

Chile, however, had more than enough working-class mobilizations. When they saw that “their” government (as they viewed it) was falling apart under the blows of reactionary forces, they established their own organizations to coordinate production, transportation, and distribution. They were repressed by this same government, which was attempting to return companies to their previous owners and then confiscate workers' weapons in hundreds of raids.

It is not by chance that the various articles published in Jacobin about Allende and the UP barely mention the cordones industriales. The strategy of the “democratic road” shifts the center of gravity toward “finding a way to maneuver in the institutional playing field while maintaining a strong connection with social movements.”[5] From this, he draws the conclusion that in contemporary Chile, a strategy of “democratic revolution” “may be much more similar to that of the Popular Front than that of Popular Unity,” that is to say, a strategy in which the Left joins the center under the latter's leadership to achieve “democratization” within the institutions of capitalism. It is no coincidence that Titelman's party, Democratic Revolution, promotes alliances with “progressive” neoliberal parties and the center of the old regime inherited from Pinochet's dictatorship.

The 1973 coup resulted in the death, incarceration, or exile of 30,000 leftists. Pinochet ruled Chile for seventeen years with an iron fist, crushing the Left and spearheading neoliberal policies worldwide. It took an entire generation for the Left to partially recover. The defeat in 1973 had devastating consequences. The lessons are clear, for those who are prepared to listen.

[1]

At that time in Chile, if no candidate won an absolute majority in the presidential election, the congress had to choose between the two candidates who garnered the most votes. On October 24, 1970, the congress proclaimed Allende's victory by 135 votes against the 35 of Alessandri's right-wing force, with the Christian Democratic Party (DC), acting as the first “arbiter” of the election.

[2]

He and Miguel Enríquez (Secretary General of the MIR) would be at the top of the dictatorship's “most wanted” list and blamed for the “coup” because of his last political speeches.

[3]

Franck Gaudichaud, Chile 1970–1973: Mil días que estremecieron al mundo (Santiago de Chile: LOM ediciones, 2016) p. 256.

[4]

Ben Beckett, Jacobin, April 2019.

[5]

Noam Titelman, Jacobin, September 2019.

Palestinian Liberation by Any Means Necessary

By Firebrand

Stop the genocide

Israel's settler-colonial project has again shown its true nature. In retaliation for the new military phase of the Palestinian liberation movement that started on October 7th, the Zionist entity is committing open genocide against Gaza.

Israeli prime minister Netanyahu absurdly and cynically tells the residents of Gaza to leave or face death. The whole world knows the residents of Gaza are in the largest open-air prison in the world. They cannot leave.

Smash apartheid

Apartheid, ethnic cleansing, and bombing civilians are all fundamental to the Zionist project. There can be no Israel without them. Talk of a two-state solution only provides cover for the continued oppression and dispossession of Palestinians.

Even Palestinians within the pre-1967 borders are citizens in name only. We support the long-standing Palestinian demand for a single democratic, secular Palestine open to all.

Watchdog state for the US

The Zionist entity serves US imperialism as a military outpost, economic partner, and police agent in the region. US imperialism is a bipartisan project.

Since the formation of Israel through the 1948 Nakba, both Democrats and Republicans have backed the Zionist expulsion, dispossession, and oppression of the Palestinian people. The US often pretends to be a mediator between Israel and Palestine. It never is. It always backs Israel.

Zionist socialists?!

US government officials who claim to be socialists, including Bernie Sanders and DSA members, Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and Jamaal Bowman, have disgustingly climbed on the Zionist bandwagon and denounced Hamas's “terrorism.”

Biden has gone so far as to call the Palestinian offensive antisemitic, when it is really anti-colonial. The target is not a religion, but a state based on stealing Palestinian land. This is not an ancient conflict, but a modern one created by imperialism and the settler-colonial project.

A united ruling class

The hypocrites that have rushed to denounce Hamas for taking “civilian” (settler) lives have had little to say about the many thousands of Palestinians slaughtered by the Zionist entity over the last 75 years. The same is true of liberal media outlets like MSNBC.

Supporters of Palestine do so in opposition to a united ruling class. This creates the potential for more radicalization than exists around other issues, where the Democrats have fraudulently positioned themselves as allies.

Zionism or peace, not both

Virtually the entire Israeli population is part of the Zionist military machine that has kicked out Palestinians and won't let them return. Israeli settlers who have been killed in the conflict are also victims of Zionist aggression.

Apartheid, ethnic cleansing, and bombing civilians are all fundamental to the Zionist project. There can be no Israel without them. Talk of a two-state solution only provides cover for the continued oppression and dispossession of Palestinians. We support the long-standing Palestinian demand for a single democratic, secular Palestine open to all.

If Zionism did not expel and oppress Palestine, Palestinians would not need to engage in military attacks on Israel. Those outraged by violence on either side should put the blame where it lies—on Zionism and its US backers!

Inspired by intifada

On Oct 7, Palestinian resistance groups launched an unprecedented military incursion into Israel. This was the first major military campaign originating within Palestine. It shattered the myth of Israel as an invincible military and intelligence state.

Palestinians' heroic breakout of Gaza and their military attacks against their occupiers have inspired an outpouring of support around the world. Massive demonstrations of solidarity have grown on every continent.

Our responsibility in the US

People in the US have a special responsibility to fight for Palestinian liberation. If not for US financial, military, and political support, the apartheid state would collapse.

We need to demand an end to US aid to the Zionist entity. We need to support the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement (BDS). We need to oppose all the politicians who give aid and political cover to Zionism. The Democrats are no more a solution than the Republicans.

Resistance is justified

We need to put all our demands on Israel and the US, not on Palestinians. We should reject calls for a general cease-fire which would pressure the Palestinians to pull back from their liberation struggle.

Unlike the fake liberal allies who only support Palestinians as docile and defenseless victims, we pledge unconditional support for Palestinian resistance.

When people are occupied, resistance is justified! There is only one solution! Intifada, revolution!

What will it take to liberate palestine?

By Steve Leigh

A free Palestine from the river to the sea is the demand that has been taken up by the unprecedented global protest movement in the wake of Israel's brutal war and genocide in Gaza. Most sincere supporters of the Palestinian cause can understand why the dismantling of the oppressive Zionist apartheid state and the creation of a free, democratic, and secular Palestine are the only objectives worth fighting for. Anything less—such as a “two-state solution”—should be rejected.

But what will it actually take to achieve a free Palestine?

Let's start by stating something obvious: the first step towards the liberation of Palestine is the resistance that's taking place in Palestine itself. Palestinians have always fought back against Zionism, even before the creation of the Zionist state; and they've fought back in many ways, from strikes to mass protests to armed struggle. If they hadn't, then the issue would never have been raised around the world. Resistance is justified, it is necessary, and it should be supported internationally on that basis alone.[1]_

Once we've established that, let's take a deeper look at what Palestinian liberation means. A free Palestine is one that upholds civic, political, and democratic rights for everyone, in contrast to a state where only people of a given religion have full rights. It also means the right of return of all Palestinians and all their descendants to the land that they were expelled from, and the return of the land itself to the Palestinians—from the river to the sea, it bears repeating.

And finally, it means ending the Zionist entity: that is, a full replacement of the current Zionist state with a free Palestine, not a two-state solution. The two-state solution is a proposal that is both undesirable and unrealistic. A look at the history of the Zionist colonial project over the past 76 years shows that it would never be willingly granted by the Zionists and their imperialist partners in the West.

But even if it were possible, it would simply mean a smaller Zionist state. Such a state would still be based on dispossession and oppression of the Palestinians—the rightful owners of the land.

This is why we adamantly reject a two-state solution. We're for one liberated state: a fully democratic, non-sectarian Palestine with equal rights for all.

A free Palestine under capitalism?

Now the question comes up: is any of this possible under capitalism? As things stand now, with capitalism in crisis amid the current landscape of multipolar imperialism, it is very unlikely. Israel is all-important for Western imperialist interests in the Middle East region. This is why Western leaders have defended Israel so staunchly even as a horrifying genocide unfolds for the world to see.

But let's consider what it would be like if the overthrow of Zionism were possible under capitalism. The best we can hope for is a situation like the one in South Africa after the downfall of apartheid in 1994. There, formal apartheid was ended because of the heroic and persistent mass struggle of the people over decades. The post-apartheid government instituted one person, one vote; equality under the law for all; and many other reforms.

Even if it were possible to end Zionism before we overthrow capitalism, we must admit that a free Palestine under capitalism would face problems similar to post-apartheid South Africa. The biggest share of the wealth would still be among the Zionists, and Palestinians would largely still be poor and oppressed (though perhaps a few more Palestinians would join the capitalist class).

But what have the material results been under South African capitalism? As undeniably necessary as the reforms were, we can't deny that a form of economic apartheid still exists in South Africa. There is mass poverty among the Black population, and concentration of wealth primarily among the ruling class—many of them hailing, unsurprisingly, from the white minority who were the oppressors under apartheid. So the social and political revolution against South African apartheid was incomplete to say the least.

In fact a socialist society is the only way to have full equality. Only economic equality can insure lasting political and civic equality.

No revolutionary hope in the Israeli working class

But who can bring about socialism in Palestine? When it comes to assessing the possibility of social transformation in a given capitalist state, Marxists usually look to the working class. This is the class that is exploited by capitalists, and the class that produces the wealth of the nation. Therefore it has an interest in overthrowing capitalism, as well as the potential economic power to do so.

The case of Israel is a special exception to this rule. Marxists do not look to the Israeli Jewish working class as a force that can transform and overthrow Zionism.[2]_

There are a number of material reasons for this. Israeli Jewish workers took direct part in the ethnic cleansing and settlement of Palestine (and still do to this day). Financially speaking, compared to other workers around the world, they greatly benefit from the Zionist government's settler project—from high rates of social welfare to grants of stolen land. Most Israeli Jewish workers have served in the IOF and have been intimately involved in oppressing Palestinians. They are furthermore deeply invested in the permanent wartime economy and culture that has prevailed since the 1967 war.

Finally, there is a vast social gulf separating Israeli Jewish workers and Palestinians due to the apartheid system. Most Jewish workers have little contact with Palestinians, even fellow Palestinian workers, preventing the kind of solidarity that develops between racial groups in the working classes of other countries.

The massive imperialist subsidies from the US and other Western nations ensure that these economic and social arrangements will continue.

The bottom line is that the continuance of the Zionist state is very much in the material interests of the Jewish working class, and Palestinian liberation is against their interests. Thus, racism against Palestinians is deeply entrenched by the social structure of the state.

Israeli Jews will never embrace Palestinian liberation or turn against the Zionist government and their own interests in large enough numbers to make a social revolution within the 1967 borders. This has been objectively demonstrated over and over by all who have studied and observed the Israeli working class.

One illustration of how all this shapes social attitudes in Israel are the polls showing that upwards of 90% of the Jewish population supports the genocide in Gaza.[3]_

We don't argue that Israeli Jewish workers are intrinsically bad or hateful people. Of course there are a few heroic individuals of conscience, including draft resisters and leftists who protest the war and the apartheid system. These individuals show that humanity can prevail even in the most racist environments.

But we must analyze the Israeli working class as a whole. As a class, their racism and toxic attitudes stem from the structure of the Israeli state and its settler-colonial nature, and this is very unlikely to change in the current conditions.

The vicious cycle of Zionism and imperialism

Because Israel is a settler-colonial state, it is naturally hostile to the people of the region, both Palestinians and the neighboring Arab-majority countries. The 76 years since the founding of the Zionist state have been characterized by continual genocidal violence against the Palestinians and militarism and aggression in the region. This hostility means that Zionism has always required imperialist support in order to prop it up. First the British, then the French, then the Soviet Union, and now the US have all taken their turns as the imperialist backers of the Zionist project.

The US benefits from this arrangement, first of all because it needs a stable ally in the region. Israel's settler-colonialist project makes it an ideal candidate for such a partnership with US imperialism. Settler-colonialism is naturally compatible with imperialism.

An illustration of this compatibility is that Israel is useful to the US even outside the Middle East. The US has benefitted from Israel's support of apartheid South Africa, and its interventions in Central America. More recently the IOF has established relationships with many police forces in the US, providing training and spy technology.

Thus a vicious cycle is created: imperialist support for Israel is based on its settler-colonial nature, and its settler-colonial nature requires imperialist support.

The US has never wavered in its support for Israel—this has always been a bipartisan policy. Both the Republicans and the Democrats have been consistently and staunchly Zionist. For example, all of the Democratic members of Congress who are now calling for a ceasefire still support the state of Israel on principle. They may issue statements about excessive bloodshed, but they continue to back Zionism, the cause of that bloodshed.

In 1986, then-Senator Joe Biden infamously said, “I think it's about time that we stop apologizing for our support for Israel. There's no apology to be made—none. It's the best three-billion-dollar investment we make. Were it not for Israel, the United States of America would have to invent an Israel to protect her interests in the region.”[4]

It is extremely unlikely that this longstanding, unshakeable support for Israel on the part of the entire US ruling class would ever change in a meaningful way.

As Israeli anti-Zionists and socialists Jabra Nicola and Moshe Machover wrote in 1969:[5]

The Palestinian people are waging a battle where they confront Zionism, which is supported by imperialism; from the rear they are menaced by the Arab regimes and Arab reaction, which are also supported by imperialism. As long as imperialism has a real stake in the Middle East, it is unlikely to withdraw its support for Zionism, its natural ally, and to permit its overthrow. It will defend it to the last drop of Arab oil.

Supporters of Palestinian liberation cannot depend on the US giving up on its Zionist ally. It is more realistic to imagine the downfall of US imperialism.

The overthrow of Zionism must be part of a regional and international revolution. Only such a revolution can be strong enough to challenge the state of Israel and its imperialist backers. Only such a revolution can alter the material and social relations of the Israeli state, and therefore win some of the Israeli working class over to support for Palestinian liberation.

This is why our strategy for anti-Zionism must be anti-imperialist. Only when US imperialism is overthrown or so weakened that it cannot aid the Israeli state will Zionism end.

The role of the regional Arab working classes

At the same time, imperialist interest and domination in the region cannot be shattered without overthrowing those junior partners of imperialist exploitation that constitute the ruling classes in the Arab world. As things stand now, under the sway of US imperialism, most Arab states support Israel. Their historic anti-Zionist rhetoric may continue, but their pro-Israeli actions speak louder—especially with the normalization process and treaties such the Abraham Accords.

As Sumaya Awad and brian bean argued in Palestine: A Socialist Introduction, the entrenchment of neoliberalism “drew various Arab states together with Israel into a single economic zone under the domination of US economic power. This has created an environment materially connecting the Arab countries of the region with Israel, thus investing the interests of national capitalists with that of settler-colonial Israel.”

However, though the ruling classes of the Arab states support Israel, the Arab masses do not. The Arab working classes and peasantry have shown over and over again that they oppose the state of Israel.

Furthermore, the Arab working classes are the ones with the economic clout to really challenge the Israeli state, because they have the potential to overthrow the Arab states that are the lynchpin of imperialist control of the region. The Arab Spring of 2011 dramatically showed that potential. So did the uprisings in the broader region in 2019. These rebellions had a strong internationalist tendency: many of the protesters made it clear that they looked past their own borders for the source of their problems. They were opposed to neoliberalism, and to Zionism as well.

The overthrow of Zionism must be part of a regional and international revolution. Only such a revolution can be strong enough to challenge the state of Israel and its imperialist backers. Only such a revolution can alter the material and social relations of the Israeli state, and therefore win some of the Israeli working class over to support for Palestinian liberation. As the old slogan goes, “the road to Jerusalem begins in Cairo, Damascus, and Amman.”

Intifada until victory

So what does all of this mean for supporters of Palestine in the US? First of all we need to support Palestinian resistance by any means necessary, with no moralistic qualms. This is the most basic and urgent way to show our solidarity.

We need to organize workers here in the US to use their economic power against Zionism and against US imperialism. We need to support the boycott, divest, and sanctions movement (BDS). We need to fight for the right to protest—opposing the repression of student organizations and other activist groups, and opposing the laws that are being put forward against BDS.

We need to reject the Zionist, imperialist Democratic Party, and reject all organizations on the left that legitimize it, including the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA).[6]_ There is increasing disillusionment with the Democrats among the young, the oppressed, and supporters of Palestine. We need to speak to that disillusionment and organize among those demographics.

We need to challenge all aspects of US imperialism, not just on Palestine. The weaker US imperialism is, the less it can aid Israel. And this means opposing US interventions in other conflicts, such as the Ukraine war.

We need to understand that imperialism is not just a policy, it is instead integral to capitalism. The economic competition which is the foundation of capitalism yields military competition. To end imperialism and war, we need to end the system that causes it. To overthrow imperialism, we must end capitalism.

As Awad and bean put it, “we need a rupture that pushes beyond the conception of a capitalist state, a revolutionary struggle not only within occupied Palestine, but also in the streets of the Arab capitals across the region, and among workers in the imperialist countries... Just as we cannot conceive of Zionism and the occupation in isolation, we cannot conceive of Palestine as a purely national question.”

To quote one of the most inspiring and relevant slogans of the current movement, we need to globalize the intifada.

As revolutionary socialists, we need to support every struggle against exploitation and oppression. We see every struggle as connected. Every struggle contributes to the weakening and finally, hopefully, the overthrow of capitalism.

However it happens, Palestinian liberation is going to be a very hard struggle. For us in the US, a central part of our role in that struggle is developing a revolutionary party that can organize the fight against capitalism.

[1]

See “Why We Support Palestinian Armed Resistance,” Firebrand, January 2024.

[2]

See “Arabs, Jews and Socialism,” Workers Liberty, 2019.

[3]

Reuters, December 2023.

[4]

Senator Joe Biden, 1986.

[5]

Jabra Nicola and Moshe Machover, “Arabs, Jews and Socialism,” 1969.

[6]

See “The French Turn: the DSA and Revolutionary Regroupment,” Firebrand, January 2024.

The Path to Socialism Requires Border Abolition

By Héctor Rivera

Although the Biden administration has attempted to differentiate its immigration policies from those of Donald Trump, the end result has been the same: deportations, abuse and negligence of children jailed in detention centers and refugees turned away at the border. What's more, Biden's refusal to allow in the refugees at the border has contributed to horrific human rights abuses. As Reuters reported, nearly 3,300 migrants stranded in Mexico have been kidnapped, raped, trafficked or assaulted since Joe Biden took office on January 20.[1]_

These conditions are the result of the continuation of most of Trump's immigration policy under Biden, especially the infamous Title 42, a public health measure weaponized by white-supremacist Stephen Miller at the beginning of the pandemic.[2]_ Title 42 has allowed the United States to use the pandemic to justify the categorical rejection of asylum claims. On Friday, June 25, Biden's Homeland Security Secretary Alejandro Mayorkas announced that Title 42 would remain in place as long as needed, and that the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) would make the final decision. “It's a public health decision... based on the well-being of the American public.” However, according to the New York Times, the CDC “has directed questions about the policy to the White House.” In other words, the continuation of the policy is a political calculation that Biden is making to position his administration as “tough” on migration.

In fact, the enactment of Title 42 violates international law and since the beginning, it has been used to attack refugees seeking asylum.[3]_ According to a report from the Associated Press published in October 2020, Vice President Mike Pence and Stephen Miller pressured Dr. Robert Redfield, CDC director, to use his emergency powers to institute the law despite opposition from the agency's scientists, who said that there was no evidence the action would slow the coronavirus.

Title 42 has turned away refugee families, which led the rise in unaccompanied minors reaching the border earlier this year. In the end, this is family separation by other means. For all their supposed differences, the Republicans and the Democrats are ruling class parties committed to enforcement-only immigration policies that safeguard the interests of US imperialism. Indeed, Kamala Harris' “Do not come” statement is the Democrat's equivalent of Donald Trump's “Send them back!”.

When we argue for a world without borders, we don't do so just for humanitarian reasons, but because we understand that immigrants' rights are workers' rights and because immigrant struggles are class struggle.

Socialists must oppose any immigration policies that do not call for the abolition of border regimes and the fascist institutions that enforce them. When we argue for a world without borders, we don't do so just for humanitarian reasons, but because we understand that immigrants' rights are workers' rights and because immigrant struggles are class struggle.

US border and immigration policy: the result of Indigenous genocide and slavery

A cursory overview of US immigration policies and border regimes reveals a violent history of dispossession and exclusion that accompanied the process of imperial-state formation to guarantee the rights of a capitalist, white-supremacist, settler colonial state.

Today's citizenship laws can be traced to the explicitly racist Naturalization Act of 1790, which conferred citizenship to “any alien, being a free white person.”[4] In addition, the criminalization of migration and limits to free movement, have been structured by the slave trade, and the policing and regulation of slaves through vagrancy laws and the Fugitive Slave Act of 1850.

From the outset, Frederick Douglass and other abolitionists opposed western expansion because annexation of the West strengthened the Southern plantation economy—a conclusion also reached by Karl Marx.[5]_ After the American invasion of Mexico, the southern border was enforced by the army and Texas Rangers that carried out land grabs against Mexican and Tejanx inhabitants of the new territories. Furthermore, patrolling across the southern border continued to enforce the Fugitive Slave Act, while the United States led campaigns of Indigenous extermination in the Southwest.

Since its inception, US immigration policy has been weaponized against Indigenous political and social formations. For example, the Indian Removal Act of 1830 forcibly removed southern Native Americans from their ancestral homelands to Oklahoma in order make way for white settlers in what became known as the Trail of Tears. In addition, through the Dawes Act of 1887, Indigenous people could become US citizens only if they agreed to relocation on reservations and the confiscation and partitioning of tribal lands.[6]_ After annexation, the capitalist state became the main enforcer of these boundaries and laws through paramilitary formations like the Texas Rangers that led a campaign of genocide against the Comanche and Apache nations to clear the frontier for more white settlers.

Towards the end of the 19th Century, white supremacist federal immigration laws merged race-based exclusion with criminalization of sex work and drug prohibition through the Page Act and the Chinese Exclusion Act. These laws were implemented by immigration agents by the turn of the century, and were later enforced by the newly created US Border Patrol in 1924, which recruited its first generation of agents from the ranks of the Texas Rangers, and Klansmen, laying the ground for the culture of racism and violence still prevalent in immigration enforcement agencies.[7]_

Throughout the twentieth century, immigration laws were selectively enforced to attack oppressed populations in periods like the Great Depression, when 1.8 million people of Mexican descent, many of them American born, were rounded up in violent, terrorizing raids and deported to open jobs for white workers. Anti-Asian racism also drove immigration legislation like the Immigration Act of 1917, which created the “Asiatic Barred Zone,” the Immigration Act of 1924 that limited Japanese immigration and other policies which eventually culminated in the internment of Japanese and Japanese-American citizens in concentration camps.

US immigration policy has historically included “guestworker programs” like the Bracero Program, that brought manual laborers from Mexico to work on US farms during World War II. Nevertheless, these programs are a form of indentured servitude and they have been used to break strikes by unionized farm workers. Today's guest worker programs are no different, they are used to undermine unionization and if foreign workers demand higher wages, they are easily replaced or lose their ability to renew their visa since they are at the mercy of their employer.

Much like the Bracero Program, Biden's immigration proposal, the “US Citizenship Act of 2021,” is a form of indentured servitude and according to Justin Akers Chacón, it “has a labor requirement that guarantees that capitalists can have direct access to three to eight years of cheap labor per person, in which wages and working conditions can be suppressed under conditions of noncitizenship.”[8]

Current plans to expand guestworker programs under the Biden Administration reveal an increased dependence on imported labor in sectors like agriculture and high-tech, where US capital is able to externalize social reproduction costs to the home country, while at the same time importing this labor at a lower cost. Furthermore, as Justin Akers Chacón has argued, regimes of migrant labor repression and control work in conjunction with the process of displacement resulting from imperialist “free trade agreements” with Mexico, Central America and the Caribbean. His research shows that these pacts have become an important source of wealth accumulation for US corporations that allows capital to concurrently exploit labor within and across borders.

To win socialism, we must abolish ICE and destroy the border

Given their bloody history and the nature of US borders as controls of land, labor and capital flows, they must be abolished to guarantee the free movement and protection of people, species and resources. Furthermore, the border and its accompanying legal-political superstructure must be abolished for the preservation and reclamation of indigenous lands and to establish the basis for genuine proletarian internationalism that puts life and humanity above the interests of US imperialism.

The function of immigration-enforcement agencies, including the direct and indirect killing of migrants at the border and other forms of violence associated with apprehension, detention and abuse, are a continuation of historic Anglo-settler violence that only serves to control labor and validate xenophobic nationalism.

The new socialist movement must be categorically opposed to the immigration policies of Republicans and Democrats, as the border enforcement regime is not about “security” or “protecting US jobs” but rather serves as an essential method of imperialist state formation and the organization of people into social hierarchies. Border enforcement is labor repression, which through the aegis of access to state-determined citizenship, establishes patchworks of labor segregation based on racial and national exclusions. Furthermore, the violence of enforcement determines who gets to work without fear of arrest and deportation and who gets terrorized by la migra. Indeed, the function of immigration-enforcement agencies, including the direct and indirect killing of migrants at the border and other forms of violence associated with apprehension, detention and abuse, are a continuation of historic Anglo-settler violence that only serves to control labor and validate xenophobic nationalism. As Harsha Walia argues,

Exclusionary projections of who belongs and who has the right to life upholds ruling-class and right-wing nationalism, thus breaking internationalist solidarity and entrenching global apartheid. A political and economic system that treats land as a commodity, Indigenous people as overburden, race as a principle of social organization, women's caretaking as worthless, workers as exploitable, climate refugees as expendable, and the entire planet as a sacrifice zone must be dismantled.[9]_

The resolute abolition of borders and ICE is an integral part of the struggle for socialism in the United States. Socialists must reject narrow bread and butter populism propagated by Bernie Sanders, caucuses like Bread & Roses in the Democratic Socialists of America, and any others claiming the socialist mantle that do not commit to border abolition—as the repression of migrant labor is central to the functioning of racial capitalism. The struggle for a world without borders is not abstract, it is a reality we must organize towards in the here and now. As Mariame Kaba teaches us, “There will be no magical day of liberation that we do not make.” Like prison abolitionists, we can organize a real movement to abolish the present state of things as we fight against Title 42, for reparations to those nations wracked by US imperialism, and against borders.

Héctor A. Rivera (He/Him) is a queer, Mexican-American, communist educator based in Los Ángeles, Califaztlán. He is a member of the Democratic Socialists of America and the Tempest Collective. He writes about geography, history and politics in the US and Latin America.

[1]

Reuters, June 2021.

[2]

See NBC News on Stephen Miller's white nationalist views.

[3]

See CMSNY.org.

[4]

Harsha Walia, Border and Rule. Global Migration, Capitalism, and the Rise of Racist Nationalism. Haymarket Books, 2020, p. 33.

[5]

Paul Ortiz, An African American and Latinx History of the United States. Beacon Press, 2018, p. 47.

[6]

Walia, Border and Rule, p. 33.

[7]

Walia, Border and Rule, p. 70.

[8]

Justin Akers Chacón, “Biden's Immigration Proposal: A Path to Nowhere,” Puntorojo, March 2021.

[9]

Walia, Border and Rule, p. 84.

Lenin, Bukharin, and Imperialism

By John Riddell

It is almost one hundred years since the publication of V. I. Lenin's Imperialism: The Highest Stage of Capitalism and Nikolai Bukharin's Imperialism and World Economy,2 written in the midst of the carnage of World War I. Imperialism was written in the first half of 1916 and published in mid-1917; Imperialism and World Economy was not published until several months later, but it was substantially written in 1915 and very likely influenced Lenin's own thinking, since he read the book in manuscript and wrote an introduction for it in December 1915 supporting its main analysis. Both books, and especially Lenin's, have had a major influence on the revolutionary left. A century after their first appearance, it is worth evaluating their legacy.

Both Lenin and Bukharin were leading figures in the militant Bolshevik wing of the Russian Social Democratic Labor Party. The Bolsheviks were one of a very small number of socialist groups in Europe to denounce the war as an imperialist conflict and to refuse to support their own government. On one side of the war were Britain, France, and Russia, on the other Germany, Austria-Hungary, and the Turkish Ottoman Empire. In the decade leading up to the war, the Second International (an association of the world's leading socialist parties), had passed numerous resolutions pledging to oppose war between the big powers if and when it broke out. But when war was finally declared in August 1914, socialists in the German parliament overwhelmingly voted for war credits, arguing that they had to defend civilization against the despotism of the Russian tsar. French socialists responded by saying they had to defend revolutionary France against Prussian militarism. The British Labour Party supported Britain's entry into the war, and so on down the line. Lenin was so surprised by this betrayal, particularly of the German Social Democratic Party, that he initially refused to believe that it was true. His comrade Gregory Zinoviev recounted his reaction a few years later:

When the war broke out we were living in a god-forsaken little mountain village in Galicia. I remember having had a bet with him. I said "You will see, the German Social Democrats will not dare vote against the war, but will abstain in the vote on the war credits." Comrade Lenin replied: "No, they are not such scoundrels as all that. They will not, of course, fight the war, but they will, to ease their conscience, vote against the credits lest the working class rise up against them." In this case Lenin was wrong, and so was I. Neither of us had taken the full measure of the flunkeyism of the social patriots. The European Social Democrats proved complete bankrupts. They all voted for the war credits. When the first number of the Vörwarts, the organ of the German Social Democrats, arrived with the news that they had voted the war credits, Lenin at first refused to believe. "It cannot be," he said, "it must be a forged number. Those scoundrels, the German bourgeoisie, have specially published such a number of the Vörwarts in order to compel us also to go against the International." Alas, it was not so. It turned out that the social patriots really had voted the war credits. When Lenin saw it, his first word was: "The Second International is dead."3

Both works by Lenin and Bukharin attempted to explain how the war was rooted in profound economic changes, but they were also intervening in the sharp political debate that had torn apart the international socialist movement when the war began. Both of them argued that the war was an imperialist conflict in which all sides were trying to grab more territory and extend their power and influence, or at the very least hang on to territories to which they had no right in the first place. People who called themselves "socialists" but who nevertheless found excuses to support their own governments had betrayed the working class and the socialist movement. Those who privately opposed the war but refused to make their opposition public were just as bad. Lenin himself advocated the sharpest opposition to the war, arguing that socialists should not just refuse to support their own ruling classes, but should openly call for their defeat.

Similarly, Lenin supported the right of oppressed nations to self-determination. National independence could not bring about genuine liberation without the abolition of class divisions and the overthrow of capitalism, but the fight for independence would weaken imperialism, and support for that fight by workers in the oppressing nation would cut against national chauvinism and make possible the emergence of a genuinely internationalist socialist movement.4

Lenin's main goal in Imperialism was to show how the colonial expansion of the major world powers in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries---which led to interimperial rivalry and eventually war---was rooted in profound changes in the nature of capitalism during the same period. That is why he called imperialism at the beginning of the twentieth century a stage of capitalism. Lenin's claim has confused some of his readers, so it is worth pointing out that he was not saying that there was no imperialism before the late nineteenth century. Rather, he was pointing out that the nature of imperialism had changed.

Colonial policy and imperialism existed before the latest stage of capitalism, and even before capitalism. Rome, founded on slavery, pursued a colonial policy and practiced imperialism. But "general" arguments about imperialism, which ignore, or put into the background the fundamental difference of social-economic systems, inevitably degenerate into absolutely empty banalities, or into grandiloquent comparisons like "Greater Rome and Greater Britain." Even the capitalist colonial policy of capitalism in its previous stages is essentially different from the colonial policy of finance capital. (Ch. VI)

Another source of confusion has been the description of imperialism as the "highest stage of capitalism." Countless commentators have attributed to Lenin the idea that early twentieth century capitalism was the final form that capitalism would take, and no further development was possible. But Lenin says no such thing. In fact a more accurate translation of his title is Imperialism: The Latest Stage of Capitalism, and the text itself repeatedly speaks of "the latest stage of capitalism,"5 not its final stage. The title was probably a deliberate echo of an important book by the Austrian Marxist Rudolf Hilferding, Finance Capital, the Latest Phase of Capitalist Development, which was an important influence on Lenin's views.6

What Lenin was attempting to explain was the extremely virulent form of imperialism that began to emerge in the late nineteenth century, resulting in the scramble for Africa from the 1880s, and the increasing tensions between the major powers. In calling it a stage of capitalism, Lenin was saying that the new imperialism could not be satisfactorily explained in ideological or political terms, and that it was fundamentally an economic phenomenon.

According to Lenin, an adequate definition of modern imperialism needs to embrace "five essential features" (Ch. VII):

The concentration of production and capital developed to such a high stage that it created monopolies which play a decisive role in economic life.

The merging of bank capital with industrial capital, and the creation, on the basis of this 'finance capital,' of a 'financial oligarchy.'

The export of capital, which has become extremely important, as distinguished from the export of commodities.

The formation of international capitalist monopolies which share the world among themselves.

The territorial division of the whole world among the greatest capitalist powers is completed.

Lenin's list has to be examined critically because, in retrospect, some of the features he listed are more fundamental than others. For example, the integration of industrial and banking capital was certainly an important aspect of German capitalism in the early twentieth century, but far less developed in countries such as Britain. Nor had all the major capitalist powers become net exporters of capital---more investment was still flowing into the United States and Japan when Lenin was writing, for example, than was going out.7 Nevertheless, Lenin was correct to point out the importance of the banking industry and the financial sector, which has continued to grow in influence over the past century. And he makes clear that the most important feature of imperialism is the first one that he listed. "If it were necessary to give the briefest possible definition of imperialism," he wrote, "we should have to say that imperialism is the monopoly stage of capitalism." So Lenin's underlying argument was that the rivalries and wars between capitalist powers were inherent in one of capitalism's basic features: the tendency, analyzed by Marx, for capital to become more centralized and concentrated---larger and larger units of production controlled, because of mergers and acquisitions, by fewer and fewer capitalists.8 By the end of the nineteenth century this process was already well underway, allowing dominant capitalist firms to acquire monopoly or near monopoly status in particular sectors of their national economies.

Lenin described his pamphlet as a "popular outline," and it is really a sketch rather than a finished theoretical study. Bukharin attempted to explain the underlying dynamic of imperialism more systematically. In Imperialism and World Economy, Bukharin analyzes imperialism as the result of two contradictory tendencies in modern capitalism. The first is the concentration and centralization of capital discussed by Lenin. As this process develops, however, the state comes to play an increasingly active role in managing the economy, and Bukharin argued that there is a tendency for capital and the state to become more and more closely integrated. The end point of this process is for state and capital to merge together and form what he called "state capitalist trusts" (Ch. X).

Second, as the first process unfolds, there is a simultaneous tendency for production, trade, and investment to break out of national boundaries and to become organized on a global scale. As a consequence of this second process, according to Bukharin, there is a tendency for economic competition between capitals to take on the form of geopolitical competition---in other words, for economic competition to be expressed in terms of political and military rivalries between states for territory, influence, and power. This is the basis of modern imperialism.

Bukharin summarizes his view as follows:

There is here a growing discord between the basis of social economy which has become world-wide and the peculiar class structure of society, a structure where the ruling class (the bourgeoisie) itself is split into "national" groups with contradictory economic interests, groups which, being opposed to the world proletariat, are competing among themselves for the division of the surplus value created on a world scale. Production is of a social nature; international division of labor turns the private "national" economies into parts of a gigantic all-embracing labor process, which extends over almost the whole of humanity. Acquisition, however, assumes the character of "national" (state) acquisition where the beneficiaries are huge state companies of the bourgeoisie of finance capital. The development of productive forces moves within the narrow limits of state boundaries while it has already outgrown those limits. Under such conditions there inevitably arises a conflict, which, given the existence of capitalism, is settled through extending the state frontiers in bloody struggles, a settlement which holds the prospect of new and more grandiose conflicts. (Ch. VIII)

Bukharin sometimes described the tendency towards the creation of state-capitalist trusts as more complete than it really was, and he wrongly believed that such trusts would only be affected by outside crises, ignoring the internal contradictions that continued to exist in all capitalist economies. On this score, Bukharin needs to be modified by Lenin, who noted: "The monopoly created in certain branches of industry increases and intensifies the anarchy inherent in capitalist production as a whole." (Ch. I) Later Lenin writes: "At the same time the monopolies, which have grown out of free competition, do not eliminate the latter but exist above it and alongside it, and thereby give rise to a number of very acute antagonisms, frictions and conflicts." (Ch. VII)

There is one other important element in this theory. Capitalism tends to create a single world economy, but development does not take place uniformly either within individual states or in the system as a whole. Instead, it is characterized---in Trotsky's famous phrase---by combined and uneven development. Economic, military, and political power tends to be concentrated in a handful of states, which therefore dominate the rest of the world. But, as Lenin noted, "Finance capital and the trusts do not diminish but increase the differences in the rate of growth of the various parts of the world economy." (Ch. VII) In certain circumstances it is possible for relatively backward states to develop rapidly by importing advanced technologies and to catch up with, or even overtake, their rivals.

This is crucial, because it shows that the division of power between the advanced states and the rest of the world isn't static. Even if stability in international relations were established for a period of time, it would eventually be undermined as the result of economic changes. So, for instance, the attempt at the end of World War I to prevent the outbreak of further wars by creating the League of Nations was a complete failure.

The main target of many of Lenin's and Bukharin's arguments was Karl Kautsky, for many years the leading theoretician of the German SPD. At the start of the war, Kautsky privately advocated abstaining on the war credits vote in the German Reichstag, but refused to publicly criticize the SPD's vote for the war and argued that democratic Germany was fighting a defensive war against autocratic Tsarist Russia. Almost a year into the war, when Germany's expansionist aims became undeniable, Kautsky did finally publicly oppose it, but he maintained that the war was not rooted in capitalism and that from the point of view of the capitalist system, war had become irrational precisely because the world economy was becoming integrated on an international level. As a consequence, Kautsky argued, "the result of the World War between the great imperialist powers may be a federation of the strongest, who renounce their arms race."9 Kautsky called this anticipated phase of capitalist development "ultra-imperialism," and he saw the formation of the League of Nations at the end of the war as part of the shift to ultra-imperialism and a more peaceful world order.

But of course the League of Nations---which Lenin described as "an alliance of robbers, each trying to snatch something from the others"10---was never able to paper over the sharp differences between the major imperialist powers, and within a generation the world was engulfed in an even more barbaric war. Kautsky's vision of a relatively peaceful capitalism was revealed as an illusion. By contrast, Lenin and Bukharin's theory seems to do a remarkably good job of explaining the development of capitalism in the first half of the twentieth century, and why the major capitalist powers plunged the globe into two catastrophic and barbaric world wars.

Imperialism since Lenin and Bukharin

But does Lenin and Bukharin's approach help us to understand the modern world? After World War II, the structure of global politics changed dramatically. Before the war, the world was economically and politically multipolar. After the war it remained economically multipolar but became politically bipolar, with the formation of two rival global military alliances, one dominated by the United States, the other by the Soviet Union. While nominally socialist, the USSR was by this time ruled by a bureaucratic elite that exploited the majority of the population in order to compete with the West for power and influence. The stage was set for the Cold War. At the end of World War II, the Soviet Union took over most of Eastern Europe (initially with the agreement of their wartime Western allies) and installed regimes modeled on its own, with one-party states that controlled in each case most of the economy. While state and capital never fully merged in most of the capitalist world, they did so in the Soviet bloc for several decades.11

It would be hard to deny that this was a period of intense interimperialist rivalry. Wars continued on the periphery resulting in millions of deaths, and the two superpowers engaged in a massive arms race, but there was no war between the USA and the USSR, although they came extremely close at the time of the Cuban missile crisis in 1962 and on several other occasions.12 But with the Eastern European revolutions of 1989 and the subsequent disintegration of the Soviet Union itself, the structure of the global system changed again.

The end of the Cold War took place at the same time as the decisive US victory in the 1991 Gulf War against Iraq, and was supposed to usher in a "new world order" of international stability, in which military conflict would decline, and we would all receive the benefits of a massive "peace dividend." But despite a mood of triumphalism among US imperial strategists and propagandists in the early 1990s, the peace dividend never materialized because the US ruling class found itself almost immediately faced with new challenges.

For the United States, one positive consequence of the Cold War was that it gave Washington political dominance over the major capitalist countries in Europe and Asia, since they depended on the US military for their security. With the fall of the Soviet Union, Western Europe's military dependency on the US decreased at the same time as its economic and political integration accelerated. US planners viewed this as a potential medium-term threat to continued American global dominance. In the mid-1990s, some European countries began floating the idea of a European Defense Force that could act independently of the US-dominated North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), which had been formed to oppose the USSR and now seemed to have little reason for its existence. US policy makers were also concerned about the possibility of a German-Russian strategic alliance, as well as the emergence of China as a major economic and military power that might begin to replace the US as the dominant power in Asia.

The Clinton administration responded to these challenges both economically and militarily. It pushed through policies of economic globalization designed to bind the other major powers into relations of dependency on the US in the World Trade Organization. Simultaneously it followed a policy of strengthening and expanding NATO in order to maintain the US presence in Europe and weaken Russia. This culminated with military interventions in the former Yugoslavia, intended to maintain European dependence on US armed power.

In the 1990s, US strategists from both sides of the political aisle began to look for ways in which Washington could use its enormous military power to keep its main rivals in check. On the right, the most influential group was a neoconservative think-tank named the Project for the New American Century (PNAC), several of whose members became prominent figures in the George W. Bush administration. In a report issued in September 2000, PNAC outlines the key strategic goal of "maintaining global US pre-eminence . . . and shaping the international security order in line with American principles and interests." Key to achieving this goal, according to the report, was seizing control of the Persian Gulf region. "While the unresolved conflict with Iraq provides the immediate justification, the need for a substantial American force presence in the Gulf transcends the issue of the regime of Saddam Hussein."13 Regime change in Iraq would, it was assumed, not only give the United States control over the second largest oil reserves in the world but also significant leverage over its main rivals, particularly Europe and China, both highly dependent on Middle Eastern oil.

This was not just the fantasy of neoconservative extremists. By the end of the 1990s, there was bipartisan consensus that Saddam's government needed to be removed, and it had become official US policy. Shortly after the PNAC report of September 2000, the bipartisan Center for Strategic and International Studies issued a report on the geopolitics of energy that pointed to a "fundamental contradiction" between the need to modernize Iraq's oil infrastructure in order to increase production to meet growing world energy demand and continued sanctions.14 But if the sanctions were lifted while the Iraqi regime remained in power, then the chief beneficiaries would be France and Russia, which had negotiated major oil concessions with Saddam.

Underlying this immediate concern were continuing imperial rivalries with other major powers, driven by the same intersecting logics of economic and military competition analyzed by Lenin and Bukharin in different geopolitical circumstances ninety years earlier. None of the other powers could threaten Washington's hegemony on a global level, but they could erode US dominance in specific areas. The long-term goal of US imperialism was to maintain its control of Middle East oil---first established after World War II---by shoring up friendly governments in the area no matter what their records might be on human rights, and by containing and when possible replacing unfriendly ones. It was in fact the Democrat Jimmy Carter who articulated this most clearly in his January 1980 State of the Union address: "An attempt by any outside force to gain control of the Persian Gulf region will be regarded as an assault on the vital interests of the United States of America, and such an assault will be repelled by any means necessary, including military force."15 The so-called "Carter Doctrine" is a reminder that control over what a 1945 State Department memorandum to President Harry Truman had described as "a stupendous source of strategic power, and one of the greatest material prizes in world history,"16 was always a bipartisan project.

When the Bush administration came to office in 2001, however, the goal of regime change in Iraq was not immediately achievable, since there was insufficient domestic support for an outright invasion. The PNAC report had bluntly noted in the previous year that what was needed to implement such a policy was "some catastrophic and catalyzing event---like a new Pearl Harbor."17 The attacks of 9/11 thus provided the Bush administration with exactly the opportunity it needed to pursue an agenda that it had already decided on. As Gilbert Achcar puts it: "September 11, 2001 came as a terrific windfall for the Bush administration. . . . The spectacular blow struck by Islamic fundamentalists, former US allies who had become its sworn enemies, created such a huge political trauma in the United States that the Bush administration thought it was possible at last, for the first time, to break once and for all with the 'Vietnam syndrome' and return to the unbridled military interventionism of the first Cold War decades."18

The important point to note is that while there were tactical differences between the administration and some other sections of the political establishment about how best to pursue the agenda, there was near unanimity on the goal itself. The shift to a much more aggressive and unilateralist foreign policy was not the result of a neoconservative coup but a consequence of radically new circumstances providing US imperialism with the opportunity to solve its problems in a new way.

Some in the Bush administration wanted to attack Iraq immediately, but for political reasons it was decided that an invasion of Afghanistan was politically more feasible and could be a stepping stone towards the goal of removing Saddam Hussein. It had the additional benefit of allowing Washington to set up a string of military bases in Central Asia, thus increasing its control over Caspian oil and gas, and giving it greater leverage against both Russia and China.

Once the operation in Afghanistan seemed to have been completed, the Bush administration turned its attention to Iraq, with support from nearly all the leading figures in the Democratic Party. The conflicts with France, Germany, Russia, and China in the buildup to the invasion revealed the key rivalries between the major powers that were at the root of US policy. The war on Iraq was supposed to assert US dominance not just over the Middle East but over these economic and military rivals too. The goal was to remove a regime hostile to US interests, to gain control over Iraqi oil, thereby increasing US leverage over Europe and China, and to use Iraq as a base to reshape the entire Middle East along lines congenial to Washington.

In an interview on BBC television, General Jay Garner, former head of the Iraq occupation authority, described Washington's long-term vision of Iraq as a political and military base, modeled on America's control of the Pacific in the early twentieth century.

We used the Philippines. And the Philippines, for the lack of a better term, it was in essence a coaling station for the navy. And it allowed the US navy to maintain presence in the Pacific. They maintained great presence in the Pacific.

I think . . . we should look right now at Iraq as our coaling station in the Middle East, where we have some presence there and it gives a settling effect there, and it also gives us a strategic advantage there, and I think we ought to just accept that and take that for a period of time, as long as the Iraqi people are willing to allow us to be guests in their country.19

This interview reveals some of the continuities of current policy with the long history of US imperialism. But the world that US policy has brought about over the past few decades has created new problems for US imperialism. The occupation of Iraq first bogged down the US militarily while at the same time removing Iran's biggest rival in the region, leading in turn to an intensification of Washington's confrontation with Tehran.

Even more importantly, while Washington has been largely successful in reintegrating the countries of Western Europe into a US-dominated international framework since the end of the Cold War, the same is not true for Russia (which is still a major military power, with thousands of nuclear missiles) or China (which is a rising economic and military power). Indeed US policy makers are obsessed by the rise of China and how they can prevent it from becoming a major challenger to US power on a regional or even a global level. The US used 9/11 to set up military bases in central Asia. In response, Russia and China formed the Shanghai Cooperation Organization in an effort to maneuver the United States out of the region. They were successful in pushing it out of Uzbekistan, with Russia and China supporting the Uzbek regime. That is an illustration of a process unfolding on a much larger scale in which the major centers of economic and military power in the world continue to maneuver against each other for advantage. None of them are prepared to stand out against the United States directly because the costs are too high, but the process illustrates the fragmentation and instability of the global system.

The shift to a much more aggressive and unilateralist foreign policy by the Bush administration following 9/11 was not the result of neoconservatives hijacking the government,20 but a consequence of radically new circumstances providing US imperialism with the opportunity to solve its problems in a new way. For that reason, little changed when Barack Obama replaced Bush as president, as the conservative New York Times columnist Ross Douthat pointed out in 2011:

For those with eyes to see, the daylight between the foreign policies of George W. Bush and Barack Obama has been shrinking ever since the current president took the oath of office. But last week made it official: When the story of America's post-9/11 wars is written, historians will be obliged to assess the two administrations together, and pass judgment on the Bush-Obama era.21

This is not exactly what most of Obama's supporters had in mind when they voted for him in 2008, but two-and-a-half years later, the record speaks for itself. Troops were eventually withdrawn from Iraq in accordance with a plan begun under Bush, but the war in Afghanistan was expanded, with regular attacks across the border into neighboring Pakistan and high numbers of civilian deaths, a secret bombing campaign in Yemen exposed by Wikileaks, an open bombing campaign against Libya, and saber rattling against Iran. Obama also announced a "pivot to Asia" to challenge China's growing power and greatly increased the US military presence in Africa. US imperialism did not end when George Bush left office.

These developments confirmed Lenin's observation that imperialism is not simply a policy, but something built into the fabric of developed capitalism, as economic competition gives rise to geopolitical competition and military intervention. The form of that competition can change over time, but so long as capitalism exists, so will imperialism. That is why---apart from minor differences---both major political parties in the United States pursue the same foreign policy agenda.

Critics on the left

I have argued that despite changes in the structure of capitalism in the last one hundred years, Lenin's and Bukharin's theories retain their relevance and remain an essential starting point for analyzing contemporary imperialism, but many on the left reject this view. The Canadian Marxist David McNally acknowledges the strengths of the analyses put forward by Lenin and Bukharin, but he goes on to argue "there were real limits to these theories---limits which become especially disenabling today."22 What are these limits? McNally mentions three.

First, according to McNally Lenin believed "that colonialism pivoted on the export to the colonies of excess capital---capital which could find no profitable outlet at home. Yet the very tables he produced in his booklet indicated instead that the bulk of exported capital went from one rich capitalist nation to another---as it continues to do today."23 McNally is certainly right to point out that most foreign investment by advanced capitalist economies goes to other developed economies, but Lenin does not deny this, and his theory does not depend on rejecting this claim. What is essential to his view is that control of the territory, resources, and markets of the less developed world plays a vital role in competition with other developed capitalisms, not that investments in such countries makes up the bulk of exported capital.

Second, McNally criticizes Bukharin for taking "an historically specific period of integration of capital with the nation-state in the early twentieth century and inflat[ing] it into an inherent tendency of capitalist development, arguing that capital and the state fuse over time. Yet as recent waves of privatization and deregulation indicate, the relationship between state and capital is much more fluid and changeable." Again, McNally's descriptive point is correct---Bukharin's account of the relation between state and capital is obviously too simple, even though it does describe a trend that remained dominant for the middle as well as the early part of the century. In fact, as we have noted, Bukharin himself in Imperialism and World Economy, pointed to the contradictory tendencies that modern capitalism exhibits:

The development of world capitalism leads, on the one hand, to an internationalisation of the economic life and, on the other, to the leveling of economic differences, and to an infinitely greater degree, the same process of economic development intensifies the tendency to "nationalise" capitalist interests, to form narrow "national" groups armed to the teeth and ready to hurl themselves at one another any moment. (Ch. VIII)

The Marxist writer Chris Harman developed this point in the 1970s:

The trend is towards state capitalism, towards the complete merger of individual capitals in each country with the national state. But the trend is also to the internationalisation of production: the most modern techniques are developed on an international scale; the resources for participation in key industries like chemicals, aerospace, computers, and, increasingly, motors can be obtained by pooling the resources of more than one country.

These two trends---towards state capitalism and towards internationalisation of production---are both complementary and contradictory...

This means that even in the advanced capitalist countries, crosscutting the "state capitalist" trend is another trend -- towards dependence on firms, which see their interests as differing from the interests of the national capital. Of course, they have a home base. Of course, they depend upon a national state to bail them out when it comes to the crunch. But that is not the same as saying that they will willingly subordinate themselves to the national state.24

Since Harman wrote this almost forty years ago, direct state ownership and state planning have greatly declined in most major capitalist countries.25 Nevertheless, it is not true (as is sometimes argued) that most giant corporations have become delinked from specific nation states,26 even if the relationship between state and capital is often characterized by sharp tensions.27 It is this connection between capitalist enterprises and specific national states that is the crucial premise of Bukharin's (and Lenin's) arguments. We need to update Bukharin to take account of the new and highly complex ways in which state and capital are intertwined, but it is the fact that they are intertwined that ultimately matters most.

Finally, according to McNally, "perhaps the biggest flaw in these theories of imperialism is that they saw territorial occupation by the major powers as a necessary feature of global capitalism." Certainly direct occupation and the acquisition of colonies was the way in which imperialism expressed itself in the late nineteenth century and the first half of the twentieth century, and Lenin and Bukharin attempt to explain why. But the hallmark of imperialism is not occupation but control, and what the main capitalist powers learned after World War II was that such control could generally be exercised more effectively using economic coercion, with military power and physical occupations generally held in reserve to deal with temporary emergencies.28 The move from direct colonial occupations to indirect or neocolonialism is certainly of major historical importance, but the underlying dynamic described by Lenin and Bukharin, in which economic competition gives rise to diplomatic, geopolitical, and military maneuvering and confrontation between capitalist states, can explain both imperialism with colonies and imperialism without them.29

The changes that have taken place in the world economy over the past century require anyone who wants to defend the theories of Lenin and Bukharin to develop and elaborate their insights in new ways. But the most influential recent theories of imperialism have tended to reject their central idea of interimperialist conflicts. For example, in their briefly influential book Empire,30 Antonio Negri and Michael Hardt downplayed the importance of nation states and described a world in which imperial domination was maintained by a much more diffuse network of multinational corporations and international institutions.

According to Negri and Hardt, rivalries between the major capitalist states on the one hand, and the huge and systematic differences in economic development and living standards between different parts of the world on the other, are no longer the main features of the world economy. Instead, over the past few decades, old-style imperialism has been replaced by Empire---a transnational, network capitalism in which the dominant economic and political relationships are no longer clustered around centers of national capitalist power, but have broken down the national organization of capitalism into relations that operate transnationally. This leads them to conclude, "no nation-state can today form the center of an imperialist project."31 Later they write, "The history of imperialist, inter-imperialist, and anti-imperialist wars is over. The end of that history has ushered in the reign of peace. Or really, we have entered the era of minor and internal conflicts."32

The problem for this view is that it didn't fit the world in the 1990s, let alone the world after September 11, 2001. Even under Clinton, the United States had openly begun to use its military power to maintain its economic primacy---that's what the war in Kosovo was largely about. Then, little more than a year after Empire was published in 2000, Washington launched a new and more aggressive phase of imperialist intervention in Afghanistan and then Iraq following the 9/11 attacks. Put simply, George W. Bush didn't use US military power in the interests of some anonymous, impersonal transnational network, he used it in the interests of US capitalism. Both the war in Afghanistan and the war in Iraq were assertions of US national power.

Negri and Hardt have various ways of trying to explain what happened after 9/11. One is to claim that Bush is a throwback who represented the past. A more sophisticated variant of this explanation is the claim that Bush represented the interests of backward-looking national capital, not the interests of transnational corporations. But this really doesn't wash. The Bush administration pursued neoliberal economic and trade policies every bit as aggressively as Clinton did and worked hand in glove with the biggest transnational companies. Moreover, as we have seen, Obama essentially continued Bush's policies.

A second view of modern imperialism, defended in greatest detail by Canadian Marxists Sam Gindin and Leo Panitch in their book The Making of Global Capitalism: The Political Economy of American Empire,33 is now more influential on the left. According to this alternative, the world is dominated by US super-imperialism. There are no longer rival centers of capitalist power competing for global or regional hegemony. The resources of the United States are so much greater than any potential competitors that other states are effectively subordinated to Washington's dictates.

On this theory, classical imperialism has been replaced not by the transnational network power of Negri and Hardt's Empire, but by the overwhelming dominance of one national center of capitalist power. Gindin and Pantich argue that since World War II the American empire has integrated and subordinated the entire advanced capitalist world. They emphasize the role of international institutions like the IMF, G-8, NATO, and so on, as means through which the United States asserts its power over the other major capitalist countries.

Now it is obviously true that the United States has considerably more power than other capitalist states in terms of its military strength, the size of its economy, and its financial clout; and it certainly uses a variety of international institutions to maintain its dominance. But the key part of Gindin and Panitch's thesis is that this means that the era of interimperialist rivalry is over. Yet while Washington has been largely successful in integrating the countries of Western Europe into a US-dominated international framework, we have already noted that the same is not true for Russia or China, and that US policy makers are determined to prevent China from becoming a major challenger to its power on a regional, or even a global, level. Gindin and Panitch's response to this is that the Chinese challenge is overstated: "China may perhaps emerge eventually as a pole of interimperial power, but it will obviously remain very far from reaching such a status for a good many decades."34

This analysis, however, may significantly underestimate the rapidity of the changes that are taking place in the global balance of power. This is what lay behind the "pivot to Asia" initiated by Obama during his second term.35 In May 2014, The New York Times reported on China's increasingly aggressive response to Washington's attempt to contain it:

All around Asia, China is pushing and probing at America's alliances, trying to loosen the bonds that have kept the countries close to Washington and allowed the United States to be the pre-eminent power in the region since World War II.

In just the past week, China traded punches with Vietnam and Japan. A Chinese fishing vessel rammed and sank a Vietnamese fishing boat on Monday near a Chinese deep-water oilrig that was placed in disputed waters off the coast of Vietnam. That confrontation followed a close encounter last Saturday in which two pairs of Chinese fighter jets flew close to Japanese surveillance and electronic intelligence planes, in disputed airspace claimed by both countries.36

Gindin and Panitch seem to downplay the significance of such conflicts because they rely on a narrow conception of what constitutes interimperial rivalries. In effect, their view is that unless there is a fairly imminent trajectory towards war, such rivalries do not exist. But there can be rivalry between, say, China and the United States, or the United States and France, without there being any immediate threat of war. When Lenin and Bukharin were writing at the beginning of the twentieth century, imperialist rivalries did lead to war between major powers for one simple reason---there were a number of competing states that were relatively evenly matched in military terms. Today, of course, that is no longer the case. The United States spends almost as much on its military budget as the rest of the world combined, so the other major powers have a strong incentive to avoid any direct military confrontation.

But interimperialist rivalries can take other forms. The contemporary world is characterized by sharp economic competition that shapes the pattern of trade negotiations between the leading centers of capital accumulation and there are also very important kinds of geopolitical rivalry. As we have noted, for example, Russia and China have formed a bloc to counter the US presence in central Asia. Neither country is willing to confront Washington directly, because the costs would be much too high, but the biggest economies nevertheless maneuver to gain economic and trade advantages, they look for ways to strengthen their political clout and weaken that of their competitors, and they look for ways to widen their areas of influence.

Lenin and Bukharin would no doubt recognize this as interimperialist rivalry, even if war between the major powers were not a likely immediate prospect. Indeed, even in their own day it took many years for such a war to break out, proceeded by a series of smaller wars, including the Second Boer War (1899--1902), the Russo-Japanese War (1904--05), and the Balkan Wars (1912 and 1913). What has not changed is that the most powerful states will use their military strength in whatever ways they can to pursue their own interests, typically by intervening militarily in weaker countries, or at least threatening to intervene. Russia's sudden invasion and annexation of Crimea in early 2014, detaching it from Ukraine, is a dramatic case in point.37

The US ruling class is currently playing for very high stakes, trying to maintain its dominant global position in a world in which the distribution of economic power is changing to its disadvantage. That produces a highly unstable and potentially very dangerous situation. Other leading powers may not be prepared to challenge the United States directly at the moment, but that doesn't mean that they won't be prepared to do so in the future. Unless we get rid of capitalism, the prospect of future military confrontations on a much larger scale remains. Even without major military confrontations between powers, it is impossible to deny the devastating effect of regional wars---such as those raging currently in the Middle East, for example---in which great powers, and in particular the United States and its allies, have played an outsize role.

Moreover, even if a war between the United States and any of its major rivals is unlikely in the immediate future, competition between the big powers is the principal reason why it has been impossible to negotiate a solution to the ongoing climate crisis, which threatens to turn into a catastrophe before the end of the century.38 When Rosa Luxemburg warned that the choice for humanity is between socialism and barbarism, she had in mind the horrors of World War I.39 A century later, we know that barbarism can take more than one form.

It is obviously true that one cannot understand the complexities of contemporary geopolitics and imperialism simply by reading Lenin and Bukharin. But it is equally true that if one ignores their key insights, it is not possible to make much sense of the otherwise bewildering set of events that is currently being played out on the international chessboard and, just as importantly, to come up with a coherent political strategy to oppose militarism, war, environmental destruction, and all the other horrors that capitalism creates. The framework Lenin and Bukharin developed a hundred years ago, taken as a methodology and not as a set of dogmas, retains its relevance for activists today.

This article is based on the introduction to a new edition of Lenin's Imperialism and Bukharin's Imperialism and World Economy, forthcoming from Haymarket Books.

The full text of both works can also be found at the Marxist Internet Archive: https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1916/imp-hsc/index.htm, https://www.marxists.org/archive/bukharin/works/1917/imperial/index.htm

"Lenin: Speech to the Petrograd Soviet by Gregory Zinoviev Celebrating Lenin's Recovery from Wounds Received in the Attempt Made on his Life on August 30, 1918," http://www.marxists.org/archive/zinoviev/works/1918/lenin/index.htm. The quotation is from the section titled "The Metal Workers Meeting." Trotsky repeats this story in Chapter 18 of his autobiography, My Life, but incorrectly locates Lenin in Switzerland: http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/1930/mylife/ch18.htm.

Lenin, The Right of Nations to Self-Determination, https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/self-det/index.htm. Lenin's views are summarized in Tom Lewis, "Marxism and nationalism," ISR 13, August--September 2000 (http://isreview.org/issues/13/marxism_nationalism_part1.shtml) and ISR 14, October--November 2000 (http://isreview.org/issues/14/marxism_nationalism_part2.shtml).

See Chapters IV, VI, and VII.

Notes from the Editors, Monthly Review, Vol. 55, No. 8, January 2004, http://monthlyreview.org/2004/01/01/january-2004-volume-55-number-8. Lenin was also influenced by the British liberal economist J.A. Hobson's book Imperialism: A Study, first published in 1902. However, Hobson viewed imperialism as beneficial only to certain sectors of business (such as the arms industry), not rooted in the nature of capitalism itself.

Michael Kidron, "Imperialism--Highest Stage but One," International Socialism (1st series), No. 9, Summer 1962, http://marxists.org/archive/kidron/works/1962/xx/imperial.htm.

Marx, Capital, Vol. 1, Ch. 25, "The General Law of Capitalist Accumulation," http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch25.htm.

"Ultra-imperialism," Die Neue Zeit, September 1914, http://marxists.org/archive/kautsky/1914/09/ultra-imp.htm.

"Speech Delivered At A Conference Of Chairmen Of Uyezd, Volost And Village Executive Committees Of Moscow Gubernia," October 15, 1920. http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1920/oct/15b.htm.

For a brief account of this period and the subsequent collapse of the Soviet bloc see Phil Gasper, "The legacy of Stalinism," International Socialist Review 69, January 2010. http://isreview.org/issue/69/legacy-stalinism.

Patricia Lewis, Heather Williams, Benoît Pelopidas and Sasan Aghlani, "Too Close for Comfort: Cases of Near Nuclear Use and Options for Policy," Chatham House Report, April 2014. http://www.chathamhouse.org/publications/papers/view/199200

Rebuilding America's Defenses: Strategy, Forces and Resources For a New Century (September 2000). PNAC disbanded in 2006 and its website no longer exists, but a copy of the report is available at http://www.informationclearinghouse.info...

CSIS Panel Report, The Geopolitics of Energy into the 21st Century (Washington: CSIS, 2000), "Executive Summary," xiv.

The State of the Union Address Delivered Before a Joint Session of the Congress, January 23, 1980. http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=33079.

Report by the Coordinating Committee of the Department of State, "Draft Memorandum to President Truman," Foreign Relations of the United States, Diplomatic Papers, The Near East and Africa, Vol. 8, 1945, 45.

Rebuilding America's Defenses.

"U.S. Imperial Strategy in the Middle East," Monthly Review Vol. 55, No. 9, February 2004, https://monthlyreview.org/2004/02/01/u-s-imperial-strategy-in-the-middle-east.

Interview on BBC Newsnight, broadcast March 19, 2004, http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/newsnight/3552737.stm.

The "hijacking" claim was common among American liberals at the time of the US invasion of Iraq in 2003, for example in Robert Kuttner's Boston Globe op-ed "Neo-cons have hijacked US foreign policy," Boston Globe, September 10, 2003, http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2003/09/10/neo_cons_have_hijacked_us_foreign_policy/. It is also worth noting that many neoconservatives were originally Cold War Democrats. As two leading neocons pointed out at the time, "Most, like former U.N. Ambassador Jeane Kirkpatrick, simply had been hawkish Democrats who became disenchanted with their party as it drifted further left in the 1970s. Many neocons, such as Richard Perle, originally rallied around Henry 'Scoop' Jackson, a Democratic senator who led the opposition to the Nixon-Ford policy of détente with the Soviet Union." Max Boot and Jeane J. Kirkpatrick, "Think again: Neocons," Foreign Policy, January/February 2004, http://www.cfr.org/united-states/think-again-neocons/p7592.

"Whose Foreign Policy Is It?" New York Times, May 8, 2011, http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/09/opinion/09douthat.html.

David McNally, "Understanding imperialism: Old and new dominion," Against the Current 117, July--August 2005, http://www.solidarity-us.org/site/node/255. McNally also briefly discusses the rather different views about imperialism developed by Rosa Luxemburg during the same time. I agree with McNally's criticisms of Luxemburg.

See the table showing "Distribution (Approximate) of Foreign Capital in Different Parts of the Globe (circa 1910)" in Chapter IV, which indicates that over two-thirds of the combined foreign investment of Britain, France, and Germany was in Europe and America.

Chris Harman, "Better a Valid Insight Than a Wrong Theory," International Socialism (1st series), No.100, July 1977, https://www.marxists.org/history/etol/writers/harman/1977/07/insight.htm.

China, which has developed its own variation of state capitalism during this time, in which state capitalists and private capitalists are both part of the ruling class, is the most significant exception. For a brief sketch see Tom Bramble, "China after the boom," Red Flag, July 29, 2015, https://redflag.org.au/article/china-after-boom.

The view that globalization has produced a transnational ruling class without any national ties is defended by the sociologist William I. Robinson in A Theory of Global Capitalism (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2004). Robinson debates his critics in the May 2012 issue of Critical Sociology.

See Chris Harman, "The State and Capitalism Today," International Socialism 2:51, Summer 1991, (http://www.marxists.org/archive/harman/1991/xx/statcap.htm), for an attempt to analyze the complex ways in which state and capital remain entwined.

In the 1960s and 1970s some dependency theorists believed that this indirect control was so strong that countries in the so-called Third World would remain in a permanently backward state. The subsequent development of countries such as China, South Korea, India and Brazil has undermined this view.

For more on this topic, see Harry Magdoff, Imperialism Without Colonies (New York: Monthly Review Press, 2003).

Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2000. Also see the review by Tom Lewis, "Empire Strikes Out," International Socialist Review 24, July--August 2002, http://www.isreview.org/issues/24/empire_strikes_out.shtml.

Hardt and Negri, Empire, xiv.

Ibid, 189.

New York: Verso Books, 2012. For further commentary see Ashley Smith, "Global Empire or Imperialism?" International Socialist Review 92, Spring 2014, http://isreview.org/issue/92/global-empire-or-imperialism.

"Global Capitalism and American Empire," in Leo Panitch and Colin Leys (eds.), Socialist Register 2004: The New Imperial Challenge (New York: Monthly Review Press, 2003), 25.

See Ashley Smith, "US imperialism's pivot to Asia," International Socialist Review 88, March--April 2013, http://isreview.org/issue/88/us-imperialisms-pivot-asia.

Helene Cooper and Jane Perlez, "U.S. Sway in Asia Is Imperiled as China Challenges Alliances," New York Times, May 30, 2014, http://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/31/world/asia/us-sway-in-asia-is-imperiled-as-china-challenges-alliances.html .

Alan Maass, "The battle over Ukraine intensifies," Socialist Worker, March 19, 2014, http://socialistworker.org/2014/03/19/battle-over-ukraine-intensifies

See, for instance, Chris Williams, "Understanding Warsaw: Capitalism, Climate Change and Neocolonialism," Truthout, 25 November 2013, http://www.truth-out.org/opinion/item/20194-understanding-warsaw-capitalism-climate-change-neocolonialism

"What Does the Spartacus League Want?" https://www.marxists.org/archive/luxemburg/1918/12/14.htm

Sapronov and the Russian Revolution Yurii Colombo

Standing up to the Zionist backlash against BDS Bill Mullen

Legacies of colonialism in Africa Lee Wengraf

Austerity, neoliberalism, and the Indian working class Snehal Shingavi

Disability and the Soviet Union: Advances and retreats Keith Rosenthal

The critical communism of Antonio Labriola Doug Enaa Greene

The legacy of Louis Althusser Andrew Ryder

"A sense of hope and the possibility of solidarity" Roxanne Dunbar-Ortiz interviewed by Ragina Johnson and Brian Ward

Islamic fundamentalism, the Arab Spring, and the Left Gilbert Achcar interviewed by Ashley Smith

Knocking down straw figures Ian Angus reviews Anthropocene or Capitalocene: Nature, History, and the Crisis of Capitalism by Jason Moore

Have the Democrats evolved? Paul Heideman reviews Listen, Liberal: or: Whatever Happened to the Party of the People? by Thomas Frank

Giving voice to the Syrian Revolution Yasser Munif reviews Burning Country: Syrians in Revolution and War by Robin Yassin-Kassab and Leila Al-Shami

From "waste people" to "white trash" Eric Kerl reviews White Trash: the 400-Year Untold History of Class in America by Nancy Isenberg

Defending our right to criticize Israel Dorian Bon reviews Uncivil Rights: Palestine and the Limits of Academic Freedom by Steven Salaita

Marxism and Nationalism: Part 1

By Tom Lewis

In the international education of the workers of the oppressor countries, emphasis must necessarily be laid on their advocating freedom for the oppressed countries to secede and their fighting for it. Without this there can be no internationalism. | –V.I.Lenin, “The Discussion on Self-Determination Summed Up”

Imperialism is the stage of capitalism in which a few economically advanced states dominate the rest of the world. Imperialism coalesces as a system during the latter half of the nineteenth century, but its cruel dynamic also drives the process known as “globalization” today. This means that we continue to live in a world in which a handful of strong nations use their economic and military power to subjugate and exploit weaker nations. It also means that our world is still one in which the strong nations regularly face off against each other—threatening, preparing, or unleashing wars whose basic aim is to secure a competitive advantage for one nation over its rivals in imperialist plunder.

One of the consequences of imperialism is nationalism. As capitalism spreads around the globe, it also gives rise to powerful movements of resistance. Initially, the revolt of workers and peasants in countries oppressed by imperialism almost invariably takes the form of nationalism. That is why it is crucial for socialists to understand how to approach nationalism and how to assess the various struggles for national liberation today.

Socialists are internationalists. Whereas nationalists believe that the world is divided primarily into different nationalities, socialists consider social class to be the primary divide. For socialists, class struggle—not national identity—is the motor of history. And capitalism creates an international working class that must fight back against an international capitalist class.

But imperialism also creates something else. In a world defined by the existence of richer and poorer nations, not only do “nationalisms of the oppressed” emerge as agents of struggle against global capitalism; “nationalisms of the oppressor” emerge as well and are used by bosses and politicians in the strong nations to justify the imperialist system. Moreover, a layer of workers in the dominant nations actually comes to think that workers, too, stand to gain from imperialism's oppression of the weaker nations. These nationalisms of the oppressor represent formidable obstacles to building the international solidarity among workers that is needed in order to succeed in the fight against global capitalism.

How, then, should socialists relate as internationalists to a world that is nevertheless divided into oppressor and oppressed nations? Marxists have sometimes been criticized for allegedly failing to comprehend the politics of the national question. Yet the revolutionary Marxist tradition offers an invaluable framework within which to understand the complexity of a world that is simultaneously characterized by the existence of nations and the globalization of capital. The purpose of this article, therefore, is to explain the central pillar of the Marxist approach to national oppression: Lenin's argument in favor of the right of nations to self-determination.

Marx and Engels on national oppression

No nation can be free if it oppresses other nations. | –Frederick Engels, “Eine polnische Problamation”

The nation that oppresses another nation forges its own chains. | –Karl Marx, “Konfidentielle Mitteilung”

In the late eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, the great struggles for national liberation represented attempts to overthrow feudalism and absolutist monarchy in the interest of removing economic and political impediments to the full development of capitalism. Capitalism was in the process of changing from being a mere sector of the economy into becoming the dominant mode of social organization. To consolidate this transition and to secure the ongoing conditions for reproducing capitalist society, a new form of state was required—one based not on personal allegiance to a royal family but rather on a shared language, a common territory, and the perception of a group history and destiny.

The victory of capitalism over feudalism, first in Europe and later throughout the continents, thus entailed strong links with national movements: “For the complete victory of commodity production, the bourgeoisie must capture the home market, and there must be politically united territories whose population speaks a single language,... [which establishes] a close connection between the market and each and every proprietor, big or little, and between seller and buyer.”[1] Nationalism furnished the bourgeoisie of a specific territory with the ideological elements it needed to impose an official language and to lay down borders on the basis of a (usually invented) collective past. Moreover, there arose a tendency within the national movements themselves toward the formation of nation-states, precisely because nation-states could best satisfy the political requirements of modern—i.e., capitalist—society. For these reasons, all of the leading Marxist contributions to the debate on the national question have accepted that “the nation state is typical and normal for the capitalist period.”[2]

Marx and Engels supported many of the national liberation struggles of their day because they viewed capitalism as a historic advance over feudalism. They were not blind to the misery and devastation that capitalism brought as well, but they understood that capitalism could develop the productive capacities of human society to levels unimaginable under feudalism. They understood further that capitalism brought into existence a class of producers—the proletariat, the modern working class—that for the first time in history was truly collective. This class thereby embodied the potential for democratic self-rule. In the eyes of Marx and Engels, every victory for capitalism over feudalism propelled humanity further toward the goal of freedom from material want and political subjugation.

The major oppressor nations during the lifetimes of Marx and Engels were Russia and Hapsburg Austria. Russia ruled by force over Poland and had crushed the democratic revolution in Hungary in 1849. Together, Russia and Austria interfered in the internal affairs of Germany and Italy to block the unification of these nations. Marx and Engels “supported all national movements which were directed against the Tsars and the Hapsburgs. At the same time,... they opposed national movements which objectively played into the hands of the Tsars or the Hapsburgs.”[3] Marx and Engels went as far as to call for revolutionary wars in order to win independence for Poland, Hungary, Germany, and Italy. The aim was “to inflict a final defeat on the last remnants of feudalism in Europe” and to advance “the process of clearing the ground for the full development of bourgeois democracy and so for the struggle of the working class against the system.”[4]

The historically progressive nature of capitalism in relation to feudalism, however, did not mean that Marx and Engels automatically supported every national movement. They opposed the national movements of the South Slavs—Serbs, Croats, and Czechs—during the 1848 revolution, arguing that these movements objectively “aided the main enemy: Croatian troops, who hated the Magyars more than they did the Hapsburg Empire, helped the Tsar's troops as they marched into Hungary; Czech troops helped to suppress revolutionary Vienna.”[5] At the time of the Great Rebellion of 1857 in India, Marx and Engels welcomed the uprising as a “national revolt,” despite their belief that British imperialism was in the process of destroying feudalism in India.

Thus Marx and Engels did not allow economic criteria to dictate whether they would lend support to specific national movements. Rather, they gave or withheld support on the basis of a political assessment of each movement in the international context.

The case of Ireland provided the main stimulus to Marx and Engels' later development of their ideas on national oppression. Initially, Marx and Engels considered that the expansion of capitalism, both in Europe and around the globe, was lessening the significance of the nation-state and therefore of the movements for national independence. “National differences, and antagonisms between peoples, are daily more and more vanishing, owing to the development of the bourgeoisie, to freedom of commerce, to the world market, to uniformity in the mode of production and in the conditions of life corresponding thereto.”[6] Thus they looked to socialist revolution as the means by which national oppression would be ended: “In proportion as the exploitation of one individual by another is put to an end, the exploitation of one nation by another will also be put to an end. In proportion as the antagonism between classes within the nation vanishes, the hostility of one nation to another will come to an end.”[7]

Considerable truth resides both in Marx and Engels' notion that national differences diminish as a result of the globalization of capital and in their view that only with the advent of socialism can national oppression be eradicated once and for all. Yet Marx and Engels eventually realized that they had underestimated the possibility of sometimes achieving bourgeois democratic freedoms in the less economically developed nations short of socialist revolution. They also saw that they had overlooked the concrete difficulties of breaking the hold that nationalism exercises over workers in the more developed nations.

A renewal of the Irish national struggle in the 1860s led Marx and Engels to modify their views. In fact they began to approach the national question less from the angle of the struggle between capitalism and feudalism and more from the angle of the struggle between the imperialist powers and the colonized nations. Marx conveyed to Engels in early November 1867: “I used to think the separation of Ireland from England was impossible. Now I think it is inevitable, although after separation there may come federation.”[8] At the end of the same month he explained, “What the Irish need is... self-government and independence from England.... Agrarian revolution.... Protective tariffs against England.”[9] And two years later he wrote to Dr.Kugelmann:

The English working class... will never be able to do anything decisive here in England before they separate their attitude towards Ireland definitively from that of the ruling classes, and not only make common cause with the Irish, but even take the initiative in dissolving the Union established in 1801. And this must be done not out of sympathy with the Irish, but as a demand on the interests of the English proletariat. If not the English proletariat will forever remain bound to the leading strings of the ruling classes, because they will be forced to make a common front with them against Ireland.[10]_

Here Marx achieves a key insight that will serve as the bedrock of Lenin's development of the socialist approach to national oppression. “The nationalism of the workers belonging to an oppressor nation binds them to their rulers and only does harm to themselves, while the nationalism of an oppressed nation can lead them to fight back against those rulers.”[11]

The 1903 Congress

Right of self-determination for all nations included within the bounds of the state. | –Article 9, Program of the Russian Social Democratic Labor Party (1903)

The RSDLP—the party to which Lenin belonged—convened its Second Congress in the summer of 1903. Delegates met in secret, first in Brussels and then in London, where they had been forced to move because of pressure from the Belgian police. The 1903 Congress is justly famous as a turning point in the history of Marxism, for it was here that Bolshevism (the majority) was born out of a split with Menshevism (the minority).

But the 1903 Congress deserves its place in history for other reasons as well. In particular, it became the forum at which the most important debates on the national question were held prior to the outbreak of the First World War and the collapse of the Second International in 1914. Two debates unfolded at the congress, each with far-reaching implications. The first concerned the Jewish Labor Bund (“bund” means “league” in Yiddish) and party organization. The second concerned Polish self-determination.

The 1903 Congress took up as its first agenda item the Bund's demand that it be recognized as the sole representative of the Jewish proletariat living in Russia. Jews were horribly oppressed throughout the Russian Empire, living under harsh legal restrictions and terrorized by pogroms. The Bund was founded by Jewish socialists in 1897 and immediately began organizing among Jewish workers in Lithuania, Poland, and Russia (all areas falling within the Tsar's empire). Bund members were genuine revolutionaries who adamantly rejected Zionism, also founded in 1897,[12]_ which they correctly regarded as a form of reactionary Jewish nationalism.

At the First Congress of the RSDLP in 1898, the Bund entered the party on the basis of “autonomy.” Soon after the 1898 Congress, however, the RSDLP was declared illegal and driven underground. Hence, relations among its various sections remained informal, and different sections of the party often acted as independent organizations.

In 1903, the Bund sought clarification of its status in the RSDLP. Lieber, speaking on behalf of the Central Committee of the Bund, explained that the expression “autonomy” now seemed too vague. He argued instead that the Bund's relations with the RSDLP should be based on the principle of “federation.” Under “autonomy,” the Bund enjoyed the right to form “subsidiary organizations and special groups and publish their own newspapers in their native tongue and so on.”[13] They also had the right to direct their own activities free from petty interference from the RSDLP Central Committee. Under “federation,” however, neither the RSDLP Central Committee nor the RSDLP's highest body—the elected Party Congress—would be able to overrule decisions taken by the Bund in matters pertaining to the Jewish proletariat. Organizationally, the Bund would function as an independent body.

“Federation” was designed to create special safeguards that would protect the interests of Jewish workers, as an oppressed group, from the RSDLP as a whole. Lieber justified the need for an independent organization of the Jewish proletariat on the grounds of a fundamental distrust: “The Jewish proletariat is very much more strongly interested in the struggle against the exceptional restrictions that are imposed on it than the rest of the proletariat is, and for this reason it is also a more active fighter against this oppression.”[14]

Trotsky, himself a Jew, responded forcefully to Lieber's argument:

If the Bund, lacking confidence in the Party, is... demanding safeguards, that we can understand. But how can we put our signatures to this demand? It would restrict our freedom, and the freedom of our successors, to make decisions. And why? So as to prevent suppression of the legitimate interests of the Jewish proletariat by the Party, that is, in order to insure ourselves against committing an act of betrayal. To accept such conditions would mean that we acknowledged our own moral and political bankruptcy, it would mean committing moral and political suicide. The congress will not do that.[15]_

In his contribution to the debate, Lenin offered a concrete assessment of the organizational implications of the Bund's demand to be the sole representative of the Jewish proletariat. He believed that to accept the Bund's proposal would amount to internalizing within the party the very divisions among workers that class society relentlessly seeks to impose.

Federation is harmful because it sanctions segregation and alienation, elevating them to the status of a principle, a law. Complete alienation does indeed exist among us, and we ought not to sanction it, or cover it with a fig leaf, but to combat it, and we ought resolutely to acknowledge and proclaim the need firmly and unswervingly to advance towards the closest unity....We recognize no obligatory partitions, and that is why we reject federation in principle.[16]_

Lenin went on to specify that different groupings will always form within the party, “groupings of comrades who are not wholly of one mind on questions of program, tactics or organization.”[17] But, he argued, there should be only one party within which these differences arise: “Let all like-minded Party members join in a single group, instead of groups being formed in one section of the Party, separately from groups in another section, and then having a union not of groups holding different views, or with different shades of opinion, but of sections of the Party, each containing different groups.”[18]

Lenin's final point addressed the question of the Bund's distrust of the party's central leadership. The RSDLP was organized on the basis of “democratic centralism.” In other words, it was a party which maximized opportunities for internal debate, but which acted as one after an issue had been decided by majority vote. Lenin emphasized that “centralism requires the absence of all partitions between the center and even the most remote and out-of-the-way sections of the Party. Our Party center will be given the absolute right to communicate directly with every single Party member.”[19] While every party branch or committee should enjoy “autonomy in the sense of freedom from petty interference by the center,” Lenin insisted that the central leadership should aggressively challenge any manifestation of passivity or indifference within the party regarding national oppression:

Does the Bund really suppose that the Party would tolerate the existence of a center that interfered in a “petty” way in the affairs of any Party organization or group?...Is it not, in fact, the duty of our entire Party to fight, for example, for full equality of rights and even for the recognition of the right of nations to self-determination? Consequently, if any section of our Party were to fail in this duty, it would undoubtedly be liable to censure, by virtue of our principles: it would undoubtedly be liable to correction by the central institutions of the Party. And if that duty was being neglected consciously and deliberately, despite full opportunity to perform it, then this neglect of duty would be treachery.[20]_

After three days of discussion, the 1903 Congress voted to reject the Bund's demand to be the sole representative of the Jewish proletariat and reaffirmed instead that the RSDLP “should unite unconditionally workers of all nationalities in all proletarian organizations without exception (political, trade union, co-operative, educational, etc., etc.).”[21] The Bund then seceded from the party as it departed the congress. A large number of Jewish workers nevertheless remained active in RSDLP branches, and subsequent events in Russia showed that there had been no grounds for the Bund's distrust. The Bund eventually reentered the party, though it never abandoned its nationalist attitude.

The second debate on the national question at the 1903 Congress revolved around what was to become Article 9 of the party platform: “Right of self-determination for all nations included within the bounds of a state.”[22] Article 9 was a sticking point in the relation between revolutionary socialists in Poland—who were members of the Social Democratic Party of the Kingdom of Poland and Lithuania and known as the Polish Social Democrats—and the RSDLP. The Polish party, including Rosa Luxemburg, opposed recognition of the right of self-determination for Poland.

The attitude of the Polish Social Democrats stemmed in part from the fact that the reform Polish socialists, who belonged to the Polish Socialist Party (PSP), considered that the struggle for Poland's national independence from Russia took precedence over every other struggle, including the class struggle. According to the PSP, the struggle of Polish workers for their own emancipation needed to remain secondary because it threatened to disrupt the unity of the Polish people. Thus the Polish Social Democrats correctly maintained that the PSP had betrayed the interests of the international working class, notably, the unity of Polish and Russian workers.

But the Polish Social Democrats did not limit themselves to making this point—a point with which Lenin and the majority of delegates at the 1903 Congress wholeheartedly agreed. Rather, they went on to claim that the demand for Polish independence was historically outdated, even reactionary, because capitalist development had integrated the economies of Poland and Russia to the point of rendering the idea of a Polish nation-state completely obsolete. The political ideal of “a right of nations to self-determination” had thus become equally outmoded. In fact, all around the globe, it was now pointless for the nationalities to aspire to a state if they did not already have one. According to the Polish Social Democrats, all that remained of the national question in the imperialist epoch was the need to defend the “freedom of cultural development of each nationality, through democratization of the historically-given state institutions.”[23]

The Polish Social Democrats urged that Article 9 be changed to read, “Institutions guaranteeing freedom of cultural development to all nations included within the state.”[24] The 1903 Congress, however, voted overwhelmingly to keep the article's original wording, which clearly conceived of “self-determination” as a political—and not a cultural—right. As one delegate voting with the majority explained, “Where the question of nationality is concerned we can adopt only negative propositions—i.e., we are against any constraint being exercised upon a nationality. But, as Social-Democrats, it is of no concern to us whether a particular nationality develops as such. That is a matter for a spontaneous process.”[25]

The Bolsheviks and self-determination

The proletariat demands a democracy that rules out the forcible retention of any one of the nations within the bounds of the state. | –V.I.Lenin, “The National Programme of the RSDLP”

The debate over the national question and the right of nations to self-determination did not end with the 1903 Congress. Rather, it intensified over the course of the following decade. Lenin undertook in a number of writings to clarify the reasoning behind Article 9. He emphasized throughout that, “however meager the Russian Social-Democratic literature on the ‘right of nations to self-determination' may be, it nevertheless shows clearly that this right has always been understood as the right to secession.”[26]

The consistent core of Lenin's arguments in defense of Article 9 is that recognition of the right to self-determination for oppressed nations remains “absolutely essential to the Social Democrats of Russia... for the sake of the basic principles of democracy in general.”[27] In other words, “‘the right to self-determination' implies a democratic system of a type in which there is not only democracy in general, but specifically one in which there could not be an undemocratic solution of the question of secession.”[28] As we shall see, Lenin provides further reasons to uphold this right, but his overarching concern is with its role as a principle that commits socialists to the fullest extension of democratic freedoms and to the swiftest liberation of lives from the yoke of national oppression.

Lenin sharply details what upholding the right to self-determination requires of socialists. Socialists must be “unconditionally hostile to the use of force in any form by the dominant nation (or the nation which constitutes the majority of the population) in respect of a nation that wishes to secede politically.”[29] Socialists must demand that the question of the secession of a given territory be settled only on the basis of a universal, direct, and equal vote of the population of that territory by secret ballot. Moreover, socialists are duty-bound to “conduct an implacable struggle against” all those who at any time “defend or sanction national oppression in general or the denial of the right of nations to self-determination.”[30]

As part of fighting for a consistently democratic state system, Lenin enjoins socialists to demand “unconditional equality for all nationalities” and to “struggle against absolutely all privileges for one or several nationalities.”[31] In particular, socialists must reject the establishment of an official state language and demand instead “the promulgation of a law, operative throughout the state, protecting the rights of every national minority in no matter what part of the state.”[32] All administrative divisions of the state—such as today's electoral and school districts—which fail to reflect the national composition of the population must be brought into line with democratic principles. Finally, “all areas of the state that are distinguished by... the national composition of the population must enjoy wide self-government and autonomy, with institutions organized on the basis of universal, equal and secret voting.”[33]

Assessing national movements

Although socialists must always uphold the right of oppressed nations to self-determination, Lenin by no means considers that socialists should automatically support every movement toward secession and independence. Socialists “should, on the contrary, give [an] independent appraisal, taking into consideration the conditions of capitalist development and the oppression of the proletarians of various nations by the united bourgeoisie of all nationalities, as well as the general tasks of democracy, first of all and most of all the interests of the proletarian class struggle for socialism.”[34] Socialists must be especially prepared

to give most emphatic warning to the proletariat and other working people of all nationalities against direct deception by the nationalistic slogans of “their own” bourgeoisie, who with their saccharine or fiery speeches about “our native land” try to divide the proletariat and divert its attention from their bourgeois intrigues while they enter into an economic and political alliance with the bourgeoisie of other nations....It follows, therefore, that workers who place political unity with “their own” bourgeoisie above complete unity with the proletariat of all nations, are acting against their own interests, against the interests of socialism and against the interests of democracy.[35]_

Lenin considers that a clear distinction must be drawn between two periods of capitalism with respect to the national question. The formation of bourgeois-democratic society and its state characterizes a first period of waning feudalism and absolutism. National movements during this period are mass movements that draw all classes of the population into politics. In contrast, a second period of fully formed capitalist states is characterized by long-established constitutional regimes and a highly developed antagonism between the proletariat and the bourgeoisie. This period increasingly “brings the antagonism between internationally united capital and the international working-class movement into the forefront.”[36]

In this second period, socialists must ask and answer a series of key questions before lending support to specific national movements. Is a particular group really oppressed? Has a consciousness of being a nation formed among those who are oppressed, such that a national movement is developing or already exists? Lenin emphasizes that “our programme refers only to cases where such a movement is actually in existence.”[37]

The most important question socialists must answer is whether support of a specific national movement would advance the interests of the working class. The leadership of national movements is invariably bourgeois at the start. And what the bourgeoisie seeks through the national struggle is either privileges for “its own” already-constituted nation—that is, equal rights alongside the dominant nations in the international market—or, if it represents the struggle of a national minority, exceptional advantages for its own group. Now, it is true that “the bourgeois nationalism of any oppressed nation has a general democratic content that is directed against oppression, and it is this content that we unconditionally support.”[38] It may simultaneously occur, however, that the “saccharine or fiery speeches” of a particular bourgeois leadership produce the effect of dividing workers rather than securing equal rights.

Any interest the working class may have in supporting a bourgeois-led national movement resides in the fact that, to one degree or another, a successful national struggle removes the oppressor nation from the picture and thereby creates conditions that bring the class struggle to the fore. In other words, workers and the national bourgeoisie no longer share a “common enemy”—the imperialist power—and it becomes easier to see the bourgeoisie as the “class enemy.” Should the national movement end up dividing workers, however, then this interest cannot be realized. Hence,

while recognizing equality and equal rights to a national state, the [proletariat] values above all and places foremost the alliance of the proletarians of all nations, and assesses any national demand, any national separation, from the angle of the workers' class struggle....Insofar as the bourgeoisie of the oppressed nation fights its oppressor, we are always, in every case, and more strongly than anyone else, in favor, for we are the staunchest and the most consistent enemies of oppression. But insofar as the bourgeoisie of the oppressed nation stands for its own bourgeois nationalism, we stand against....That is why the proletariat confines itself, so to speak, to the negative demand for recognition of the right to self-determination, without giving guarantees to any nation, and without undertaking to give anything at the expense of another nation.[39]_

On the eve of the First World War, Lenin encapsulated the Bolshevik position on the right of nations to self-determination as follows: “The recognition of the right of secession for all; the appraisal of each concrete question of secession from the point of view of removing all inequality, all privileges, and all exclusiveness.”[40] In other words, socialists provide unconditional support for the right of oppressed nations to self-determination, but they condition their support for the actual independence of a given nation on the interests of the international working class and the principles of democracy in general.

Against cultural-national autonomy

Combat all national oppression? Yes, of course! Fight for any kind of national development, for “national culture” in general? Of course not! | –V.I.Lenin, “Critical Remarks on the National Question”

Lenin's idea that the notion of self-determination expresses a political right, as opposed to an economic or cultural right, led him into heated debates. Again and again, beginning with the 1903 Congress and continuing throughout the last year of his life, Lenin found himself insisting that “the article of our program on the self-determination of nations cannot be interpreted to mean anything but political self-determination, i.e., the right to secede and form a separate state.”[41] Lenin's definition continued to be opposed from two different directions. From one side, Otto Bauer and the Austro-Marxists advocated a cultural interpretation of the right to self-determination. On the other, Rosa Luxemburg and the Polish Marxists argued that capitalist economic development had eliminated the very possibility of self-determination.

Bauer, the leading theoretician of the Austro-Marxists, proposed an elaborate program of “cultural-national autonomy” as the means for reconciling tensions between existing nationalisms and proletarian internationalism. Bauer was concerned to preserve the unity of the workers' movement within the Austro-Hungarian empire, a multinational state under Hapsburg rule which included what are today Austria, Hungary, the Czech Republic, Slovakia, and much of former Yugoslavia. Rivalries between the dominant nationalities—the Germans, the Magyars (Hungarians)—and the various Slavic nationalities threatened to tear the empire apart. The Austro-Marxists misguidedly sought to preserve the unity of the workers' movement by preventing the disintegration of the Hapsburg state.

In The Nationalities Question and Social Democracy (1907), Bauer defined the nation as “the totality of men bound together through a common destiny into a community of character.”[42] He viewed nationalist sentiments among workers as inevitable because, he claimed, the individual human being in the modern era is the product of the nation. According to Bauer, individuals belonging to one nation actually experience the world differently from individuals of another nation, because of the unique cultural environment that has determined their thought and behavior. Rather than repudiating nationalism, Bauer argued that “socialists should embrace the idea of the nation as an important social and historical factor in human existence, and tell the different nationalities that only under socialism would national culture reach its full development.”[43]

With the phrase “cultural-national autonomy” Bauer advocated an “extra-territorial” constitution of the nation. Autonomy would not be granted, say, to a Czech republic on the basis that Czechs comprise the majority nationality residing in a specific region of the Austro-Hungarian empire. Rather, autonomy would be granted to individual Czechs irrespective of territory, no matter which area of the Hapsburg state they might inhabit. This in turn would require that Czechs, Serbs, Germans, Magyars, etc., insofar as they were scattered throughout the empire, be administratively organized into separate “nations,” which would then form components of the Hapsburg state. Nationality for Bauer was not essentially connected with territory; it functioned as the essential component of an individual's identity.

Lenin harshly denounced Bauer's plan for redressing national inequalities as a contradictory and dangerous attempt to fight nationalism with nationalism. “‘Cultural-national autonomy,”' Lenin asserted, “implies precisely the most refined and, therefore, the most harmful nationalism.”[44]

Lenin believed that, in practice, cultural-national autonomy could only intensify the isolation and impoverishment of national minorities. He referred to the oppressive effects of Jim Crow laws on American Blacks and to the hypocrisy of “separate but equal” ideology in the U.S.as a way of illustrating the inadequacy of Bauer's ideas. “At the present time we see that the different nations are unequal in the rights they possess and in their level of development. Under these circumstances, segregating the schools according to nationality would actually and inevitably worsen the conditions of the more backward nations.”[45] Instead, “we must strive to create the fundamental democratic conditions for the peaceful coexistence of the nations on the basis of equal rights.”[46]

Thus Lenin challenged “the whole Bauerite approach, by making a sharp distinction between the fight against every element of discrimination against any group on the basis of their language or culture, and exaltation of particular national cultures.”[47] He insisted that the slogan of “cultural-national autonomy” actually conceals the existence of two cultures within every “national” culture.

The elements of democratic and socialist culture are present, if only in rudimentary form, in every national culture, since in every nation there are toiling and exploited masses, whose conditions of life inevitably give rise to the ideology of democracy and socialism. But every nation also possesses a bourgeois culture (and most nations a reactionary and clerical culture as well) in the form, not merely of “elements,” but of the dominant culture. Therefore, the general “national culture” is the culture of the landlords, the clergy and the bourgeoisie.[48]_

When the right of nations to self-determination shifts from the political realm to the cultural realm, oppressed nations are abandoned to the influence of an “aggressive bourgeois nationalism, which drugs the minds of workers, stultifies and disunites them in order that the bourgeoisie may lead them around by the halter.”[49] That is why Lenin stated repeatedly that socialists “take from each national culture only its democratic and socialist elements; we take them only and absolutely in opposition to the bourgeois culture and the bourgeois nationalism of each nation.”[50]

“Our banner,” Lenin proclaimed, “does not carry the slogan ‘national culture' but international culture, which unites all the nations in a higher, socialist unity, and the way to which is being paved by the international amalgamation of capital.”[51]

[1]

V.I.Lenin, “The Right of Nations to Self-Determination,” Collected Works Vol.20 (Moscow: International Publishers, 1964), p.397.

[2]

Lenin, “Right of Nations,” p.396.

[3]

Tony Cliff, Rosa Luxemburg (London: Bookmarks, 1980), p.55.

[4]

Chris Harman, “The Return of the National Question,” International Socialism 56, Autumn 1992, p.18.

[5]

Cliff, p.56.

[6]

Karl Marx and Frederick Engels, The Communist Manifesto (New York and London: Verso Press, 1998), p.58.

[7]

Marx and Engels, The Communist Manifesto, p.58.

[8]

Marx, “Letter of 2 November 1867,” Marx-Engels Collected Works, Vol.42 (Moscow: International Publishers, 1987), pp.460–61.

[9]

Marx, “Letter of 30 November 1867,” Collected Works, Vol.42, pp.486–87.

[10]

Marx, “Letter of 29 November 1869,” Collected Works, Vol.43 (Moscow: International Publishers, 1987), pp.390–91.

[11]

Harman, p.19.

[12]

This is the date of the founding of Theodor Herzl's new Zionist organization and is commonly accepted as the birthdate of modern political Zionism. There were, however, precursors. As Zachary Lockman points out: “The first organized political manifestation of this new nationalism [Zionism] was the small and loose knit Hibbat Tziyon (‘Love of Zion') movement, which crystallized after the pogroms of 1881 and took the form of a network of local associations established to promote Jewish immigration to and settlement in Palestine, and the reconstitution there of Jewish national life.” Zachary Lockman, Comrades and Enemies: Arab and Jewish Workers in Palestine, 1906–1948 (Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1996), p.24.

[13]

Grigorii Zinoviev, History of the Bolshevik Party (London: New Park Publications, 1973), p.88.

[14]

1903. Second Ordinary Congress of the RSDLP. Complete Text of the Minutes. Brian Pearce, trans.(London: New Park Publications, Ltd., 1978), p.78.

[15]

1903, p.98.

[16]

1903, p.118.

[17]

1903, p.118.

[18]

1903, p.118.

[19]

1903, p.118.

[20]

1903, p.119.

[21]

Lenin, “Theses on the National Question,” Collected Works, Vol.19, p.249.

[22]

1903, p.6.

[23]

1903, p.506.

[24]

1903, p.506.

[25]

1903, p.230.

[26]

Lenin, “Right of Nations,” p.442.

[27]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.243.

[28]

Lenin, “The National Programme of the RSDLP,” Collected Works, Vol.19, p.543.

[29]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.244.

[30]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.244.

[31]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.245.

[32]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.246.

[33]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.246.

[34]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.244.

[35]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.245.

[36]

Lenin, “Right of Nations,” p.401.

[37]

Lenin, “Right of Nations,” p.405.

[38]

Lenin, “Right of Nations,” p.412.

[39]

Lenin, “Right of Nations,” pp.411–12, p.410.

[40]

Lenin, “Right of Nations,” p.412.

[41]

Lenin, “Theses,” p.243.

[42]

Otto Bauer, “The Nationalities Question and Social Democracy,” The Nationalism Reader, Omar Dahbour and Micheline R.Ishay, eds.(Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities Press, 1995), p.183.

[43]

Harman, p.20.

[44]

Lenin, “The National Programme of the RSDLP,” p.541.

[45]

Lenin, “Cultural-National Autonomy,” Collected Works, Vol.19, p.504.

[46]

Lenin, “The Nationality of Pupils in Russian Schools,” Collected Works, Vol.19, p.532.

[47]

Harman, p.31.

[48]

Lenin, “Critical Remarks on the National Question,” Collected Works, Vol.20, p.24.

[49]

Lenin, “Critical Remarks,” p.25.

[50]

Lenin, “Critical Remarks,” p.24.

[51]

Lenin, “Once More on the Segregation of the Schools According to Nationality,” Collected Works, Vol.19, p.549.

In Defense of Revolutionary Organization

By James Radek

What kind of party should revolutionary socialists be focused on building? I want to propose some answers to the organizational questions we're facing. But more than that, I want to invite those who are asking the same questions to commit to answering them together in the coming months and years.

In short, we should not be focused on building a labor party, a broad left party, or an electorally focused party. Some think they already are the party we need and all they need to do is gobble up the other pretenders to the throne. Anarchists and movementists reject the idea of party altogether. So do base-builders and those drawn to building vague “infrastructures of dissent,” to use a phrase popularized by the new book, Revolutionary Rehearsals in the Neoliberal Age. Both mistake tasks of the class for those of revolutionaries.

As one of our predecessor organizations, the International Socialist Organization was collapsing, Hal Draper's critique of “the micro-sect” was set off like a bomb to finish the job. It vilified the fundamental Marxist approach of organizing around a shared politics of some specificity. Questions raised by the rape and abuse in the ISO, as well as the pressures of opportunism, went beyond how to prevent such horrors in our organizations to whether we should enter a reformist socialist organization as scattered individuals, whether we should organize on a political basis, or whether we should organize at all. Many comrades came to question Leninist basics... as if Lenin himself covered up the rape!

We need to go where the struggle is. We need to build on the rebellious elements in workers' consciousness and try to win the best fighters to a Marxist perspective. The forefront of class struggle today is in social movements, where people are coming into motion over political issues. The people most open to Marxism will be found in these movements.

So, it must be affirmed that we need a revolutionary socialist vanguard party. Its necessity derives from features of class society and human consciousness that remain unchanged since such a party was conceived and tested by the Bolsheviks. These features include: the hegemony of the bourgeois ideology, the uneven development of consciousness within the proletariat, the centralized power of the capitalist state, and the treacherous role of reformism.

On vanguardism

While vanguardism is widely misunderstood and misapplied, there is a truth at its core that is undeniable: revolutionaries need a fighting formation to fight the ideas of the bourgeoisie, and eventually to fight the bourgeoisie and their lackeys, quite literally. It is true that the level of struggle and class organization is low, that there is no existing vanguard, and that Firebrand is far from a party at this stage. But that does not relieve us of our responsibility to relate to and organize with the most politically conscious sections of our class.

Class struggle can and should be advanced by organized socialist intervention. We must take a political lead. We must avoid lowering our politics to the lowest common denominator. Instead we must fight to raise the politics of others. We should not be ashamed to compete for influence in every fight we can get into. We don't know everything, but solid Marxist politics can illuminate every issue and turbocharge every fightback.

Wielding the Marxist toolset

We need a revolutionary organization dedicated to wielding the Marxist toolset for understanding and changing the world. It needs cadres trained in theory and action, and politically developed enough to carry Marxist methods and arguments into every fight. It must be large, radically democratic, and represent all sections and identities of our class. It needs permanent persuaders, activist-writers and activist-speakers, a big sexy profile, and a reputation as the best fighters. It needs vibrant publications that are subordinated to it, not the other way around.

Today there are thousands of Marxists and many more potential Marxists who don't know what to do. It is imperative for developed Marxists to get off the sidelines and into the fray—not just as movement activists, but as open Marxists actively working toward revolution. The current rise in interest in Marxism has been accompanied by a decline in Marxist organization. The crisis of Marxism in the U.S. today is a crisis of organization! However, we cannot just snap our fingers and create it.

Ultimately, we need a combat party fit for the task of seizing power. Such a party cannot be built in the absence of widespread radicalization and the organized intervention of Marxists. We have no control over the first condition and must dedicate ourselves to the second.

We need national organization, but we must organize locally in the meantime. Local groups can start as little more than study circles that go to protests together. These can form the basis to recruit and develop cadre through propaganda, political education, and social movement and labor activism.

As the first step toward national organization, we need to create a framework for local groups to provide mutual support, clarify our ideas, and coordinate action. We're currently trying to do this through Firebrand.

Political unity

What is the right level of political agreement for our current context? Some of the divisions between Marxists can be contained within a single organization, others are too fundamental.

An organization that is too narrowly defined will not attract enough members, nor foster the vibrancy necessary to develop self-confident, critically thinking cadre. Similarly, rather than fixating on crafting the perfect program for a particular movement, we should ask ourselves: What demands and approaches will get more people actively involved and provide a basis for further action? This is based on the idea that people learn best in struggle, not by being convinced of an abstract, overly detailed program.

On the other hand, a revolutionary organization that papers over the issues that have rightly divided Bolsheviks from social democrats, Stalinists, Maoists, and anarchists only entangles itself in interminable debates and precludes effective activity. We need a coherent politics and methodology.

Firebrand has developed and formed around points of unity we consider fit for this moment. First and foremost, we uphold the Marxist principle of class independence. That leads us to consider the Democratic Party a permanent and decisive impediment to class-consciousness and class-organization, not a path to it. We seek confrontation with the state, not capture of it. We orient on class struggle and rupture, not electoral gains and gradualism. We oppose all imperialisms and take the side of the international proletariat against “their own” ruling classes. We reject campism and the logic of “the enemy of my enemy is my friend.”

We take an abolitionist stance on the police, military, prisons, and borders. In the fight against oppression, we connect it to the fight against exploitation, while rejecting the twin pitfalls of class-reductionism and separatism. We fight for socialism from below and will settle for nothing less than the self-emancipation of the working class. And we advocate for a revolutionary party to accomplish it.

Strategy

In addition to political agreement, an effective revolutionary organization needs to agree on strategy. We need “more than a mere collection of individuals giving general adherence to a platform,” to quote Duncan Hallas, but “a centre for mutual training and debate, for raising the level of the raw activist to that of the experienced.”

We should seek every opportunity to demonstrate our politics in action, but until we build the capacity to lead major struggles, we must recruit primarily on the basis of our ideas. We're better off admitting that, as Mick Armstrong cautions in From Little Things Big Things Grow:

If we look at the history of the socialist movement, we can see that one of the key reasons why so many small revolutionary groups came to grief is that they overestimated their own capabilities and greatly exaggerated their ability to influence struggles or campaigns. All too often they attempted to leap over the stage of development dictated by the balance of forces between bosses and workers and the limitations imposed by their own small size. They were too impatient. ...Similarly, small groups of socialists who declare themselves to be “activist groups” or parties are deluding themselves. Because of their small size, they remain propaganda groups, whatever they think they are. But they are confused propaganda groups and therefore a lot less effective than they could be.

We need to go where the struggle is. We need to build on the rebellious elements in workers' consciousness and try to win the best fighters to a Marxist perspective. The forefront of class struggle today is in social movements, where people are coming into motion over political issues. The people most open to Marxism will be found in these movements. Eventually we need to be implanted in strategic industries, but it is heightened struggle, not a few dozen artificially implanted socialists, that changes consciousness and provides an opening for our ideas.

Our experiences

These perspectives were developed in concert with my closest comrades in the Denver Communists; Seattle, Boston, and Central Ohio Revolutionary Socialists; the Revolutionary Socialist Network, and Firebrand. They come from years of discussion and our collective experiences—especially since the ISO collapsed, when we have had to figure out how to proceed and what to keep and reject from our past.

After the collapse of the ISO, the Denver branch refounded almost immediately as the Denver Communists, on the same political basis we had been recruited to. We also adopted a “guilty until proven innocent” policy on accusations of sexual assault. A core group of six remained and we've since built a membership of 33.

We've been active in anti-racism, anti-fascism, and the fights for immigrant, abortion, and trans rights, but I'm proud to say the center of our work has been political education via weekly meetings on revolutionary socialist theory, history, strategy, and tactics. We've managed to develop some political clarity and avoid getting lost in the swamp of reformism, eclecticism, movementism, mutual-aidism, anti-organizationalism, and the romanticization of illegality. The siren song of the ballot box has fallen on deaf ears.

Nobody's around to tell us not to be so mean to social democrats anymore. We present ourselves as bold, brash, loud and proud Marxists, Leninists, and Trotskyists. Though coalition and campaign work can require a softer touch, we take unapologetically hard-left positions, without worrying too much about having mass appeal. We raise the red flag like the Bat-Signal and see who responds.

Our current challenge

In the movement of the present, we must also represent and take care of the future of that movement. We basically have to build a locomotive while it is already hurtling down the tracks. We need to build a national organization, while also building locally. We need to incubate locals across the country, reactivate our unorganized former org-mates, and figure out how to integrate contacts from cities without locals.

I think we're caught in a predicament between “build it and they will come” and providing an opportunity for comrades to “get in on the ground floor.” It's why we helped found a network and an organizing project and organized a conference and a coalition: to take a step forward toward revolutionary organization, while encouraging others to take the next step together with us.

This article is adapted from a talk given by Radek at the Revolutionary Socialism Conference in June of 2022.

Is Maoism Marxist?

By Kenneth G

Maoism is a political tradition with enduring appeal on the left, especially for its association with the Chinese revolution and other liberation movements. Thus it is important to understand the ways Maoism diverges from Marxism. Maoism's orientation on guerrilla warfare, its view of “labor aristocracy,” and its dismissal of the self-emancipation of the working class contradict revolutionary socialism and are doomed to failure.

It is often the case that newly radicalizing Marxists end up confused about our relationship to Maoism. Is it just “Marxism in China” or “socialism with Chinese characteristics”? Is it a newer form of Marxism which we can learn from and engage with? What Maoist ideas, if any, have merit? How do Marxists differ from Maoists, if at all? These are questions with definite answers, and they can be answered by looking at the history and theoretical tradition of both Marxism and Maoism.

Historical origins of Maoism

Maoism is a development of Stalinism. It originated as the theoretical summation of the strategies and tactics used by the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) in the course of its revolution. Since then, it has become an international tendency in its own right, whose political and theoretical traditions supersede the experience of the Chinese revolution.

In the early 1900s, China was still ruled by a corrupt feudal aristocracy, the Qing dynasty. China itself was carved up by various imperial powers, such as the British and Portuguese. Famines were common throughout China, and thanks to the backwardness of the Qing dynasty, technological and economic progress was halted. These are the circumstances that precipitated the coming revolutionary changes in China.

The CCP was originally small, but was quite influential among the working class in its early years. It was officially founded in July 1921 with help from the Soviet Union and the Communist or Third International (Comintern). At the time, the strategy of the Comintern was international socialist revolution. This changed after Lenin died in 1924 and Stalin rose to power, managing to consolidate power in both the Soviet Union and the Comintern by 1925. The Kuomintang (KMT), the rival Chinese Nationalist Party, had been working with the Comintern since the 1920s, but Stalin's rise to power led to a rightward shift in the policy of the Comintern towards support for “progressive” bourgeois nationalism abroad. Against this, Trotsky argued for class independence and international revolution. This rightward turn led to the Comintern arguing for a policy of alliance between the CCP and the KMT to defeat the Qing aristocracy. At the time, Wang Ming was the most well-respected member of the CCP and carried forth this perspective from Moscow.

Unfortunately, in April 1927, Chiang Kai-shek, leader of the KMT, ordered the KMT military to mass-murder members of the CCP. Due to this disastrous alliance, the CCP was driven out to the countryside and forced to adapt. Rather than organizing the working class, which was overwhelmingly concentrated in the cities, they would organize the peasants in the countryside into a guerrilla army. In this period, Mao demonstrated himself most up to the task of organizing a guerrilla army, and began to grow in power.

In 1931, Japan invaded China and ended up quickly scoring several military victories, capturing Beijing, Shanghai and Nanjing. Estimates vary, but Japanese colonialism likely cost between 20 and 50 million Chinese lives. The Japanese engaged in numerous war crimes, perhaps the most grotesque of which was the Rape of Nanjing, in which the Japanese slaughtered millions of Chinese in Nanjing over a period of six weeks.

Wang Ming, effectively representing the Soviet line in the CCP, argued for a temporary “united front” (really a popular front) between the CCP and the KMT against Japan. (In Marxism we refer to an alliance of working-class organizations as a “united front,” by contrast to collaboration with bourgeois forces, which we term a “popular front”). After the KMT suffered numerous embarrassing defeats against the Japanese, his political influence waned significantly, leaving his rival Mao the most influential member of the CCP.

During this period, the CCP was engaged in a three-way fight between the KMT and the Japanese. The Japanese were eventually driven out after their defeat in World War II in 1945. Afterward, in a context of hyperinflation, the KMT quickly discredited itself through its corruption and ineptitude. The CCP quickly defeated the KMT by 1949, leaving them in control of all of mainland China. The KMT was left to control only Taiwan (then called Formosa), with the backing of the United States.

The new regime that rose to power under Mao's command resulted in the expropriation of the former landowning gentry and giving land back to the peasants. This was essentially a bourgeois revolution. Mao called this government a “bloc of four classes” — the four classes in question being workers, peasants, small capitalists, and “progressive” large capitalists.

In reality, the CCP was thoroughly in control of all economic questions. Private capitalists were kept on an exceptionally short leash by the CCP, and neither workers nor peasants had any real control over the government. Officially, however, Mao called this a proletarian government and declared the socialist nature of the revolution.

Mao then attempted to apply Stalin's policies of rapid industrial development in China with the “Great Leap Forward.” This policy led to the redirection of peasant labor away from agricultural food production towards industrial production. Due to the low productivity of China's agriculture and low levels of industrial development, this policy resulted in widespread famines in the countryside with little to show for it. The failure of this policy led to Mao being sidelined in the CCP in 1961.

In 1966, Mao launched the Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution (GPCR) in an attempt to regain power. He argued that bourgeois elements had infiltrated the CCP and needed to be purged. What followed was a widespread ultra-left campaign characterized by chaos and violence. The GPCR resulted in the formation of “Red Guards” (primarily by youth and students) who massacred their fellow workers, destroyed many priceless historical artifacts, and persecuted almost everyone.

The GPCR was effectively politically exhausted by 1972, and formally ended with Mao's death in 1976. Following the GPCR's end, Deng Xiaoping rose to power and shifted China's economic policy towards reconciliation and trade with Western powers, a policy outlook which it has mostly maintained ever since.

The Chinese revolution and Mao's writings have inspired several other revolutionary organizations, including the Communist Party of India (Maoist) (also known as the Naxalites), the Black Panther Party, the Shining Path in Peru, and many others. While all of these organizations are worthy of study in their own right, for the sake of brevity I will focus on the Shining Path, since it was the most successful in applying Maoism's strategy of rural guerrilla warfare, and was directly influenced by Maoist ideology.

The Peruvian Communist Party (AKA The Shining Path)

The Shining Path (SP) was founded in 1969 by Abimael Guzmán (often referred to by his pen name, Presidente Gonzalo). It was an offshoot of the original Peruvian Communist Party (PCP), which was founded in 1928 by José Carlos Mariátegui. Guzmán was deeply influenced by Maoism after a trip to China and felt that the original PCP had become revisionist. He distanced himself from organizing workers and instead decided to focus on organizing the peasantry. By the time the SP had emerged, the original PCP had split into several parties, all claiming to continue Mariátegui's legacy.

For the first decade of its existence, the SP focused primarily on growing numbers and developing its members politically. It was only after the Peruvian government opened up elections in 1980 that the SP entered into the political scene. Prior to the elections, the Peruvian government had been under a military dictatorship. In contrast to other leftist groups, the SP denounced the elections and burned ballot boxes, declaring it an “act of war.”

The SP initially benefited from the government's tepid response. The SP rapidly took over several rural areas of Peru, owing to the political vacuum. During the initial period of the SP's ascendancy, the government relied on the police and on arming peasants to fight the SP.

The government's reticence was due primarily to the previous military dictatorship. Peru's president, Fernando Belaúnde Terry, had been overthrown in a military coup in his previous term, and was therefore quite wary of relying on the military to suppress the SP. The rest of the government shared this viewpoint, considering the historic fragility of liberal democracy in Peru.

The SP quickly distinguished itself for its ruthless use of violence to achieve its political goals. The SP regularly attacked and killed rival socialists and labor leaders who criticized the SP. It also tended to brutalize peasants who came into conflict with its rule, which took place frequently due to the SP's tendency to disrespect indigenous culture and its generally undemocratic political outlook.

The infamous Lucanamarca Massacre epitomizes this tendency. In response to the death of 13 militants at the hands of a few ronderos (peasants armed by the government), the SP took its revenge by entering the town of Lucanamarca and indiscriminately murdering anyone they could get their hands on. The official reports tally up 69 deaths, including 18 children and a six-month-old baby. In response to the outrage over this atrocity, Guzmán gave an interview in the pro-SP newspaper Diario defending the action as necessary in the face of “reactionary military actions,” though he did euphemistically admit to “excesses.” It is important to note that while this was the worst massacre committed by the SP, it was far from the only one.

By 1990, the SP presented an existential threat to the stability of the government. At this point, Alberto Fujimori was elected president. Where previous presidents had resisted the complete use of military force against the SP, Fujimori decided to take the gloves off. In 1992, he granted the military broad powers to arrest and prosecute anyone suspected of being an SP guerrilla, with secret trials and suspended democratic rights.

The results of this military repression were catastrophic. The military not only attacked SP militants, but also anyone suspected of supporting the SP. The military destroyed entire villages and murdered indiscriminately, resulting in an estimated 70,000 deaths throughout the conflict. This number far exceeds even the highest casualty estimates given for the SP.

After this declaration, the SP rapidly declined in power, and in September of 1992, Guzmán was captured by the Peruvian government. The result was the nearly immediate collapse of the SP, considering there was no real political successor anywhere in the party. Upon being captured, Guzmán began to call for peace talks at the behest of his jailors, which split the SP into multiple factions and led to a total rout.

Apart from the political vacuum, the SP also suffered a series of military defeats against ronderos. These were embarrassing not just because the ronderos were poorly armed peasants, but also because the SP claimed that the peasantry was their social base.

With the SP defeated, Fujimori easily won reelection, and in 1995, he and his supporters declared amnesty for the human rights violations undertaken by soldiers, police officers and ronderos against the SP. Guzmán took responsibility for the Lucanamarca massacre and like many other members of the SP, ended up serving a life sentence in prison. Fujimori would eventually end up with a life sentence as well, due to flagrant corruption and human rights violations during his presidency.

Maoism as a theoretical tradition

In this section, I am going to explore the points of disagreement that Maoism has in relation to Trotskyism. Since Maoism is influenced by Marxism, there is obviously substantial agreement on various topics between Maoists and Trotskyists, but historically these points of agreement have not been enough for Trotskyists and Maoists to coexist in the same organizations. Here are the reasons why.

Internationalism

Since Maoism is a development of Stalinism, it inherits the Stalinist conception of “socialism in one country.” Maoists argue that socialism can be built in a single country following a socialist revolution, whereas Trotskyists believe that only the dictatorship of the proletariat or a workers' state can be built in a single country. This is theoretically underlied by the view that world capitalism is composed of various “capitalisms” rather than a single, integrated world system. According to Joshua Moufawad-Paul, a Maoist:

Trotsky's theory of “combined and uneven development” was fundamental to his understanding of the theory of permanent revolution's international meaning. Here we have a theory that seems to imply that capitalism is a global mode of production that develops in a combined and uneven manner, rather than a theory (as those influenced by what would become the Maoist tradition have argued) of a world system of capitalism where capitalist modes of production form the centres of capitalism, and impose/control global capitalism through imperialism, and capitalist social formations on the periphery that are still economically defined, internally, as pre-capitalist modes of production.

Moufawad-Paul meant it as a criticism, but he was correct: Trotskyists view capitalism as a single globally integrated economic system. While various imperialist blocs may vie for power with each other, and the class structure and local conditions are different throughout the world, all capitalist nation-states are ultimately economically dependent on each other. For this reason, along with the obvious looming threat of imperialist intervention, revolution in a single country is not enough to safeguard a proletarian revolution.

Obviously, the international revolution has to begin somewhere, and the only real place for this to begin is at a national stage. However, the Trotskyist position is that the revolution must spread to other countries and escalate the fight against capitalism, otherwise it will eventually revert back to capitalism. This does not mean that a workers' revolution in one country should be held back if international revolution is impossible. It simply means that we must recognize that socialism has not yet been won.

On the revolutionary party

Maoists also inherit the Stalinist conception of the revolutionary party. Rather than being a party of the working class which convinces other workers to take power for themselves, it is thought of as a party above the working class, meant to impose “socialism” on the workers for their benefit. Moufawad-Paul is helpful here in understanding the Maoist perspective on this issue. He argues that the revolutionary party has an inherently petty-bourgeois nature. As he puts it in his 2016 book Continuity and Rupture:

The working-class caught up in trade unions cannot produce a revolutionary organization by itself because, in this context, it is only capable of producing an economism (“trade union consciousness”), or a defiant anarchism, but not a mediating party that produces a revolutionary movement with a coherent and revolutionary theory. Here we must recall Althusser's analysis of the philosophy of Marxism-Leninism where he points out that the working-class, which spends most of its time working, can only conceive of its rebellion according to the ruling ideas of the ruling class.

Essentially the argument here is that workers are incapable of coming to revolutionary consciousness on their own, and thus can only generally develop “trade-union” consciousness. Whereas those with a revolutionary consciousness seek to overthrow capitalism, those with trade-union consciousness seek to reform it and negotiate with its representatives — i.e. build unions, form labor parties, win elections, pass legislation, etc. Therefore, the petty bourgeoisie must step in to build a revolutionary party on behalf of the working class instead.

The reasoning for this position has taken many forms, but usually it boils down to a lack of faith in the intellectual capacities of workers. Regrettably, this was Lenin's position when he wrote the classic foundational text “What Is to Be Done?”:

We have said that there could not have been Social-Democratic consciousness among the workers. It would have to be brought to them from without. The history of all countries shows that the working class, exclusively by its own effort, is able to develop only trade-union consciousness, i.e., the conviction that it is necessary to combine in unions, fight the employers, and strive to compel the government to pass necessary labour legislation, etc.

Those who continue to make this argument today ignore the work of later Marxists such as Tony Cliff and Marcel Liebman who pointed out that Lenin abandoned this elitism after the 1905 revolution and the resultant upsurge in class consciousness. In fact, following the revolution Lenin argued the exact opposite formulation. As he put it in his 1905 essay “The Reorganization of the Party”:

It would be simply ridiculous to doubt that the workers who belong to our Party, or who will join it tomorrow at the invitation of the Central Committee, will be Social-Democrats in ninety-nine cases out of a hundred. The working class is instinctively, spontaneously Social-Democratic.

It is at this point that we come to the main contradiction in the Stalinist conception of the party, perhaps best expressed by Moufawad-Paul:

On the one hand it is impossible for the proletariat to spontaneously develop a revolutionary party with a revolutionary ideology; on the other hand it is impossible for a party that the workers cannot possibly develop, and thus is developed instead by the petty bourgeoisie, to carry a revolution to its completion.

To overcome the contradiction between the petty-bourgeois intellectuals of the party and the proletariat, Maoists introduce the strategy known as the mass line. The mass line is often summarized by Maoists as “to the masses, from the masses, to the masses.” It was developed by Mao during the CCP's period of guerrilla warfare against the KMT and the Japanese. It consists of collecting ideas and drawing inspiration from the masses, and then bringing forth a systematic program which they will provide feedback on. Thus the task of the party is to ask the masses how to proceed and then to systematize their thoughts into a coherent revolutionary program.

It is worth pausing for a second to consider the origins of the mass-line theory in more depth. During Mao's period of guerrilla warfare, he organized peasants, not workers. While peasants and workers are both laboring, exploited classes, they differ significantly in class interests. Peasants produce for themselves and their families first, and society second, whereas for workers, the reverse is true. Thus for workers, economic cooperation is second nature, whereas peasants must generally be forced to work extra to produce a social surplus. While peasants as a class benefit from a stored social surplus, since it guards against famines and scarcity in times of disaster, a peasant as an individual is less secure for contributing to that surplus. As Marx put it in his essay “The Eighteenth Brumaire of Napoleon Bonaparte”:

[The peasants] are therefore incapable of asserting their class interest in their own name, whether through a parliament or a convention. They cannot represent themselves, they must be represented. Their representative must at the same time appear as their master, as an authority over them, an unlimited governmental power which protects them from the other classes and sends them rain and sunshine from above.

The mass line can be seen as a strategy to resolve this contradiction, to both represent and protect the interests of the peasants while simultaneously being their master. Of course, just because a strategy was developed with peasants in mind does not necessarily mean it has no applications for organizing workers. But it does mean it deserves more critical examination than other strategies that have been tried and tested among workers already.

Another point in evaluating the mass-line strategy is how it fits into Maoist politics as a whole. The belief that underlies the strategy is that the masses already possess, in some germinal form, revolutionary consciousness. Hence why the party, which is inherently petty-bourgeois, must draw inspiration from them. But this contradicts the premise that the masses are incapable of achieving revolutionary consciousness! If they already possess a germ of revolutionary consciousness, why can't they just form their own party? If they don't have revolutionary consciousness, what is the point of the mass line?

This is just a specific manifestation of an important contradiction inherent to Maoist ideology. On the one hand, the masses (or in some formulations, the oppressed) know best and are the authority on revolutionary politics. On the other hand, they cannot be trusted to develop revolutionary consciousness without outside intervention either.

The Trotskyist view is that the majority of workers lack revolutionary consciousness outside of a revolutionary situation. While there generally always exists a layer of people disillusioned with capitalism and looking for change, revolutionaries are almost always in the minority.

In the context which we find ourselves in today in the US, the majority of workers are not revolutionaries. This means that truly revolutionary politics will alienate the majority of workers. If we are going to maintain revolutionary socialist politics as the basis of our organization, we have to accept the fact that we will be a political minority for the foreseeable future.

For us, the role of the revolutionary party is to persuade workers to take power for themselves. Persuading large numbers of workers to adopt a set of politics ultimately requires that those politics be correct. Unfortunately, the mass line is not a scientific method for determining what our politics should be. To really be correct, our political positions should flow from a scientific analysis of the structure of the society we seek to change, not necessarily from the opinion of the masses. From the Trotskyist perspective, the role of the party is to find out and speak the truth to the working class and the oppressed, even if they find the truth objectionable. This truth does not come from polling the masses, but from careful study of history and the experience of class struggle.

On revolutionary strategy

Apart from their flawed conception of the revolutionary party, Maoists also generally hold to a strategy of guerrilla warfare over mass working-class insurrection. Briefly, the idea of insurrection is this:

In non-revolutionary times, socialists engage in a mostly legal struggle under capitalism for reforms. The reward of winning reforms in this period is not the reforms themselves, but the cadres trained in class struggle who are formed within the struggle. These political struggles are not won primarily through contests of armed force, but through strikes and disruptive protests. The overarching goal in this period is to build a party which contains the most resolute and experienced Marxist cadres — i.e., the revolutionary socialist vanguard party.

As the contradictions mature or when circumstances permit, socialists organize among the rank and file of the military. Since the low-ranking recruits of the military are drawn from working-class backgrounds, the military as an institution is subject to internal class contradictions, and therefore to class struggle.

Once a revolutionary crisis emerges, supposing the socialists have done their jobs right, the military's rank and file turn on their superiors. Rather than crushing the revolution, they become part of it, and help the working class take power.

Maoists argue that this path to revolution only worked once in Russia and is unrealistic in every other situation. Rather than engaging in political organizing in the cities among the urban working class, they argue for People's War or guerrilla warfare. The idea of guerrilla warfare is to organize an army in the countryside and initially, engage in hit-and-run tactics against your enemy. During the initial phase, the goal is to wear down your opponent's resistance while avoiding long engagements or decisive battles. Over time as the guerrilla army gains in strength and the opponent's resistance is worn down, more conventional military tactics can be used.

According to this strategy, the road to victory lies in gaining control over the countryside surrounding the cities first, and from there gain control over the country entirely.

We believe that the strategy of guerrilla warfare is misguided on several counts. First, armies of any kind are not democratic institutions. A soldier must follow the orders of their superior with little room for debate, otherwise discipline breaks down. Thus the guerrilla strategy trains its adherents in obedience and following orders, rather than in democratic debate and accountability.

Second, using violence to achieve political objectives tends to discourage working-class participation. Political violence can only be used effectively if the majority of the working-class views its use as legitimate, which in non-revolutionary times, is a rare occurrence.

None of this is to suggest that we should not defend ourselves against state or fascist violence with arms. As Marxists we also critically support armed liberation movements. Violence is a tactical question to be answered when the time comes. But contrary to Mao, we do not believe that workers' power “flows from the barrel of a gun.”

Oppression and “labor aristocracy”

The final point of difference between us and Maoists is our view of oppression and the working classes of imperialist nations. Maoists generally have a pessimistic or downright hostile view of the working class in imperialist nations. The best summation of this view is perhaps J. Sakai's work Settlers: The Mythology of the White Proletariat, in which he argues that the white working class of the US benefits from the super-exploitation of people of color, and thus can never go beyond a reformist consciousness. According to Sakai, in the US, only people of color can rightfully be said to be proletarian. Maoists generally refer to the working class in imperialist countries as a “labor aristocracy.”

For Trotskyists, this analysis can be correct under certain circumstances, but not usually. In the US's settler-colonial period which lasted roughly up until the end of the 1800s, all classes of the US, including poor whites, benefited from the colonial theft of Native lands. Thus the main contradiction during this period was between the settlers and the Native peoples. However, with the completion of the process of colonial theft, the genocide of Natives, and their confinement to reservations, the circumstances have changed. The primary contradiction is now between the working class and the capitalist class.

Maoists argue that settler-colonial theft has been replaced by imperial wars abroad. However, imperialist adventures primarily benefit the owners of major corporations and their benefactors — in other words, the capitalist class. The working class in the imperialist country sacrifices their resources, their health, and ultimately their lives in imperialist wars. In return, soldiers receive a paltry wage and, in the US at least, the promise of free college. There is a reason why the military relies on poverty, desperation, and, when those don't work, the draft, to obtain recruits.

This view that workers in imperialist countries benefit from imperialism is something Maoists extend onto other forms of oppression. Maoists generally argue that white workers have an interest in upholding racism, for example. One could extend this to numerous other forms of oppression, including xenophobia, patriarchy, etc. But this overlooks the many historical efforts by class-conscious workers of all stripes to overcome oppression, and the ruling class' insistence on maintaining it.

Our view is that workers of all kinds benefit from fighting oppression, even if they are not immediately affected by it. The white working class does not, as a whole, benefit from the existence of racism, xenophobia, imperialism, etc. Of course, it is a structural advantage to be white rather than a person of color, to be a citizen rather than an immigrant, and to be in the US rather than to be in a peripheral nation. But the old labor slogan, “An injury to one is an injury to all,” applies to white workers as well, regardless of their opinions otherwise.

Conclusion

The Chinese revolution had many positive aspects to it. The CCP finally rid China of its longstanding class of feudal landlords. It beat out the KMT, which almost certainly would have left China as a vassal state to US imperialism. It was decisive in liberating China from the grips of Japanese imperialism. All of these things are towering historical accomplishments.

However, with the benefit of hindsight, we can see that Maoism has not led to socialism. Its attachment to guerrilla warfare as a strategy leaves its adherents without the ability to develop a democratic politics. It has a tendency to develop personality cults around its leaders, to disastrous effect. Perhaps most damningly, it has a tendency to organize classes other than the working class — leaving it without a basis to achieve socialism.

Instead of developing into socialism, China has developed from its former state-capitalist model into a more mixed economy, with elements of both state capitalism and private capitalism mixed in. The Chinese working class has about as much control over their government as any other working class does — which is to say, not much.

As for the Shining Path, their failure was in large part due to their own undemocratic practices. Once Guzmán was captured, there was no other political leadership left owing to Guzmán's cult of personality. Their regular and frequently unnecessary conflicts with peasants — their supposed social base — left them politically vulnerable to uprisings against their rule. And so the revolutionary situation in Peru was squandered and the Peruvian people ended up living under a neoliberal military dictatorship instead.

All of this explains why Trotskyists and Maoists have generally not organized together. None of this is to suggest that we should simply dismiss everything Maoists say out of hand, or that we can't work with Maoist organizations on issues which we agree on. Rather, we must view Maoist ideas with a critical eye, with the understanding that Maoists and Trotskyists have a fundamentally different political outlook. To paraphrase Carl Sagan, we must keep an open mind — but not so open that it falls out.

Opposing Ultra-leftism, The Marxist Method

By Steve Leigh

Marxism is essentially the full completion of class struggle.

Revolutionary organizations need to steer clear of reformism and opportunism. However, there is another danger, recruiting on the basis of ultra-leftism.

For Marx, socialism was the self-emancipation of the working class. John Molyneux called Marxism “the theory of international proletarian revolution.” These basic statements have implications that some Marxists have ignored or misunderstood.

Marxism is essentially the full completion of class struggle. Instead of just resisting or modifying exploitation, Marxism eliminates it. Instead of just fighting the ruling class, communism abolishes all social classes.

For Marx, communism was not just a doctrine, but the real movement of the working class. This led Marx to reject utopianism. It led him to call for communist involvement in the class struggle instead of criticizing it from the outside. He said of communists, “They do not set up any sectarian principles of their own. They have no interests separate and apart from those of the proletariat as a whole.”

The distinguishing thing about communists is that: “ In the national struggles of the proletarians of the different countries, they point out and bring to the front the common interests of the entire proletariat, independently of all nationality. 2. In the various stages of development which the struggle of the working class against the bourgeoisie has to pass through, they always and everywhere represent the interests of the movement as a whole.”

And

“The theoretical conclusions of the Communists are in no way based on ideas or principles that have been invented, or discovered, by this or that would-be universal reformer.

They merely express, in general terms, actual relations springing from an existing class struggle, from a historical movement going on under our very eyes.”

This approach by Marx was based on the idea that “capitalism first of all creates its own gravediggers, the working class”. In other words, the tendency of the class struggle is toward communism.

Reformism

As history later showed, Marx had underestimated the potential strength of reformism. The class struggle could be diverted from its revolutionary potential as Rosa Luxemburg laid out in Reform or Revolution.

Lenin drew organizational conclusions from the need to fight reformism. By 1912, he had come to the conclusion that an exclusively revolutionary organization was needed to overcome reformism. He developed the theory of the revolutionary socialist vanguard party: the most revolutionary workers must unite in order to convince the whole working class to take power. In fact, this same conclusion had been briefly reached by Marx in 1849. He expressed this in the “Address to the Communist League.”

Did Leninism Complete or Reject Marx's Approach to Class Struggle?

The Communist Manifesto was a document produced by the Communist League. Even as Marx urged communists to participate in class struggle, he understood the need for an organization of communists within the class struggle. He called for communists to win the movement to internationalism and the ultimate goal of communism. While the Manifesto rejected “sects”, it did support communist organization within the struggle. His rejection of separate principles by communists was a rejection of utopianism, not a rejection of political argument within the working-class movement.

He said:

“The Communists disdain to conceal their views and aims. They openly declare that their ends can be attained only by the forcible overthrow of all existing social conditions.”

As the communist movement developed it came to more clarity on the principles that were needed to complete the class struggle into communism. These for the most part were already explicit or implicit in Marx's writing: confrontation and militancy, opposition to racism, sexism etc., the use of the united front method, working class independence from capitalist politics and parties, internationalism, revolution etc.

Over time communists understood the need to more directly confront reformism in the working-class movement. Lenin's call for a revolutionary vanguard party grew from this understanding. Lenin's organizational ideas were in line with Marx's overall approach to the working-class movement. In What Is to Be Done, he called for “educating spontaneity”. Lenin made this clear in Left-wing Communism, An Infantile Disorder.

Implications for Today

While aiming to build a Leninist Vanguard Party, revolutionaries today should adhere to Marx's overall method. The revolutionary organization needs to be part of the working-class struggle. It wants to see that struggle succeed. It supports the aims and ends of that struggle. It is in the main a critical supporter of the working-class movement.

There is an important strategic reason to take this stance: Throughout working-class history, reactionaries and even liberals denounce communists as “outside agitators”. They claim that communists are not legitimate members of the movement. Communists have to fight for their right to be activists in the movement. To defend their participation, communists have to show that they support the aims of the movement. The way to win people to communist strategies, tactics and politics is for communists to be seen as fighting alongside other activists. The ultra-left attitude of primarily denouncing the movement rather than giving it critical support, leads to voluntary self-isolation. It undercuts the possibility of winning workers to communism. It does the work of reactionaries for them.

If the working class movement, the struggle against exploitation, is the force that will bring communism, communists must be part of that movement.

Reform Movements

This applies to movements for reforms that express the interests of the working-class: movements for equality and liberation, against imperialism, against authoritarianism etc. Revolutionaries need to go into these movements as militant but critical supporters, even if they oppose the politics of the leadership of those movements. Marxists want these movements to succeed. Marxists criticize these movements mainly over their strategies, tactics and leadership politics. This means that revolutionaries join these movements positively. Marxists want as many people involved as possible and try to build these movements even while critical of their leadership. Of course, as Marx said in the Manifesto, communists “disdain to hide their politics.” Critical support means openness about criticism. As British Marxist Tony Cliff put it “We are with and against the movements.”

Completion, not Fundamental Opposition to the Movement

Flowing from Marx's method in relation to movements, revolutionaries try to “radicalize movements from within, rather than pooh pooh them from without” (Engels). This means being fundamentally with the movement even with their criticism of it. It flows from Marx's idea that communism is the ultimate completion of the class struggle. Though it can be diverted by reformism, when the movement reaches its logical goals, it reaches communism.

Ultra-Leftism

The basic idea of ultra-leftism is that the working-class movement does not have a fundamental trajectory towards communism. Ultra-leftists think that the movement needs to be rejected and replaced by an authentic communist movement. Ultra-leftists opposed unions that were under reformist leadership. They wanted to form separate organizations outside of the dominant working-class organizations. They set up red unions only made up of communists instead of contesting for leadership within existing unions. Instead of fighting reformist bureaucrats for the allegiance of the workers, they let the reformists dominate the union's politics by withdrawing from the unions.

The Theory of the Offensive

One manifestation of ultra-leftism was the “theory of the offensive”. This was the idea that the working class had to be shocked into activity. In 1921, the Communist Party of Germany determined that a general strike was necessary. Instead of arguing for and winning the majority of workers to this idea, they declared the general strike and tried to force workers off work. This resulted in physical battles, mass arrests, and even death of workers on both sides. It was a major set-back. It in turn resulted in the failure to organize an insurrection in 1923 when the working class was ready for it. Ultra-leftism made the CP skittish about waging a battle when it was possible.

Applications Today

The Left in the U.S. is tiny. It needs to grow significantly before it can have much impact on class struggle. While revolutionary organizations need to grow, they must grow on a solid basis. They could open their doors to supporters of the Democratic Party and likely become much bigger. The DSA method seems superficially to work since it has become an organization of tens of thousands. However, it is not revolutionary. It has become an obstacle to class struggle as it supports the second major imperialist party.

Revolutionary organizations need to steer clear of reformism and opportunism. However, there is another danger, recruiting on the basis of ultra-leftism. This can also create a house of cards. Recruiting on this basis may lead to increases in membership. The problem is that this will prevent growth beyond a certain point. Ultra-leftism will deter serious revolutionaries from joining. If an organization does grow based on ultra-leftism, it will become an obstacle to struggle in the future.

The Two Souls of Socialism

By Hal Draper

Socialism's crisis today is a crisis in the meaning of socialism. For the first time in the history of the world, very likely a majority of its people label themselves "socialist" in one sense or another; but there has never been a time when the label was less informative. The nearest thing to a common content of the various "socialisms" is a negative: anti-capitalism. On the positive side, the range of conflicting and incompatible ideas that call themselves socialist is wider than the spread of ideas within the bourgeois world.

Even anti-capitalism holds less and less as a common factor. In one part of the spectrum, a number of social democratic parties have virtually eliminated any specifically socialist demands from their programs, promising to maintain private enterprise wherever possible. The most prominent example is the German social-democracy. ("As an idea, a philosophy, and a social movement, socialism in Germany is no longer represented by a political party," sums up D.A. Chalmers' recent book The Social Democratic Party of Germany.) These parties have defined socialism out of existence, but the tendency which they have formalized is that of the entire reformist social democracy. In what sense are these parties still "socialist"?

In another part of the world picture, there are the Communist states, whose claim to being "socialist" is based on a negative: the abolition of the capitalist private-profit system, and the fact that the class which rules does not consist of private owners of property. On the positive side, however, the socio-economic system which has replaced capitalism there would not be recognizable to Karl Marx. The state owns the means of production -- but who "owns" the state? Certainly not the mass of workers, who are exploited, unfree, and alienated from all levers of social and political control. A new class rules, the bureaucratic bosses; it rules over a collectivist system -- a bureaucratic collectivism. Unless statification is mechanically equated with "socialism," in what sense are these societies "socialist"?

These two self-styled socialisms are very different, but they have more in common than they think. The social democracy has typically dreamed of "socializing" capitalism from above. Its principle has always been that increased state intervention in society and economy is per se socialistic. It bears a fatal family resemblance to the Stalinist conception of imposing something called socialism from the top down, and of equating statification with socialism. Both have their roots in the ambiguous history of the socialist idea.

Back to the roots: the following pages propose to investigate the meaning of socialism historically, in a new way. There have always been different "kinds of socialism," and they have customarily been divided into reformist or revolutionary, peaceful or violent, democratic or authoritarian, etc. These divisions exist, but the underlying division is something else. Throughout the history of socialist movements and ideas, the fundamental divide is between Socialism-from-Above and Socialism-from-Below.

What unites the many different forms of Socialism-from-Above is the conception that socialism (or a reasonable facsimile thereof) must be handed down to the grateful masses in one form or another, by a ruling elite which is not subject to their control in fact. The heart of Socialism-from-Below is its view that socialism can be realized only through the self-emancipation of activized masses in motion, reaching out for freedom with their own hands, mobilized "from below" in a struggle to take charge of their own destiny, as actors (not merely subjects) on the stage of history. "The emancipation of the working classes must be conquered by the working classes themselves": this is the first sentence in the Rules written for the First International by Marx, and this is the First Principle of his lifework.

It is the conception of Socialism-from-Above which accounts for the acceptance of Communist dictatorship as a form of "socialism." It is the conception of Socialism-from-Above which concentrates social-democratic attention on the parliamentary superstructure of society and on the manipulation of the "commanding heights" of the economy, and which makes them hostile to mass action from below. It is Socialism-from-Above which is the dominant tradition in the development of socialism.

Please note that it is not peculiar to socialism. On the contrary, the yearning for emancipation-from-above is the all-pervading principle through centuries of class society and political oppression. It is the permanent promise held out by every ruling power to keep the people looking upward for protection, instead of to themselves for liberation from the need for protection. The people looked to kings to right the injustices done by lords, to messiahs to overthrow the tyranny of kings. Instead of the bold way of mass action from below, it is always safer and more prudent to find the "good" ruler who will Do the People Good. The pattern of emancipation-from-above goes all the way back in the history of civilization, and had to show up in socialism too. But it is only in the framework of the modern socialist movement that liberation from below could become even a realistic aspiration; within socialism it has come to the fore, but only by fits and starts. The history of socialism can be read as a continual but largely unsuccessful effort to free itself from the old tradition, the tradition of emancipation-from-above.

In the conviction that the current crisis of socialism is intelligible only in terms of this Great Divide in the socialist tradition, we turn to a few examples of the two souls of socialism.

Some Socialist “Ancestors”

Karl Kautsky, the leading theoretician of the Second International, began his book on Thomas More with the observation that the two great figures inaugurating the history of socialism are More and Münzer, and that both of them "follow the long line of Socialists, from Lycurgus and Pythagoras to Plato, the Gracchi, Cataline, Christ ..."

This is a very impressive list of early "socialists," and considering his position Kautsky should certainly have been able to recognize a socialist when he saw one. What is most fascinating about this list is the way it falls apart under examination into two quite different groups.

Plutarch's life of Lycurgus led the early socialists to adopt him as the founder of Spartan "communism" -- this is why Kautsky lists him. But as described by Plutarch, the Spartan system was based on equal division of land under private ownership; it was in no way socialistic. The "collectivist" feeling one may get from a description of the Spartan regime comes from a different direction: the way of life of the Spartan ruling class itself, which was organized as a permanent disciplined garrison in a state of siege; and to this add the terroristic regime imposed over the helots (slaves). I do not see how a modern socialist can read of the Lycurgan regime without feeling that he is meeting not an ancestor of socialism but a forerunner of fascism. There is quite a difference! But how is it that it did not impress itself on the leading theoretician of social-democracy?

Pythagoras founded an elite order which acted as the political arm of the landed aristocracy against the plebeian-democratic movement; he and his party were finally overthrown and expelled by a popular revolutionary rising. Kautsky seems to be on the wrong side of the barricades! But besides, inside the Pythagorean order a regime of total authoritarianism and regimentation prevailed. In spite of this, Kautsky chose to regard Pythagoras as a socialist ancestor because of the belief that the organized Pythagoreans practised communal consumption. Even if this were true (and Kautsky found out later it was not) this would have made the Pythagorean order exactly as communistic as any monastery. Chalk up a second ancestor of totalitarianism on Kautsky's list.

The case of Plato's Republic is well-enough known. The sole element of "communism" in his ideal state is the prescription of monastic-communal consumption for the small elite of "Guardians" who constitute the bureaucracy and army; but the surrounding social system is assumed to be private-property-holding, not socialistic. And -- here it is again -- Plato's state model is government by an aristocratic elite, and his argument stresses that democracy inevitably means the deterioration and ruin of society. Plato's political aim, in fact, was the rehabilitation and purification of the ruling aristocracy in order to fight the tide of democracy. To call him a socialist ancestor is to imply a conception of socialism which makes any kind of democratic control irrelevent.

On the other hand, Catiline and the Gracchi had no collectivist side. Their names are associated with mass movements of popular-democratic revolt against the Establishment. They were not socialists, to be sure, but they were on the popular side of the class struggle in the ancient world, the side of the people's movement from below. It seems it was all the same to the theoretician of social-democracy.

Here, in the pre-history of our subject, are two kinds of figures ready-made for adoption into the pantheon of the socialist movement. There were the figures with a tinge of (alleged) collectivism, who were yet thorough elitists, authoritarians and anti-democrats; and there were the figures without anything collectivist about them, who were associated with democratic class struggles. There is a collectivist tendency without democracy, and there is a democratic tendency without collectivism but nothing yet which merges these two currents.

Not until Thomas Münzer, the leader of the revolutionary left wing of the German Reformation, do we find a suggestion of such a merger; a social movement with communistic ideas (Münzer's) which was also engaged in a deep-going popular-democratic struggle from below. In contrast is precisely Sir Thomas More: the gulf between these two contemporaries goes to the heart of our subject. More's Utopia pictures a thoroughly regimented society, more reminiscent of 1984 than of socialist democracy, elitist through and through, even slaveholding, a typical Socialism-from-Above. It is not surprising that, of these two "socialist ancestors" who stand at the threshold of the modern world, one (More) execrated the other and supported the hangmen who did him and his movement to death.

What then is the meaning of socialism when it first came into the world? From the very beginning, it was divided between the two souls of socialism, and there was war between them.

The First Modern Socialists

Modern socialism was born in the course of the half century or so that lies between the Great French Revolution and the revolutions of 1848. So was modern democracy. But they were not born linked like Siamese twins. They traveled at first along separate lines. When did the two lines first intersect?

Out of the wreckage of the French Revolution rose different kinds of socialism. We will consider three of the most important in the light of our question.

Babeuf. -- The first modern socialist movement was that led in the last phase of the French Revolution by Babeuf ("the Conspiracy of the Equals"), conceived as a continuation of revolutionary Jacobinism plus a more consistent social goal: a society of communist equality. This represents the first time in the modern era that the idea of socialism is wedded to the idea of a popular movement -- a momentous combination.

This combination immdiately raises a critical question: What exactly in each case is the relationship that is seen between this socialist idea and that popular movement? this is the key question for socialism for the next 200 years.

As the Babouvists saw it: The mass movement of the people has failed; the people seem to have turned their backs on the Revolution. But still they suffer, still they need communism: we know that. The revolutionary will of the people has been defeated by a conspiracy of the right: what we need is a cabal of the left to re-create the people's movement, to effectuate the revolutionary will. We must therefore seize power. But the people are no longer ready to seize power. Therefore it is necesary for us to seize power in their name, in order to raise the people up to that point. This means a temporary dictatorship, admittedly by a minority; but it will be an Educational Dictatorship, aiming at creating the conditions which will make possible democratic control in the future. (In that sense we are democrats.) This will not be a dictatorship of the people, as was the Commune, let alone of the proletariat; it is frankly a dictatorship over the people -- with very good intentions.

For most of the next fifty years, the conception of the Educational Dictatorship over the people remains the program of the revolutionary left -- through the three B's (Babeuf to Buonarroti to Blanqui) and, with anarchist verbiage added, also Bakunin. The new order will be handed down to the suffering people by the revolutionary band. This typical Socialism-from-Above is the first and most primitive form of revolutionary socialism, but there are still today admirers of Castro and Mao who think it is the last word in revolutionism.

Saint-Simon. -- Emerging from the revolutionary period, a brilliant mind took an entirely different tack. Saint-Simon was impelled by a revulsion against revolution, disorder and disturbances. What fascinated him was the potentialities of industry and science.

His vision had nothing to do with anything resembling equality, justice, freedom, the rights of man or allied passions: it looked only to modernization, industrialization, planning, divorced from such considerations. Planned industrialization was the key to the new world, and obviously the people to achieve this were the oligarchies of financiers and businessmen, scientists, technologists, managers. When not appealing to these, he called on Napoleon or his successor Louis XVIII to implement schemes for a royal dictatorship. His schemes varied, but they were all completely authoritarian to the last planned ordinance. A systematic racist and a militant imperialist, he was the furious enemy of the very idea of equality and liberty, which he hated as offspring of the French Revolution.

It was only in the last phase of his life (1825) that, disappointed in the response of the natural elite to do their duty and impose the new modernizing oligarchy, he made a turn toward appealing to the workers down below. The "New Christianity" would be a popular movement, but its role would be simply to convince the powers-that-be to heed the advice of the Saint-Simonian planners. The workers should organize -- to petition their capitalists and managerial bosses to take over from the "idle classes."

What then was his relationship between the idea of the Planned Society and the popular movement? The people, the movement, could be useful as a battering-ram -- in someone's hands. Saint-Simon's last idea was a movement-from-below to effectuate a Socialism-from-Above. But power and control must remain where it has always been -- above.

The Utopians. -- A third type of socialism that arose in the post-revolutionary generation was that of the utopian socialists proper -- Robert Owen, Charles Fourier, Etienne Cabet, etc. They blueprinted an ideal communal colony, imagined fullblown from the cranium of the Leader, to be financed by the grace of the philanthropic rich under the wing of Benevolent Power.

Owen (in many ways the most sympathetic of the lot) was as categorical as any of them: "This great change ... must and will be accomplished by the rich and powerful. There are no other parties to do it ... it is a waste of time, talent and pecuniary means for the poor to contend in opposition to the rich and powerful ..." Naturally he was against "class hate," class struggle. Of the many who believe this, few have written so bluntly that the aim of this "socialism" is "to govern or treat all society as the most advanced physicians govern and treat their patients in the best arranged lunatic hospitals," with "forbearance and kindness" for the unfortunates who have "become so through the irrationality and injustice of the present most irrational system of society."

Cabet's society provided for elections, but there could be no free discussion; and a controlled press, systematic indoctrination, and completely regimented uniformity was insisted on as part of the prescription.

For these utopian socialists, what was the relationship between the socialist idea and the popular movement? The latter was the flock to be tended by the good shepherd. It must not be supposed that Socialism-from-Above necessarily implies cruelly despotic intentions.

This side of these Socialisms-from-Above is far from outlived. On the contrary, it is so modern that a modern writer like Martin Buber, in Paths in Utopia, can perform the remarkable feat of treating the old utopians as if they were great democrats and "libertarians"! This myth is quite widespread, and it points once again to the extraordinary insensitivity of socialist writers and historians to the deep-rooted record of Socialism-from-Above as the dominant component in the two souls of socialism.

Strictly speaking, this combination had been anticipated by Gerrard Winstanley and the "True Levelers," the left wing of the English Revolution; but it was forgotten and led to nothing, historically speaking.

What Marx Did

Utopianism was elitist and anti-democratic to the core because it was utopian -- that is, it looked to the prescription of a prefabricated model, the dreaming-up of a plan to be willed into existence. Above all, it was inherently hostile to the very idea of transforming society from below, by the upsetting intervention of freedom-seeking masses, even where it finally accepted recourse to the instrument of a mass movement for pressure upon the Tops. In the socialist movement as it developed before Marx, nowhere did the line of the Socialist Idea intersect the line of Democracy-from-Below.

This intersection, this synthesis, was the great contribution of Marx: in comparison, the whole content of his Capital is secondary. This is the heart of Marxism: "This is the Law; all the rest is commentary." The Communist Manifesto of 1848 marked the self-consciousness of the first movement (in Engels' words) "whose notion was from the very beginning that the emancipation of the working class must be the act of the working class itself."

The young Marx himself went through the more primitive stage just as the human embryo goes through the gill stage; or to put it differently, one of his first immunizations was achieved by catching the most pervasive disease of all, the illusion of the Savior-Despot. When he was 22, the old kaiser died, and to the hosannahs of the liberals Friedrich Wilhelm IV acceded to the throne amidst expectations of democratic reforms from above. Nothing of the sort happened. Marx never went back to this notion, which has bedeviled all of socialism with its hopes in Savior-Dictators or Savior-Presidents.

Marx entered politics as the crusading editor of a newspaper which was the organ of the extreme left of the liberal democracy of the industrialized Rhineland, and soon became the foremost editorial voice of complete political democracy in Germany. The first article he published was a polemic in favor of the unqualified freedom of the press from all censorship by the state. By the time the imperial government forced his dismissal, he was turning to find out more about the new socialist ideas coming from France. When this leading spokesman of liberal democracy became a socialist, he still regarded the task as the championing of democracy -- except that democracy now had a deeper meaning. Marx was the first socialist thinker and leader who came to socialism through the struggle for liberal democracy.

{In manuscript notes made in 1844, he rejected the extant "crude communism" which negates the personality of man, and looked to a communism which would be a "fully developed humanism." In 1845 he and his friend Engels worked out a line of argument against the elitism of a socialist current represented by one Bruno Bauer. In 1846 they were organizing the "German Democratic Communists" in Brussels exile, and Engels was writing: "In our time democracy and communism are one." "Only the proletarians are able to fraternize really, under the banner of communist democracy."}

In working out the viewpoint which first wedded the new communist idea to the new democratic aspirations, they came into conflict with the existing communist sects such as that of Weitling, who dreamed of a messianic dictatorship. Before they joined the group which became the Communist League (for which they were to write the Communist Manifesto), they stipulated that the organization be changed from an elite conspiracy of the old type into an open propaganda group, that "everything conducive to superstitious authoritarianism be struck out of the rules," that the leading committee be elected by the whole membership as against the tradition of "decisions from above." They won the league over to their new approach, and in a journal issued in 1847 only a few months before the Communist Manifesto, the group announced:

"We are not among those communists who are out to destroy personal liberty, who wish to turn the world into one huge barrack or into a gigantic workhouse. There certainly are some communists who, with an easy conscience, refuse to countenance personal liberty and would like to shuffle it out of the world because they consider that it is a hindrance to complete harmony. But we have no desire to exchange freedom for equality. We are convinced ... that in no social order will personal freedom be so assured as in a society based upon communal ownership... [Let us put] our hands to work in order to establish a democratic state wherein each party would be able by word or in writing to win a majority over to its ideas ..."

The Communist Manifesto which issued out of these discussions proclaimed that the first objective of the revolution was "to win the battle of democracy." When, two years later and after the decline of the 1848 revolutions, the Communist League split, it was in conflict once again with the "crude communism" of putschism, which thought to substitute determined bands of revolutionaries for the real mass movement of an enlightened working class. Marx told them:

"The minority ... makes mere will the motive force of the revolution, instead of actual relations. Whereas we say to the workers: 'You will have to go through fifteen or twenty or fifty years of civil wars and international wars, not only in order to change extant conditions, but also in order to change yourselves and to render yourselves fit for political dominion,' you, on the other hand, say to the workers: 'We must attain to power at once, or else we may just as well go to sleep.'"

"In order to change yourselves and to render yourselves fit for political dominion": this is Marx's program for the working-class movement, as against both those who say the workers can take power any Sunday, and those who say never. Thus Marxism came into being, in self-conscious struggle against the advocates of the Educational Dictatorship, the Savior-Dictators, the revolutionary elitists, the communist authoritarians, as well as the philanthropic do-gooders and bourgeois liberals. This was Marx's Marxism, not the caricatured monstrosity which is painted up with that label by both the Establishment's professoriat, who shudder at Marx's uncompromising spirit of revolutionary opposition to the capitalist status quo, and also by the Stalinists and neo-Stalinists, who must conceal the fact that Marx cut his eyeteeth by making war on their type.

"It was Marx who finally fettered the two ideas of Socialism and Democracy together" [2]_because he developed a theory which made the synthesis possible for the first time. The heart of the theory is this proposition: that there is a social majority which has the interest and motivation to change the system, and that the aim of socialism can be the education and mobilization of this mass-majority. This is the exploited class, the working class, from which comes the eventual motive-force of revolution. Hence a socialism-from-below is possible, on the basis of a theory which sees the revolutionary potentialities in the broad masses, even if they seem backward at a given time and place. Capital, after all, is nothing but the demonstration of the economic basis of this proposition.

It is only some such theory of working-class socialism which makes possible the fusion of revolutionary socialism and revolutionary democracy. We are not arguing at this point our conviction that this faith is justified, but only insisting on the alternative: all socialists or would-be reformers who repudiate it must go over to some Socialism-from-Above, whether of the reformist, utopian, bureaucratic, Stalinist, Maoist or Castroite variety. And they do.

Five years before the Communist Manifesto a freshly converted 23-year-old socialist had still written in the old elitist tradition: "We can recruit our ranks from those classes only which have enjoyed a pretty good education; that is, from the universities and from the commercial class ..." The young Engels learned better; but this obsolete wisdom is still with us as ever.

2 The quotation is from H.G. Wells' autobiography. Inventor of some of the grimmest Socialism-from-Above utopias in all literature, Wells is here denouncing Marx for this historic step.

The Myth of Anarchist “Libertarianism”

One of the most thoroughgoing authoritarians in the history of radicalism is none other than the "Father of Anarchism," Proudhon, whose name is periodically revived as a great "libertarian" model, because of his industrious repetition of the word liberty and his invocations to "revolution from below."

Some may be willing to pass over his Hitlerite form of anti-Semitism ("The Jew is the enemy of humankind. It is necessary to send this race back to Asia, or exterminate it ..."). Or his principled racism in general (he thought it was right for the South to keep American Negroes in slavery, since they were the lowest of inferior races). Or his glorification of war for its own sake (in the exact manner of Mussolini). Or his view that women had no rights ("I deny her every political right and every initiative. For woman liberty and well-being lie solely in marriage, in motherhood,in domestic duties ...") -- that is, the "Kinder-Kirche-Küche" of the Nazis.

But it is not possible to gloss over his violent opposition not only to trade-unionism and the right to strike (even supporting police strikebreaking), but to any and every idea of the right to vote, universal suffrage, popular sovereignty, and the very idea of constitutions. ("All this democracy disgusts me ... What would I not give to sail into this mob with my clenched fists!") His notes for his ideal society notably include suppression of all other groups, any public meeting by more than 20, any free press, and any elections; in the same notes he looks forward to "a general inquisition" and the condemnation of "several million people" to forced labor -- "once the Revolution is made."

Behind all this was a fierce contempt for the masses of people -- the necessary foundation of Socialism-from-Above, as its opposite was the groundwork of Marxism. The masses are corrupt and hopeless ("I worship humanity, but I spit on men!") They are "only savages ... whom it is our duty to civilize, and without making them our sovereign," he wrote to a friend whom he scornfully chided with: "You still believe in the people." Progress can come only from mastery by an elite who take care to give the people no sovereignty.

At one time or another he looked to some ruling despot as the one-man dictator who would bring the Revolution: Louis Bonaparte (he wrote a whole book in 1852 extolling the Emperor as the bearer of the Revolution); Prince Jerome Bonaparte; finally Czar Alexander II ("Do not forget that the despotism of the czar is necessary to civilization").

There was a candidate for the dictator's job closer to home, of course: himself. He elaborated a detailed scheme for a "mutualist" business, cooperative in form, which would spread to take over all business and then the state. In his notes Proudhon put himself down as the Manager in Chief, naturally not subject to the democratic control he so despised. He took care of details in advance: "Draw up a secret program, for all the managers: irrevocable elimination of royalty, democracy, proprietors, religion [and so on]." -- "The Managers are the natural representatives of the country. Ministers are only superior Managers or General Directors: as I will be one day ... When we are masters, Religion will be what we want it to be; ditto Education, philosophy, justice, administration and government."

The reader, who may be full of the usual illusions about anarchist "libertarianism," may ask: Was he then insincere about his great love for liberty?

Not at all: it is only necessary to understand what anarchist "liberty" means. Proudhoun wrote: "The principle of liberty is that of the Abbey of Theleme [in Rabelais]: do what you want!" and the principle meant: "any man who cannot do what he wants and anything he wants has the right to revolt, even alone, against the government, even if the government were everybody else. "the only man who can enjoy this liberty is a despot; this is the sense of the brilliant insight by Dostoyevsky's Shigalev: "Starting from unlimited freedom, I arrive at unlimited despotism."

The story is similar with the second "Father of Anarchism," Bakunin, whose schemes for dictatorship and suppression of democratic control are better known than Proudhon's.

The basic reason is the same: Anarchism is not concerned with the creation of democratic control from below, but only with the destruction of "authority" over the individual, including the authority of the most extremely democratic regulation of society that it is possible to imagine. This has been made clear by authoritative anarchist expositors time and again; for example, by George Woodcock: "even were democracy possible, the anarchist would still not support it ... Anarchists do not advocate political freedom. What they advocate is freedom from politics..." Anarchism is on principle fiercely anti-democratic, since an ideally democratic authority is still authority. But since, rejecting democracy, it has no other way of resolving the inevitable disagreements and differences among the inhabitants of Theleme, its unlimited freedom for each uncontrolled individual is indistinguishable from unlimited despotism by such an individual, both in theory and practice.

The great problem of our age is the achievement of democratic control from below over the vast powers of modern social authority. Anarchism, which is freest of all with verbiage about something-from-below, rejects this goal. It is the other side of the coin of bureaucratic despotism, with all its values turned inside-out, not the cure or the alternative.

Lassalle and State Socialism

That very model of a modern social-democracy, the German Social-Democratic Party, is often represented as having arisen on a Marxist basis. This is a myth, like so much else in extant histories of socialism. The impact of Marx was strong, including on some of the top leaders for a while, but the politics which permeated and finally pervaded the party came mainly from two other sources. One was Lassalle, who founded German socialism as an organized movement (1863); and the other was the British Fabians, who inspired Eduard Bernstein's "revisionism."

Ferdinand Lassalle is the prototype of the state-socialist -- which means, one who aims to get socialism handed down by the existing state. He was not the first prominent example (that was Louis Blanc), but for him the existing state was the Kaiser's state under Bismarck.

The state, Lassalle told the workers, is something "that will achieve for each one of us what none of us could achieve for himself." Marx taught the exact opposite: that the working class had to achieve its emancipation itself, and abolish the existing state in the course. E. Bernstein was quite right in saying that Lassalle "made a veritable cult" of the state. "The immemorial vestal fire of all civilization, the State, I defend with you against those modern barbarians [the liberal bourgeoisie]," Lassalle told a Prussian court. This is what made Marx and Lassalle "fundamentally opposed," points out Lassalle's biographer Footman, who lays bare his pro-Prussianism, pro-Prussian nationalism, pro-Prussian imperialism.

Lassalle organized this first German socialist movement as his personal dictatorship. Quite consciously he set about building it as a mass movement from below to achieve a Socialism-from-Above (remember Saint-Simon's battering-ram). The aim was to convince Bismarck to hand down concessions -- particularly universal suffrage, on which basis a parliamentary movement under Lassalle could become a mass ally of the Bismarckian state in a coalition against the liberal bourgeoisie. To this end Lassalle actually tried to negotiate with the Iron Chancellor. Sending him the dictatorial statutes of his organization as "the constitution of my kingdom which perhaps you will envy me," Lassalle went on:

"But this miniature will be enough to show how true it is that the working class feels an instinctive inclination towards a dictatorship, if it can first be rightly persuaded that the dictatorship will be exercised in its interests; and how much, despite all republican views -- or rather precisely because of them -- it would therefore be inclined, as I told you only recently, to look upon the Crown, in opposition to the egoism of bourgeois society, as the natural representative of the social dictatorship, if the Crown for its part could ever make up its mind to the -- certainly very improbable -- step of striking out a really revolutionary line and transforming itself from the monarchy of the privileged orders into a social and revolutionary people's monarchy."

Although this secret letter was not known at the time, Marx grasped the nature of Lassalleanism perfectly. He told Lassalle to his face that he was a "Bonapartist," and wrote presciently that "His attitude is that of the future workers' dictator." Lassalle's tendency he called "Royal Prussian Government socialism," denouncing his "alliance with absolutist and feudal opponents against the bourgeoisie."

"Instead of the revolutionary process of transformation of society," wrote Marx, Lassalle sees socialism arising "from the 'state aid' that the state gives to the producers' cooperative societies and which the state, not the worker, 'calls into being.'" Marx derides this. "But as far as the present cooperative societies are concerned, they are of value only insofar as they are the independent creations of the workers and not proteges either of the government or of the bourgeoisie." Here is a classic statement of the meaning of the word independent as the keystone of Socialism-from-Below versus state-socialism.

There is an instructive instance of what happens when an American-type academic anti-marxist runs into this aspect of Marx. Mayo's Democracy and Marxism (later revised as Introduction to Marxist Theory) handily proves that Marxism is anti-democratic mainly by the simple expedient of defining Marxism as "the Moscow orthodoxy." But at least he seems to have read Marx, and realized that nowhere, in acres of writing and a long life, did Marx evince concern about more power for the state but rather the reverse. Marx, it dawned on him, was not a "statist":

"The popular criticism leveled against Marxism is that it tends to degenerate into a form of 'statism.' At first sight [i.e., reading] the criticism appears wide of the mark, for the virtue of Marx's political theory ... is the entire absence from it of any glorification of the state."

This discovery offers a notable challenge to Marx-critics, who of course know in advance that Marxism must glorify the state. Mayo solves the difficulty in two statements: (1) "the statism is implicit in the requirements of total planning ..." (2) Look at Russia. But Marx made no fetish of "total planning." He has so often been denounced (by other Marx-critics) for failing to draw up a blueprint of socialism precisely because he reacted so violently against his predecessors' utopian "plannism" or planning-from-above. "Plannism" is precisely the conception of socialism that Marxism wished to destroy. Socialism must involve planning, but "total planning" does not equal socialism just as any fool can be a professor but not every professor need be a fool.

The Fabian Model

In Germany, behind the figure of Lassalle there shades off a series of "socialisms" moving in an interesting direction.

The so-called Academic Socialists ("Socialists of the chair," Kathedersozialisten -- a current of Establishment academics) looked to Bismarck more openly than Lasalle, but their conception of state-socialism was not in principle alien to his. Only, Lassalle embarked on the risky expedient of calling into being a mass movement from below for the purpose -- risky because once in motion it might get out of hand, as indeed it did more than once. Bismarck himself did not hesitate to represent his paternalistic economic policies as a kind of socialism, and books got written about "monarchical socialism," "Bismarckian state-socialism," etc. Following further to the right, one comes to the "socialism" of Friedrich List, a proto-Nazi, and to those circles where an anti-capitalist form of anti-Semitism (Dühring, A. Wagner, etc.) lays part of the basis for the movement that called itself socialism under Adolf Hitler.

The thread that unites this whole spectrum, through all the differences, is the conception of socialism as equivalent merely to state intervention in economic and social life. "Staat, greif zu!" Lassalle called. "State, take hold of things!" -- this is the socialism of the whole lot.

This is why Schumpeter is correct in observing that the British equivalent of German state-socialism is -- Fabianism, the socialism of Sidney Webb.

The Fabians (more accurately, the Webbians) are, in the history of the socialist idea, that modern socialist current which developed in more complete divorcement from Marxism, the one most alien to Marxism. It was almost chemically-pure social-democratic reformism unalloyed, particularly before the rise of the mass labor and socialist movement in Britain, which it did not want and did not help to build (despite a common myth to the contrary). It is therefore a very important test, unlike most other reformist currents which paid their tribute to Marxism by adopting some of its language and distorting its substance.

The Fabians, deliberately middle-class in composition and appeal, were not for building any mass movement at all, least of all a Fabian one. They thought of themselves as a small elite of brain-trusters who would permeate the existing institutions of society, influence the real leaders in all spheres Tory or Liberal, and guide social development toward its collectivist goal with the "inevitability of gradualness." Since their conception of socialism was purely in terms of state intervention (national or municipal), and their theory told them that capitalism itself was being collectivized apace every day and had to move in this direction, their function was simply to hasten the process. The Fabian Society was designed in 1884 to be pilot-fish to a shark: at first the shark was the Liberal Party; but when the permeation of Liberalism failed miserably, and labor finally organized its own class party despite the Fabians, the pilot-fish simply reattached itself.

There is perhaps no other socialist tendency which so systematically and even consciously worked out its theory as a Socialism-from-Above. The nature of this movement was early recognized, though it was later obscured by the merging of Fabianism into the body of Labor reformism. The leading Christian socialist inside the Fabian Society once attacked Webb as "a bureaucratic Collectivist" (perhaps the first use of that term.) Hilaire Belloc's once-famous book of 1912 on The Servile State was largely triggered by the Webb type whose "collectivist ideal" was basically bureaucratic. G.D.H. Cole reminisced: "The Webb's in those days, used to be fond of saying that everyone who was active in politics was either an 'A' or a 'B' -- an anarchist or a bureaucrat -- and that they were 'B's' ..."

These characterizations scarcely convey the full flavor of the Webbian collectivism that was Fabianism. It was through-and-through managerial, technocratic, elitist, authoritarian, "plannist." Webb was fond of the term wirepulling almost as a synonym for politics. A Fabian publication wrote that they wished to be "the Jesuits of Socialism." The gospel was Order and Efficiency. The people, who should be treated kindly, were fit to be run only by competent experts. Class struggle, revolution and popular turbulence were insanity. In Fabianism and the Empire imperialism was praised and embraced. If ever the socialist movement developed its own bureaucratic collectivism, this was it.

"It may be thought that Socialism is essentially a movement from below, a class movement," wrote a Fabian spokesman, Sidney Ball, to disabuse the reader of this idea; but now socialists "approach the problem from the scientific rather than the popular view; they are middle-class theorists," he boasted, going on to explain that there is "a distinct rupture between the Socialism of the street and the Socialism of the chair."

The sequel is also known, though often glossed over. While Fabianism as a special tendency petered out into the larger stream of Labor Party reformism by 1918, the leading Fabians themselves went in another direction. Both Sidney and Beatrice Webb as well as Bernard Shaw -- the top trio -- became principled supporters of Stalinist totalitarianism in the 1930s. Even earlier, Shaw, who thought socialism needed a Superman, had found more than one. In turn he embraced Mussolini and Hitler as benevolent despots to hand "socialism" down to the Yahoos, and he was disappointed only that they did not actually abolish capitalism. In 1931 Shaw disclosed, after a visit to Russia, that the Stalin regime was really Fabianism in practice. The Webbs followed to Moscow, and found God. In their Soviet Communism: a New Civilization, they proved (right out of Moscow's own documents and Stalin's own claims, industriously researched) that Russia is the greatest democracy in the world; Stalin is no dictator; equality reigns for all; the one-party dictatorship is needed; the Communist Party is a thoroughly democratic elite bringing civilization to the Slavs and Mongols (but not Englishmen); political democracy has failed in the West anyway, and there is no reason why political parties should survive in our age ...

They staunchly supported Stalin through the Moscow purge trials and the Hitler-Stalin Pact without a visible qualm, and died more uncritical pro-Stalinists than can now be found on the Politburo. As Shaw has explained, the Webbs had nothing but scorn for the Russian Revolution itself, but "the Webbs waited until the wreckage and ruin of the change was ended, its mistakes remedied, and the Communist State fairly launched." That is, they waited until the revolutionary masses had been straitjacketed, and the leaders of the revolution cashiered, the efficient tranquillity of dictatorship had settled on the scene, the counter-revolution firmly established; and then they came along to pronounce it the Ideal.

Was this really a gigantic misunderstanding, some incomprehensible blunder? Or were they not right in thinking that this indeed was the "socialism" that matched their ideology, give or take a little blood? The swing of Fabianism from middle-class permeation to Stalinism was the swing of a door that was hinged on Socialism-from-Above.

If we look back at the decades just before the turn of the century that launched Fabianism on the world, another figure looms, the antithesis of Webb: the leading personality of revolutionary socialism in that period, the poet and artist William Morris, who became a socialist and a Marxist in his late forties. Morris' writings on socialism breathe from every pore the spirit of Socialism-from-Below, just as every line of Webb's is the opposite. This is perhaps clearest in his sweeping attacks on Fabianism (for the right reasons); his dislike of the "Marxism" of the British edition of Lassalle, the dictatorial H.M. Hyndman; his denunciations of state-socialism; and his repugnance at the bureaucratic-collectivist utopia of Bellamy's Looking Backward. (The last moved him to remark: "If they brigaded me into a regiment of workers, I'd just lie on my back and kick.")

Morris' socialist writings are pervaded with his emphasis from every side on class struggle from below, in the present; and as for the socialist future, his News from Nowhere was written as the direct antithesis of Bellamy's book. He warned

"that individual men cannot shuffle off the business of life on to the shoulders of an abstraction called the State, but must deal with it in conscious association with each other ... Variety of life is as much an aim of true Communism as equality of condition, and ... nothing but an union of these two will bring about real freedom."

"Even some Socialists," he wrote, "are apt to confuse the cooperative machinery towards which modern life is tending with the essence of Socialism itself." This meant "the danger of the community falling into bureaucracy." Therefore he expressed fear of a "collectivist bureaucracy" lying ahead. Reacting violently against state-socialism and reformism, he fell backwards into anti-parliamentarism but he did not fall into the anarchist trap:

"... people will have to associate in administration, and sometimes there will be differences of opinion ... What is to be done? Which party is to give way? Our Anarchist friends say that it must not be carried by a majority; in that case, then, it must be carried by a minority. And why? Is there any divine right in a minority?"

This goes to the heart of anarchism far more deeply than the common opinion that the trouble with anarchism is that it is over-idealistic.

William Morris versus Sidney Webb: this is one way of summing up the story.

The “Revisionist” Facade

Eduard Bernstein, the theoretician of social-democratic "revisionism," took his impulsion from Fabianism, by which he was heavily influenced in his London exile. He did not invent the reformist policy in 1896: he merely became its theoretical spokesman. (The head of the party bureaucracy preferred less theory: "One doesn't say it, one does it," he told Bernstein, meaning that the politics of German social-democracy had been gutted of Marxism long before its theoreticians reflected the change.)

But Bernstein did not "revise" Marxism. His role was to uproot it while pretending to prune away withered limbs. The Fabians had not needed to bother with pretense, but in Germany it was not possible to destroy Marxism by a frontal attack. The reversion to Socialism-from-Above ("die alte Scheisse") had to be presented as a "modernization", a "revision".

Essentially, like the Fabians, "revisionism" found its socialism in the inevitable collectivization of capitalism itself; it saw the movement toward socialism as the sum of the collectivist tendencies immanent in capitalism itself; it looked to the "self-socialization" of capitalism from above, through the institutions of the existing state. The equation of Statification = Socialism is not the invention of Stalinism; it was systematized by the Fabian-Revisionist-State-socialist current of social-democratic reformism.

Most of the contemporary discoveries which announce that socialism is obsolete, because capitalism no longer really exists, can already be found in Bernstein. It was "absurd" to call Weimar Germany capitalist, he declared, because of the controls exercised over the capitalists; it follows from Bernsteinism that the Nazi state was even more anti-capitalist, as advertised ...

The transformation of socialism into a bureaucratic collectivism is already implicit in Bernstein's attack on workers' democracy. Denouncing the idea of workers' control of industry, he proceeds to redefine democracy. Is it "government by the people"? He rejects this, in favor of the negative definition "absence of class government." Thus the very notion of workers' democracy as a sine qua non of socialism is junked, as effectively as by the clever redefinitions of democracy current in the Communist academies. Even political freedom and representative institutions have been defined out: a theoretical result all the more impressive since Bernstein himself was not personally antidemocratic like Lassalle or Shaw. It is the theory of Socialism-from-Above which requires these formulations. Bernstein is the leading social-democratic theoretician not only of the equation statification = socialism, but also of the disjunction of socialism from workers' democracy.

It was fitting, therefore, that Bernstein should come to the conclusion that Marx's hostility to the state was "anarchistic," and that Lassalle was right in looking to the state for the initiation of socialism. "The administrative body of the visible future can be different from the present-day state only in degree," wrote Bernstein; the "withering away of the state" is nothing but utopianism even under socialism. He, on the contrary, was very practical; for example, as the Kaiser's non-withering state launched itself into the imperialist scramble for colonies, Bernstein promptly came out for colonialism and the White Man's Burden: "Only a conditional right of savages to the land occupied by them can be recognized; the higher civilization ultimately can claim a higher right."

Bernstein contrasted his own vision of the road to socialism with that of Marx: Marx's "is the picture of an army. It presses forward, through detours, over sticks and stones ... Finally it arrives at a great abyss. Beyond it there stands beckoning the desired goal -- the state of the future, which can be reached only through at sea, a red sea as some have said." In contrast, Bernstein's vision was not red but roseate: the class struggle softens into harmony as a beneficent state gently changes the bourgeoisie into good bureaucrats. It didn't happen that way -- when the Bernsteinized social-democracy first shot down the revolutionary left in 1919, and then, reinstating the unregenerate bourgeoisie and the military in power, helped to yield Germany into the hands of the fascists.

If Bernstein was the theoretician of the identification of bureaucratic collectivism with socialism, then it was his left-wing opponent in the German movement who became the leading spokesman in the Second International of a revolutionary-democratic Socialism-from-Below. This was Rosa Luxemburg, who so emphatically put her faith and hope in the spontaneous struggle of a free working class that the myth-makers invented for her a "theory of spontaneity" which she never held, a theory in which "spontaneity" is counterposed to "leadership."

In her own movement she fought hard against the "revolutionary" elitists who rediscovered the theory of the Educational Dictatorship over the workers (it is rediscovered in every generation as The Very Latest Thing), and had to write: "Without the conscious will and the consious action of the majority of the proletariat there can be no socialism ... [We] will never assume governmental authority except through the clear unambiguous will of the vast majority of the German working class ..." And her famous aphorism: "Mistakes committed by a genuinely revolutionary labor movement are much more fruitful and worthwhile historically than the infallibility of the very best Central Committee."

Rosa Luxemburg versus Eduard Bernstein: this is the German chapter of the story.

The 100% American Scene

At the Wellsprings of American "native socialism," the picture is the same, only more so. If we overlook the imported "German socialism" (Lassallean with Marxist trimmings) of the early Socialist Labor Party, then the leading figure here is, far and away, Edward Bellamy and his Looking Backward (1887). Just before him came the now forgotten Laurence Gronlund, whose Cooperative Commonwealth (1884) was extremely influential in its day, selling 100,000 copies.

Gronlund is so up-to-date that he does not say he rejects democracy -- he merely "redefines" it; as "Administration by the Competent," as against "government by majorities," together with a modest proposal to wipe out representative government as such as well as all parties. All the "people" want, he teaches, is "administration -- good administration." They should find "the right leaders," and then be "willing to thrust their whole collective power into their hands." Representative government will be replaced by the plebiscite. He is sure that his scheme will work, he explains, because it works so well for the hierarchy of the Catholic Church. Naturally he rejects the horrible idea of class struggle. The workers are incapable of self-emancipation, and he specifically denounces Marx's famous expression of this First Principle. The Yahoos will be emancipated by an elite of the "competent," drawn from the intelligentsia; and at one point he set out to organize a secret conspiratorial American Socialist Fraternity for students.

Bellamy's socialist utopia in Looking Backward is expressly modeled on the army as the ideal pattern of society -- regimented, hierarchically ruled by an elite, organized from the top down, with the cozy communion of the beehive as the great end. The story itself pictures the transition as coming through the concentration of society into one big business corporation, a single capitalist: the state. Universal suffrage is abolished; all organizations from below eliminated; decisions are made by administrative technocrats from above. As one of his followers defined this "American socialism": "Its social idea is a perfectly organized industrial system which, by reason of the close interlocking of its wheels, shall work at a minimum of friction with a maximum of wealth and leisure to all."

As in the case of the anarchists, Bellamy's fanciful solution to the basic problem of social organization -- how to resolve differences of ideas and interests among men -- is the assumption that the elite will be superhumanly wise and incapable of injustice (essentially the same as the Stalinist-totalitarian myth of the infallibility of the Party), the point of the assumption being that it makes unnecessary any concern about democratic control from below. The latter is unthinkable for Bellamy because the masses, the workers, are simply a dangerous monster, the barbarian horde. The Bellamyite movement -- which called itself "Nationalism" and originally set out to be both anti-socialist and anti-capitalist -- was systematically organized on a middle-class appeal, like the Fabians.

Here were the overwhelmingly popular educators of the "native" wing of American socialism, whose conceptions echoed through the non-Marxist and anti-Marxist sectors of the socialist movement well into the 20th century, with a resurgence of "Bellamy Clubs" even in the 1930s, when John Dewey eulogized Looking Backward as expounding the American ideal of democracy." Technocracy, which already reveals fascist features openly, was a lineal descendant of this tradition on one side. If one wants to see how thin the line can be between something called socialism and something like fascism, it is instructive to read the monstrous exposition of "socialism" written by the once famous inventor-scientist and Socialist Party luminary Charles P. Steinmetz. His America and the New Epoch (1916) sets down in deadly seriousness exactly the anti-utopia once satirized in a science-fiction novel, in which Congress has been replaced by direct senators from DuPont, General Motors and the other great corporations. Steinmetz, presenting the giant monopolistic corporations (like his own employer, General Electric) as the ultimate in industrial efficiency, proposes to disband the political government in favor of direct rule by the associated corporate monopolists.

Bellamyism started many on the road to socialism, but the road forked. By the turn of the century, American socialism developed the world's most vibrant antithesis to Socialism-from-Above in all its forms: Eugene Debs. In 1897 Debs was still at the point of asking none other than John D. Rockefeller to finance the establishment of a socialist utopian colony in a western state; but Debs, whose socialism was forged in the class struggle of a militant labor movement, soon found his true voice.

The heart of "Debsian socialism" was its appeal to, and faith in, the self-activity of the masses from below. Debs' writings and speeches are impregnated with this theme. He often quoted or paraphrased Marx's "First Principle" in his own words: "The great discovery the modern slaves have made is that they themselves their freedom must achieve. This is the secret of their solidarity; the heart of their hope..." His classic statement is this: "Too long have the workers of the world waited for some Moses to lead them out of bondage. He has not come; he never will come. I would not lead you out if I could; for if you could be led out, you could be led back again. I would have you make up your minds that there is nothing you cannot do for yourselves." He echoed Marx's words of 1850:

"In the struggle of the working class to free itself from wage slavery it cannot be repeated too often that everything depends on the working class itself. The simple question is, Can the workers fit themselves, by education, organization, cooperation and self-imposed discipline, to take control of the productive forces and manage industry in the interest of the people and for the benefit of society? That is all there is to it."

Can the workers fit themselves? ... He was under no starry-eyed illusions about the working class as it was (or is). But he proposed a different goal than the elitists whose sole wisdom consists in pointing a finger at the backwardness of the people now, and in teaching that this must always be so. As against the faith in elite rule from above, Debs counterpoised the directly contrary notion of the revolutionary vanguard (also a minority) whose faith impels them to advocate a harder road for the majority:

"It is the minorities who have made the history of this world [he said in the 1917 anti-war speech for which Wilson's government jailed him]. It is the few who have had the courage to take their places at the front; who have been true enough to themselves to speak the truth that was in them; who have dared oppose the established order of things; who have espoused the cause of the suffering, struggling poor; who have upheld without regard to personal consequences the cause of freedom and righteousness."

This "Debsian socialism" evoked a tremendous response from the heart of the people, but Debs had no successor as a tribune of revolutionary-democratic socialism. After the postwar period of radicalization, the Socialist Party became pinkly respectable on the one hand, and the Communist Party became Stalinized on the other. On its side, American liberalism itself had long been undergoing a process of "statification," culminating in the great New Deal illusion of the '30s. The elite vision of a dispensation-from-above under the aegis of the Savior-President attracted a whole strain of liberals to whom the country gentleman in the White House was as Bismarck to Lassalle.

The type had been heralded by Lincoln Steffens, the collectivist liberal who (like Shaw and Georges Sorel) was as attracted to Mussolini as to Moscow, and for the same reasons. Upton Sinclair, quitting the Socialist Party as too "sectarian," launched his "broad" movement to "End Poverty in California," with a manifesto appropriately called I, Governor of California, and How I Ended Poverty (probably the only radical manifesto with two I's in the title) on the theme of "Socialism-from-Up-in-Sacramento. One of the typical figures of the time was Stuart Chase, who wove a zigzag course from the reformism of the League for Industrial Democracy to the semi-fascism of Technocracy. There were the Stalinoid intellectuals who managed to sublimate their joint admiration for Roosevelt and Russia by hailing both the NRA and the Moscow Trials. There were signs of the times like Paul Blanshard, who defected from the Socialist Party to Roosevelt on the ground that the New Deal program of "managed capitalism" had taken the initiative in economic change away from the socialists.

The New Deal, often rightly called America's "social-democratic period," was also the liberals' and social-democrats' big fling at Socialism-from-Above, the utopia of Roosevelt's "people's monarchy." The illusion of the Rooseveltian "revolution from above" united creeping-socialism, bureaucratic liberalism, Stalinoid elitism, and illusions about both Russian collectivism and collectivized capitalism, in one package.

Six Strains of Socialism-From-Above

We have seen that there are several different strains or currents running through Socialism-From-Above. They are usually intertwined, but let us separate out some of the more important aspects for a closer look.

Philanthropism. -- Socialism (or "freedom," or what-have-you) is to be handed down, in order to Do the People Good, by the rich and powerful out of the kindness of their hearts. As the Communist Manifesto put it, with the early utopians like Robert Owen in mind, "Only from the point of view of being the most suffering class does the proletariat exist for them." In gratitude, the downtrodden poor must above all avoid getting rambunctious, and no nonsense about class struggle or self- emancipation. This aspect may be considered a special case of --

Elitism. -- We have mentioned several cases of this conviction that socialism is the business of a new ruling minority, non-capitalist in nature and therefore guaranteed pure, imposing its own domination either temporarily (for a mere historical era) or even permanently. In either case, this new ruling class is likely to see its goal as an Educational Dictatorship over the masses -- to Do Them Good, of course -- the dictatorship being exercised by an elite party which suppresses all control from below, or by benevolent despots or Savior-Leaders of some kind, or by Shaw's "Supermen," by eugenic manipulators, by Proudhon's "anarchist" managers or Saint-Simon's technocrats or their more modern equivalents -- with up-to-date terms and new verbal screens which can be hailed as fresh social theory as against "nineteenth-century Marxism."

On the other hand, the revolutionary-democratic advocates of Socialism-from-Below have also always been a minority, but the chasm between the elitist approach and the vanguard approach is crucial, as we have seen in the case of Debs. For him as for Marx and Luxemburg, the function of the revolutionary vanguard is to impel the mass-majority to fit themselves to take power in their own name, through their own struggles. The point is not to deny the critical importance of minorities, but to establish a different relationship between the advanced minority and the more backward mass.

Plannism. -- The key words are Efficiency, Order, Planning, System -- and Regimentation. Socialism is reduced to social-engineering, by a Power above society. Here again, the point is not to deny that effective socialism requires over-all planning (and also that efficiency and order are good things); but the reduction of socialism to planned production is an entirely different matter; just as effective democracy requires the right to vote, but the reduction of democracy merely to the right to vote once in a while makes it a fraud.

As a matter of fact, it would be important to demonstrate that the separation of planning from democratic control-from-below makes a mockery of planning itself; for the immensely complicated industrial societies of today cannot be effectively planned by an all-powerful central committee's ukases, which inhibit and terrorize the free play of initiative and correction from below. This is indeed the basic contradiction of the new type of exploiting social system represented by Soviet bureaucratic collectivism. But we cannot pursue this subject further here.

The substitution of Plannism for socialism has a long history, quite apart from its embodiment in the Soviet myth that Statification = Socialism, a tenet which we have already seen to have been first systematized by social-democratic reformism (Bernstein and the Fabians particularly). During the 1930's, the mystique of the "Plan," taken over in part from Soviet propaganda, became prominent in the right wing of the social-democracy, with Henri de Man hailed as its prophet and as successor to Marx. De Man faded from view and is now forgotten because he had the bad judgment to push his Revisionist theories first into corporatism and then into collaboration with the Nazis.

Aside from theoretical construction, Plannism appears in the socialist movement most frequently embodied in a certain psychological type of radical. To give credit due, one of the first sketches of this type came in Belloc's The Servile State, with the Fabians in mind. This type, writes Belloc,

"loves the collectivist ideal in itself ... because it is an ordered and regular form of society. He loves to consider the ideal of a State in which land and capital shall be held by public officials who shall order other men about and so preserve them from the consequences of their vice, ignorance and folly. [Belloc writes further:] In him the exploitation of man excites no indignation. Indeed, he is not a type to which indignation or any other lively passion is familiar ... [Belloc's eye is on Sidney Webb here.] ... the prospect of a vast bureaucracy wherein the whole of life shall be scheduled and appointed to certain simple schemes ... gives his small stomach a final satisfaction."

As far as concerns contemporary examples with a pro-Stalinist coloration, examples-a-go-go can be found in the pages of Paul Sweezy's magazine Monthly Review.

In a 1930 article on the "motive patterns of socialism," written when he still thought he was a Leninist, Max Eastman distinguished this type as centered on "efficiency and intelligent organization ... a veritable passion for a plan ... businesslike organization." For such, he commented, Stalin's Russia has a fascination:

"It is a region at least to be apologized for in other lands -- certainly not denounced from the standpoint of a mad dream like emancipation of the workers and therewith all mankind. In those who built the Marxian movement and those who organized its victory in Russia, that mad dream was the central motive. They were, as some are now prone to forget, extreme rebels against oppression. Lenin will perhaps stand out, when the commotion about his ideas subsides, as the greatest rebel in history. His major passion was to set men free ... if a single concept must be chosen to summarize the goal of the class struggle as defined in Marxian writings, and especially the writings of Lenin, human freedom is the name for it ..."

It might be added that more than once Lenin decried the push for total-planning as a "bureaucratic utopia."

There is a subdivision under Plannism which deserves a name too: let us call it Productionism. Of course, everyone is "for" production just as everyone is for Virtue and the Good Life; but for this type, production is the decisive test and end of a society. Russian bureaucratic collectivism is "progressive" because of the statistics of pig-iron production (the same type usually ignores the impressive statistics of increased production under Nazi or Japanese capitalism). It is all right to smash or prevent free trade-unions under Nasser, Castro, Sukarno or Nkrumah because something known as "economic development" is paramount over human rights. This hardboiled viewpoint was, of course, not invented by these "radicals," but by the callous exploiters of labor in the capitalist Industrial Revolution; and the socialist movement came into existence fighting tooth-and-nail against these theoreticians of "progressive" exploitation. On this score too, apologists for modern "leftist" authoritarian regimes tend to consider this hoary doctrine as the newest revelation of sociology.

"Communionism." -- In his 1930 article Max Eastman called this "the united-brotherhood pattern," of "the gregarian or human-solidarity socialists" -- "those yearning with a mixture of religious mysticism and animal gregariousness for human solidarity." It should not be confused with the notion of solidarity in strikes, etc., and not necessarily identified with what is commonly called comradeship in the socialist movement or a "sense of community" elsewhere. Its specific content, as Eastman says, is a "seeking for submersion in a Totality, seeking to lose himself in the bosom of a substitute for God."

Eastman is here pointing to the Communist Party writer Mike Gold; another excellent case is Harry F. Ward, the CP's hardy clerical fellow-traveler, whose books theorize this kind of "oceanic" yearning for the shucking-off of one's individuality. Bellamy's notebooks reveal him as a classic case: he writes about the longing "for absorption into the grand omnipotency of the universe;" his "Religion of Solidarity" reflects his mistrust of the individualism of the personality, his craving to dissolve the Self into communion with Something Greater.

This strain is very prominent in some of the most authoritarian of the Socialisms-from-Above and is not seldom met in milder cases like the philanthropic elitists with Christian Socialist views. Naturally, this kind of "communionist" socialism is always hailed as an "ethical socialism" and praised for holding class struggle in horror; for there must be no conflict inside a beehive. It tends to flatly counterpose "collectivism" to "individualism" (a false opposition from a humanist standpoint), but what it really impugns is individuality.

Permeationism. -- Socialism-from-Above appears in many varieties for the simple reason that there are always many alternatives to the self-mobilization of masses from below; but the cases discussed tend to divide into two families.

One has the perspective of overthrowing the present, capitalist hierarchical society in order to replace it with a new, non-capitalist type of hierarchical society based on a new kind of elite ruling class. (These varieties are usually ticketed "revolutionary" in histories of socialism.) The other has the perspective of permeating the centers of power in the existing society in order to metamorphose it -- gradually, inevitably -- into a statified collectivism, perhaps molecule by molecule the way wood petrifies into agate. This is the characteristic stigmatum of the reformist, social-democratic varieties of Socialism-from-Above.

The very term permeationism was invented for self-description by what we have already called the "purest" variety of reformism ever seen, Sidney Webb's Fabianism. All social-democratic permeationism is based on a theory of mechanical inevitability: the inevitable self-collectivization of capitalism from above, which is equated with socialism. Pressure from below (where considered permissible) can hasten and straighten the process, provided it is kept under control to avoid frightening the self-collectivizers. Hence the social-democratic permeationists are not only willing but anxious to "join the Establishment" rather than to fight it, in whatever capacity they are allowed to join it, whether as cabin boys or cabinet ministers. Typically the function of their movement-from-below is primarily to blackmail the ruling powers into buying them off with such opportunities for permeation.

The tendency toward the collectivization of capitalism is indeed a reality: as we have seen, it means the bureaucratic collectivization of capitalism. As this process has advanced, the contemporary social-democracy has itself gone through a metamorphosis. Today, the leading theoretician of this neo-reformism, C.A.R. Crosland, denounces as "extremist" the mild statement favoring nationalization which was originally written for the British Labor program by none other than Sidney Webb (with Arthur Henderson)! The number of continental social democracies that have now purged their programs of all specifically anti-capitalist content -- a brand new phenomenon in socialist history -- reflects the degree to which the ongoing process of bureaucratic collectivization is accepted as an installment of petrified "socialism."

This is permeationism as grand strategy. It leads, of course, to permeationism as political tactic, a subject we cannot here pursue beyond mentioning its presently most prominent U.S. form: the policy of supporting the Democratic Party and the lib-lab coalition around the "Johnson Consensus," its predecessors and successors.

The distinction between these two "families" of Socialism-from-Above holds for home-grown socialism, from Babeuf to Harold Wilson; that is, cases where the social base of the given socialist current is inside the national system, be it the labor aristocracy or declassé elements or any other. The case is somewhat different for those "socialisms-from-outside" represented by the contemporary Communist Parties, whose strategy and tactics depend in the last analysis on a power base outside any of the domestic social strata; that is, on the bureaucratic collectivist ruling classes in the East.

The Communist Parties have shown themselves uniquely different from any kind of home-grown movement in their capacity to alternate or combine both the "revolutionary"-oppositionist and the permeationist tactics to suit their convenience. Thus the American Communist Party could swing from its ultra-left-adventurist "Third Period" of 1928-34 into the ultra-permeationist tactic of the Popular Front period, then back into fire-breathing "revolutionism" during the Hitler-Stalin Pact period, and again, during the ups-and-downs of the Cold War, into various degrees of combination of the two. With the current Communist split along Moscow-Peking line, the "Krushchevites" and the Maoists tend each to embody one of the two tactics which formerly alternated.

Frequently, therefore, in domestic policy the official Communist Party and the social-democrats tend to converge on the policy of permeationism, though from the angle of a different Socialism-from-Above.

Socialism-from-Outside. -- The preceding varieties of Socialism-from-Above look to power at the tops of society: now we come to the expectation of succor from the outside.

The flying-saucer cult is a pathological form, messianism a more traditional form, when "outside" means out of this world; but for the present purposes, "outside" means outside the social struggle at home. For the Communists of East Europe after World War II, the New Order had to be imported on Russian bayonets; for the German Social-Democrats in exile, liberation of their own people could finally be imagined only by grace of foreign military victory.

The peacetime variety is socialism-by-model-example. This, of course, was the method of the old utopians, who built their model colonies in the American backwoods in order to demonstrate the superiority of their system and convert the unbelievers. Today, it is this substitute for social struggle at home which is increasingly the essential hope of the Communist movement in the West.

The model-example is provided by Russia (or China, for the Maoists); and while it is difficult to make the lot of the Russian proletarians half-attractive to Western workers even with a generous dose of lies, there is more success to be expected from two other approaches:

The relatively privileged position of managerial, bureaucratic and intellectual-flunky elements in the Russian collectivist system can be pointedly contrasted with the situation in the West, where these same elements are subordinated to the owners of capital and manipulators of wealth. At this point the appeal of the Soviet system of statified economy coincides with the historic appeal of middle-class socialisms, to disgruntled class-elements of intellectuals, technologists, scientists and scientific employees, administrative bureaucrats and organization men of various types, who can most easily identify themselves with a new ruling class based on state power rather than on money power and ownership, and therefore visualize themselves as the new men of power in a non-capitalist but elitist setup.

While the official Communist Parties are required to maintain the facade of orthodoxy in something called "Marxism-Leninism," it is more common that serious theoreticians of neo-Stalinism who are not tied to the party do free themselves from the pretense. One development is the open abandonment of any perspective of victory through social struggle inside the capitalist countries. The "world revolution" is equated simply with the demonstration by the Communist states that their system is superior. This has now been put into thesis-form by the two leading theoreticians of neo-Stalinism, Paul Sweezy and Isaac Deutscher.

Baran and Sweezy's Monopoly Capitalism (1966) flatly rejects "the answer of traditional Marxist orthodoxy -- that the industrial proletariat must eventually rise in revolution against its capitalist oppressors." Same for all the other "outsider" groups of society -- unemployed, farm workers, ghetto masses, etc.; they cannot constitute a coherent force in society." This leaves no one; capitalism cannot be effectively challenged from within. What then? Some day, the authors explain on their last page, "perhaps not in the present century," the people will be disillusioned with capitalism "as the world revolution spreads and as the socialist countries show by their example that it is possible" to build a rational society. That is all. Thus the Marxist phrases filling the other 366 pages of this essay become simply an incantation like the reading of the Sermon on the Mount at St. Patrick's Cathedral.

The same perspective is presented less bluntly by a more circumlocuitous writer in Deutscher's The Great Contest. Deutscher transmits the new Soviet theory "that Western capitalism will succumb not so much -- or not directly -- because of its own crises and contradictions as because of its inability to match the achievements of socialism [i.e. the Communist states]"; and later on: "It may be said that this has to some extent replaced the Marxist prospect of a permanent social revolution." Here we have a theoretical rationale for what has long been the function of the Communist movement in the West: to act as border guard and shill for the competing, rival establishment in the East. Above all, the perspective of Socialism-from-Below becomes as alien to these professors of bureaucratic collectivism as to the apologists for capitalism in the American academies.

This type of neo-Stalinist ideologist is often critical of the actual Soviet regime -- a good example is Deutscher, who remains as far as possible from being an uncritical apologist for Moscow like the official Communists. They must be understood as being permeationists with respect to bureaucratic-collectivism. What appears as a "socialism-from-outside" when seen from the capitalist world, becomes a sort of Fabianism when viewed from within the framework of the Communist system. Within this context, change-from-above-only is as firm a principle for these theoreticians as it was for Sidney Webb. This was demonstrated inter alia by Deutscher's hostile reaction to the East German revolt of 1953 and to the Hungarian revolution of 1956, on the classical ground that such upheavals from below would scare the Soviet establishment away from its course of "liberalization" by the Inevitability of Gradualness.

Which Side Are You On?

From the point of view of intellectuals who have a choice of roles to play in the social struggle, the perspective of Socialism-from-Below has historically had little appeal. Even within the framework of the socialist movement it has had few consistent exponents and not many inconsistent ones. Outside the socialist movement, naturally, the standard line is that such ideas are visionary, impractical, unrealistic, "utopian"; idealistic perhaps but quixotic. The mass of people are congenitally stupid, corrupt, apathetic and generally hopeless; and progressive change must come from Superior People rather like (as it happens) the intellectual expressing these sentiments. This is translated theoretically into an Iron Law of Oligarchy or a tinny law of elitism, in one way or another involving a crude theory of inevitability -- the inevitability of change-from-above-only.

Without presuming to review in a few words the arguments pro and con for this pervasive view, we can note the social role it plays, as the self-justificatory rite of the elitist. In "normal" times when the masses are not moving, the theory simply requires pointing with scorn, while the whole history of revolution and social upheaval is simply dismissed as obsolete. But the recurrence of revolutionary upheavals and social disturbances, defined precisely by the intrusion onto the historical stage of previous inactive masses and characteristic of periods when basic social change is on the agenda, is just as "normal" in history as the intervening periods of conservatism. When the elitist theorist therefore has to abandon the posture of the scientific observer who is merely predicting that the mass of people will always continue quiescent, when he is faced with the opposite reality of a revolutionary mass threatening to subvert the structure of power, he is typically not behindhand in switching over to an entirely different track: denouncing mass intervention from below as evil in itself.

The fact is that the choice between Socialism-from-Above and Socialism-from-Below is, for the intellectual, basically a moral choice, whereas for the working masses who have no social alternative it is a matter of necessity. The intellectual may have the option of "joining the Establishment" where the worker does not; the same option holds also for labor leaders, who, as they rise out of their class, likewise confront a choice that did not exist before. The pressure of conformity to the mores of the ruling class, the pressure for bourgeoisification, is stronger in proportion as personal and organizational ties with the ranks below become weak. It is not hard for an intellectual or bureaucratized official to convince himself that permeation of and adaptation to the existing power is the smart way to do it, when (as it happens) it also permits sharing in the perquisites of influence and affluence.

It is an ironic fact, therefore, that the "Iron Law of Oligarchy" is iron-clad mainly for the intellectual elements from whom it arises. As a social stratum (i.e., apart from exceptional individuals) intellectuals have never been known to rise against established power in anything like the way that the modern working class has done time and again through its relatively brief history. Functioning typically as the ideological flunkies of the established rulers of society, the brain-worker sector of the non-propertied middle classes is yet, at the same time, moved to discontent and disgruntlement by the relationship. Like many another servant, this Admirable Crichton thinks, "I am a better man than my master, and if things were different we would see who should bend the knee." More than ever in our day, when the credit of the capitalist system is disintegrating throughout the world, he easily dreams of a form of society in which he can come into his own, in which the Brain and not Hands or Moneybags would dictate; in which he and his similars would be released from the pressure of Property through the elimination of capitalism, and released from the pressure of the more numerous masses through the elimination of democracy.

Nor does he have to dream very far, for existing versions of such a society seem to be before his eyes, in the Eastern collectivisms. Even if he rejects these versions, for various reasons including the Cold War, he can theorize his own version of a "good" kind of bureaucratic collectivism, to be called "Meritocracy" or "managerialism" or "Industrialism" or what-have-you, in the U.S.; or "African Socialism" in Ghana and "Arab Socialism" in Cairo; or various other kinds of socialism in other parts of the world.

The nature of the choice between Socialism-from-Above and Socialism-from-Below stands out most starkly in connection with a question on which there is a considerable measure of agreement among liberal, social-democratic and Stalinoid intellectuals today. This is the alleged inevitability of authoritarian dictatorships (benevolent despotisms) in the newly developing states of Africa and Asia particularly -- e.g. Nkrumah, Nasser, Sukarno, et al. -- dictatorships which crush independent trade unions as well as all political opposition and organize to maximize the exploitation of labor, in order to extract from the hides of the working masses sufficient capital to hasten industrialization at the tempo which the new rulers desire. Thus to an unprecented degree, "progressive" circles which once would have protested injustice anywhere have become automatic apologists for any authoritarianism which is considered non-capitalist.

Apart from the economic-determinist rationale usually given for this position, there are two aspects of the question which illuminate what is broadly at stake:

The economic argument for dictatorship, purporting to prove the necessity of breakneck industrialization, is undoubtedly very weighty for the new bureaucratic rulers -- who meanwhile do not stint their own revenue and aggrandizement -- but it is incapable of persuading the worker at the bottom of the heap that he and his family must bow to super-exploitation and super-sweating for some generations ahead, for the sake of a quick accumulation of capital. (In fact, this is why breakneck industrialization requires dictatorial controls.)

The economic-determinist argument is the rationalization of a ruling class viewpoint; it makes human sense only from a ruling-class viewpoint, which of course is always identified with the needs of "society." It makes equally good sense that the workers at the bottom of the heap must move to fight this super-exploitation to defend their elementary human dignity and wellbeing. So was it also during the capitalist Industrial Revolution, when the "newly developing states" were in Europe.

It is not a question simply of some technical-economic argument but of sides in a class struggle. The question is: Which side are you on?

It is argued that the mass of people in these countries are too backward to control the society and its government; and this is no doubt true, not only there. But what follows? How does a people or a class become fit to rule in their own name?

Only by fighting to do so. Only by waging their struggle against oppression -- oppression by those who tell them they are unfit to govern. Only by fighting for democratic power do they educate themselves and raise themselves up to the level of being able to wield that power. There has never been any other way for any class.

Although we have been considering a particular line of apologia, the two points which emerged do in fact apply all over the world, in every country, advanced or developing, capitalist or Stalinist. When the demonstrations and boycotts of the Southern Negroes threatened to embarrass President Johnson as he faced an election, the question was: which side are you on? When the Hungarian people erupted in revolt against the Russian occupier, the question was: which side are you on? When the Algerian people fought for liberation against the "socialist" government of Guy Mollet, the question was: which side are you on? When Cuba was invaded by Washington's puppets, the question was: which side are you on? and when the Cuban trade unions are taken over by the commissars of the dictatorship, the question is also: which side are you on?

Since the beginning of society, there has been no end of theories "proving" that tyranny is inevitable and that freedom-in-democracy is impossible; there is no more convenient ideology for a ruling class and its intellectual flunkies. These are self-fulfilling predictions, since they remain true only as long as they are taken to be true. In the last analysis, the only way of proving them false is in the struggle itself. That struggle from below has never been stopped by the theories from above, and it has changed the world time and again. To choose any of the forms of Socialism-from-Above is to look back to the old world, to the "old crap." To choose the road of Socialism-from-Below is to affirm the beginning of a new world.

A Few References

As mentioned in the Note, following are a few useful titles, but for most of the questions dealt with, one must go back to the sources.

For Section 1, one book worth reading is A.D. Winspear's The Genesis of Plato's Thought, which discusses Pythagoras somewhat too. For Proudhon, see the chapter in J.S. Schapiro's Liberalism and the Challenge of Fascism, and Proudhon's Carnets. For Bakunin, see E. Pyzuir's The Doctrine of Anarchism of M.A. Bakunin, with E.H. Carr's biography for background. For Lassalle, see E. Bernstein's F. Lassalle as a Social Reformer, and D. Footman's biography. For Fabianism, there is only one half-decent published study, A.N. McBriar's Fabian Socialism and English Politics, and E.J. Hobsbawm's unpublished thesis, Fabianism and the Fabians, neither adequate for our purpose. For Rosa Luxemburg, see Paul Frölich's biography, and Tony Cliff's thin book both titled with her name. For Bellamy and Gronlund, see Arthur Lipow's unpublished thesis, Edward Bellamy and the Nationalist Movement (Berkeley, Univ. of Calif., 1965).

Two articles by me in New Politics bear on some aspects of the subject: Neo-Corporatists and Neo-Reformists (I, 1, Winter 1962) and The New Social-Democratic Reformism (II, 2, Winter 1963). Also relevant are parts of the following two publications of the Independent Socialist Committee: Independent Socialism: a Perspective for the Left (pamphlet), and Introduction to Independent Socialism (a "clipping-book"). [H.D.]

Should Socialist Groups Unite?

By Steve Leigh

(this is a supplement to *Red Spark and the Revolutionary Left. It goes into detail on specific differences between Red Spark and other socialist organizations)*

The Importance of Political Clarity

“Without revolutionary theory, there is no revolutionary movement” Lenin

Marxists are historical materialists. Marx said “It is not consciousness that determines social being, but social being that determines consciousness.” However, the interaction between ideas and material reality is dialectical—i.e. the ideas people hold influence the actions they take. These actions in turn change material reality and hence the ideas people hold later. Language is one of the key distinguishing features of humanity. Virtually all action is organized with words.

In terms of our political practice, this means that a clarity of ideas is essential, not just for its own sake, but because it can lead to clarity of action. Different sets of ideas can lead to very different actions. When push comes to shove, these differences can be life or death for a revolutionary movement. Lenin said “Without revolutionary theory, there is no revolutionary movement”. Even in the short term, different analyses and understandings of Marxism can lead to different strategies and tactics, some of which will work, others of which will not.

This is why there are different organizations. From the outside, the fact that there are dozens of socialist groups can seem like silly sectarian hairsplitting. The common refrain “Why don't all you socialists get together?” is based on an underestimation of the importance of clarity.

Of course, socialists who agree on fundamental politics and the key tasks of the day should unite. Exactly what differences are significant enough to warrant different groups is always open for discussion and debate. At some points, unification may move the struggle forward. At other times, staying apart or even splitting up may be necessary. Ultimately numbers are decisive—but numbers without clarity will achieve little.

Another point is essential: Unity is NOT the same as a United Front. Marxists do two things at once: 1) build a clear Marxist organization to provide the best strategies and tactics today and to prepare for the revolution. 2) Form coalitions and United Fronts with all possible people around particular issues. This flows from the points above. We want material changes. We want struggles to succeed in winning reforms. These embolden people to further action, change consciousness, enhance organization and lay the basis for further changes. To do that we need to organize the maximum amount of people. Yet within the coalition, Marxists propose strategies and tactics that will be most effective at making the movement successful. Again—clarity to develop effective action. Being very clear about our politics and even arguing hard when necessary is NOT the same as refusal to work with people we disagree with! We have and will continue to work with other socialists, anarchists, liberals, religious people etc.

Part of the quest for clarity in understanding the world and how to change it is understanding the political positions of other socialist groups. “Red Spark and the Revolutionary Left” does this in very broad strokes.

For maximum effectiveness, a Marxist group needs to be unified on a broad analysis of the world and national situation and the strategies and tactics that flow out of that analysis. The essential issues on which unity is needed will vary over time.

What Positions are Necessary for Unity Change Over Time

“Red Spark wants to regroup more of the Left into a larger and stronger organization. However, this must be done on the basis of firm principles. If it unifies with groups that don't hold these principles it will be a house of cards which will lead to confusion and future splits.”

During the Cold War, it was vital that Marxists have a clear view of the conflict between the U.S. and Russia, between the Eastern and Western Bloc. The position of the tradition that Firebrand comes out of put forward the slogan “Neither Washington, Nor Moscow, but Workers' Power and International Socialism”. This was unique among Trotskyists. Others from the Trotskyist tradition saw Russia as progressive against the West and supported the East in the Cold War. This led to clear differences on key points of international conflict. A merger of those in our tradition and dominant trend of Trotskyism would have led to confusion and would therefore not have been healthy.

Today, 35 years after the end of the Cold War, the key international disputes have shifted. Many traditional Trotskyist organizations now see the former Eastern Bloc countries as capitalist. They no longer support one side or the other in international disputes. On the other hand, some on the Left have been influenced by Stalinism. They are so opposed to U.S. Imperialism that they adopt the attitude “the enemy of my enemy is my friend”.

They are often soft on Putin and Russia and/or China and Assad in Syria. This leads them to downplay or deny the oppression that these states impose on their own population or neighbors. (Putin against Crimea and Ukraine; China against the Muslims in north west China, against Tibet, Hong Kong etc.)

When there is need for international working-class solidarity against oppression, siding with repressive governments against their own people is unconscionable! The Marxist slogan “Workers of the World Unite” is as appropriate as ever. Those that reject this principle and instead embrace one camp or the other in the conflict between the US and its enemies are called “campists”. Beyond the issue of international solidarity, campists who claim to be socialists undermine the meaning of socialism. They call oppressive states where workers have no power “socialist”. This simply confuses potential Marxists on what socialism actually is. Unity between campists and internationalists in one socialist organization would be confusing and untenable. Unity with those who see socialism as just another oppressive and exploitive system is impossible.

On the flip side of this international conflict are “Leftists” who actually embrace their own imperialism. There are many in the U.S. who claim to be socialists who actually support U.S. foreign policy—even if with reservations and criticisms. This is the bigger problem on the broad U.S. Left though anti-U.S. campism is a bigger problem among those who consider themselves revolutionary.

Examples of this abound. “Socialists” who support Bernie and AOC are willing to overlook their votes for U.S. military budgets. They overlook their position on Israel which while critical is ultimately supportive. Bernie for example calls on us to “tone down the rhetoric” on Palestine. These would-be socialists are in the broad sense campist because they support the Western Camp against the anti-US camp. No Marxist group can put forward a socialist alternative if it is soft on U.S. imperialism!

This issue feeds into a broader issue—the Democratic Party. The DP is not just an imperialist party, it is also a key party of big Capital. It pursues the interests of big business against those of workers and the oppressed. Revolution in the U.S. will come in opposition to the Democratic Party and bourgeois liberalism which seeks to get workers to collaborate with the bosses. Revolutionaries in the U.S. are those who reject the use of the Democratic Party. Revolutionaries understand that it is impossible to reform the Democrats into a pro-working-class party. Revolutionaries want to weaken and finally abolish the police. Reformists often want to make the police more effective by improving police/community relations. A socialist organization has to take a clear stand on these issues. Including revolutionaries and reformists in one organization leads to domination by the reformists.

Those who support the Democratic Party often have a weak position on oppression. Marxists have always understood the necessity to take a vigorous stand against all forms of oppression. We see the need to integrate the fight against oppression into the fight against exploitation and vice versa. It is in the interest of workers of all backgrounds to fight it. A working class divided by oppression will be defeated. Unity can only be solidly created on the highest level—not by ignoring it, but by confronting it head on. This means winning whites to support Black Liberation, men to support women's liberation etc.

In contrast to this, some reformists adopt a strategy of class reductionism. They say that the oppressed can best have their conditions improved only by universal programs. They reject or downplay specific anti-oppression demands, such as affirmative action, reparations or Black Lives Matter.

On the opposite extreme, some anti-racist activists adopt separatist strategies. They despair of unified action by workers against oppression. Instead, they believe that only separate struggles by the oppressed can bring liberation.

Marxists reject both strategies, even while defending the RIGHT of oppressed groups to separate off if they feel the need to. A socialist organization that embraces class reductionism and/or separatism will create confusion on what an effective Marxist strategy is.

Marxists must also be united on the need for a revolutionary party. Those who want a revolution but do not want to organize for it will never be successful. We reject spontaneism. Workers and the oppressed will fight back, but success depends on organization. Lenin called for a revolutionary socialist vanguard party. For him, Marxists need to organize the vanguard of the working class, those who are leading struggles into a revolutionary party that can lead the working class to victory. This attitude requires realism. Marxists should not proclaim themselves THE vanguard party unless they really represent the actually existing vanguard of working class struggle. In the early 70's many Maoist groups in the U.S. proclaimed themselves THE vanguard party. All came to naught.

Finally, Marxists support unions but take a rank-and-file approach. We see the need for ordinary workers to organize to influence their unions in a militant direction. The bureaucracy of unions has its own interests, in mediating conflict between workers and bosses. These interests are different from the interest of workers, hence the need for workers to organize to fight for more militant and radical positions.

Red Spark is the group on the U.S. Left that most consistently embodies all these principles. It opposes campism and the Democratic Party. It embraces the need for revolution and a revolutionary party but opposes premature proclamation of such a party. It opposes class reductionism and separatism while favoring the integration of the fight against exploitation and oppression. It supports unions but is for workers organizing to strengthen their unions. Red Spark wants to regroup more of the Left into a larger and stronger organization. However, this must be done on the basis of firm principles. If it unifies with groups that don't hold these principles it will be a house of cards which will lead to confusion and future splits.

Analysis of Socialist Organizations

Below are some of the key political differences Red Spark has with other Left groups. These differences explain why Red Spark cannot simply unify with other groups that often use similar rhetoric on the Left:

DSA—Contains people who want revolution but also reformists. It engages in struggles but is primarily oriented to elections. Most of this orientation is on using and for many changing the Democrats into a Social Democratic Party. Its overall stance is critically pro-US imperialism. Some of its members are anti-U.S. campists. It does not believe in building a revolutionary party. The dominant trend in this organization is class reductionism.

Within DSA there are several distinct caucuses. In Seattle one that came out of Socialist Alternative is the “Reform and Revolution” caucus. Its politics are like Socialist Alternative. Since joining DSA, they have moved to the Right. They now argue for the “Dirty Break” strategy—running “socialists” on the Democratic Party ballot line. The supposed purpose of this is to build up leftist forces within the DP that can break out to form an independent party at a future time. In practice, the Dirty Break leads to more and more accommodation to the politics of the Democratic Party.

Communist Parties—During the late 20s and 30's the Communist Party was Stalinized. It went from being a revolutionary party to being a supporter of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) under Stalin. It was ultra-left in the late 20s and early 30's—rejecting participation in official unions. In the mid-30s it switched to the “Popular Front” an alliance with the Democratic Party. It backed the Hitler-Stalin Pact in 1939 but then allied with U.S. imperialism in WWII. After the war, a brief left turn was followed by consistent support of the Democratic Party. Its twists and turns followed the interests and demands of the USSR. Today it is virtually indistinguishable from the Democrats.

The recent offshoot of the CP, the Party of Communists USA seeks to go back to the period before “revisionism”. They believe that in 1956, the USSR under Khrushchev moved away from true Marxism. In effect they embrace the Stalin period of the CP with all its twists and turns. They reject the slightly more liberal Stalinism of the post-Stalin period which tried to have “peaceful coexistence” with the West. They support the system of State Capitalist exploitation of workers in the USSR from the late 20s to the early 50s as “socialism”.

Revolutionary Communist Party (RCP)—Looks to China under Mao as a model of socialism. It thinks workers in the U.S. are “bought off” and cannot be the force for revolution. VERY moralistic. It sees Trump as Fascist. This led them to openly support a vote for Biden in the 2020 election. It set up their own front groups as a main strategy. Their most recent front group is Refuse Fascism.

Freedom Road Socialist Organization (FRSO) is another Stalinist/Maoist group. FRSO looks to the USSR before 1956 as an example of socialism. It rejects the “revisionism” of Khrushchev after Stalin's death. It differs from the RCP in still supporting current day China as being socialist:

Today, the People's Republic of China, Vietnam, Laos, Cuba and Democratic Korea still follow the socialist road, and have built socialism based on their own particular conditions. We have a lot to learn from studying their experiences as well. China in particular stands out. Looking at People's China today is like looking into the future. By creatively applying Marxist-Leninist principles to Chinese conditions, the Communist Party of China has modernized their country, wiped out extreme poverty, and set out well on the way towards building prosperous and harmonious socialist society.

As befitting its Stalinism, it has operated in an undemocratic way in coalitions, including the Palestine college encampments. It also shown its class collaborationism by celebrating the victory of Brandon Johnson as mayor of Chicago. Brandon has turned out to be another repressive liberal Democrat who even pushed through an increase in the police budget:

Johnson's victory is also a victory for working and oppressed people, as demonstrated by the range of organizations and individuals who celebrated with Johnson and his family at the Marriott Marquis on election night.

—FRSO's newspaper Fightback

US Socialist Workers Party (SWP)—Historically the main party of American Trotskyism. In the 80's they moved away from Trotskyism, rejecting the theory of Permanent Revolution. Instead of calling for a worker's state they call for a multi-class state as a transition to socialism. Lately they have gotten very conservative within the Left. They attack liberals from the right instead of the left because they see Liberals as middle class. They orient to workers who are right-wing. This included support for the “Freedom Convoy” against Covid vaccination in Canada. They reject Boycott Divestment and Sanctions against Israel because they see Israeli workers as a revolutionary force. They are actually Zionist. They supported the Dobbs decision. Their excuse for this was that it would be good to have a democratic debate about abortion rights at the state level. They believe that the fundamental rights of women should be up to a vote of women and men! They focus on running their own candidates with leftist demands mixed with support of Israel. Despite their origins and some rhetoric, they are no longer part of the Left.

Socialist Alternative—Came out of the Militant Tendency in Britain. The Militant Tendency entered the Labor Party in the late 40s and stayed in for over 4 decades. In the 90s, the Militant Tendency split. The CWI which left the Labor Party set up Socialist Alternative in the U.S. (SAlt). Recently, the CWI split again with SAlt becoming part of the International Socialist Alternative. Its fundamental politics persist from the Militant. It is not revolutionary. Instead, it believes in taking over the bourgeois state through an election and using that state to start the transition to socialism. It claims to believe in smashing the state, but only after first using the state. It does not think it is crucial to take the whole economy into public ownership, but wants to continue small property ownership, and hence a quasi-market economy. It supports police unions and sees police as workers. Instead of police abolition it calls for purging the police of bad apples. It has a quasi-pacifist position on the overthrow of capitalism. It does not clearly differentiate the nationalism of the oppressor from that of the oppressed. It does not see clearly that one can be progressive (the nationalism of the oppressed) and the other is reactionary. It downplays the fight against oppression in practice and tends toward class reductionism. Like the SWP it opposes BDS and sees the Israeli working class as an agent of revolutionary transformation. In the war between the U.S. and Iran they support neither side, seeing the war as an inter-imperialist conflict. Red Spark sees that war as primarily an oppressed nation fighting imperialism.

Another offshoot of the Militant Tendency is the International Marxist Tendency. In the Spring of 2024, it renamed itself Revolutionary Communists of America. It is not quite as conservative as SAlt but shares the same fundamental politics. It has argued strongly for its reactionary position on Palestine. During the Genocidal bombing of Gaza from Oct.7 2023 on, IMT condemned Hamas' tactics rather than supporting Palestinian Liberation “by any means necessary”.

Party of Socialism and Liberation—(PSL)—VERY campist! Its ancestors were in the Trotskyist tradition. In 1956, they broke with most Trotskyists by opposing the Hungarian Revolution against Stalinism. Since then, this tendency has opposed the students in Tiananmen Square in 1989, bemoaned the overthrow of the Stalinist states in Eastern Europe, supported Assad against the Syrian Revolution, supported China against its oppressed minorities, opposed the movement in Hong Kong etc. It actually praises Kim Jung Un and North Korea as socialist! It is uncritical of the Maduro regime in Venezuela. Its strong support of Trans rights contradicts the position of regimes it supports. In the 2020 election it flirted with lesser evilism. It said that if Bernie were the Democratic nominee, they would adopt a “safe state” strategy, implicitly supporting Bernie in states that would have close votes. During the Palestine Liberation movement 2023–24 it supported people voting uncommitted in the Democratic primaries to pressure the Democrats, rather than fully breaking with the Democratic Party. Otherwise, its positions on domestic issues are mostly fine though its tactics are often questionable. It seems to vary in that regard from branch to branch.

PSL started as a breakaway from the Workers' World Party which shares its fundamental politics.

Freedom Socialist Party (FSP)—Started as the Seattle branch of the SWP in the late 60's. Its differences with the SWP were that it was more supportive of Mao's China and more opposed to Black Nationalism. It did not see any progressive potential in Black Nationalism, instead supporting “revolutionary integrationism”. Red Spark does not see Black Nationalism as a solution to racism. However, as materialists, we look at struggles first on the basis of their potential material impact. We support struggles that will have a positive impact even if we disagree with the set of ideas motivating that struggle. When we disagree with the dominant ideas of a positive struggle, we would give the struggle critical support.—Support in helping it win, criticism in seeing its ideas as limiting its impact. The FSP instead takes an approach purely on the basis of ideas. On the other issue, it still sees China as in transition between capitalism and socialism and rejects calling it an imperialist power. It therefore takes a soft campist position.

It has an extreme multi-issue approach to coalitions which is based on idealism, not materialism. It seems to believe that a coalition will be more radical and successful the more demands it has. The Marxist stand instead is that the key goal of a movement is to win material changes. The best demands for a movement are what can best motivate struggle in a progressive direction. As Engels said “one step forward in the movement is worth a dozen programs”. Because of this attachment to the “correct” program of demands, it often operates in a very bureaucratic way in coalitions. It has taken undemocratic actions within coalitions to ensure the “correct” program.

It also has a tendency to argue that Marxist politics are the only REAL politics of a movement. It seems to believe that only Marxists can be consistent Feminists, Ecology activists etc. In fact, these movements are broad politically and multi-class. Feminism, for example, started as Bourgeois Feminism, for the gender integration of the class structure, not for the overthrow of classes. The point should not be to argue about who the “real” Feminists are but to explain that only socialist revolution can bring women's liberation. Marxists are Feminists in that we see women's liberation as essential to socialism and only possible through socialist revolution. We are Marxist Feminists but understand that others who are Feminists see themselves as Feminists as much as we do. We need to win people to Marxist Feminism and hence Marxism, not to “real Feminism”.

During the Genocidal bombing of Gaza from Oct.7 2023 on, like the IMT and SAlt, the FSP condemned Hamas' tactics rather than supporting Palestinian Liberation “by any means necessary”.

Finally, it is a bit separatist. It has maintained a theoretically separate but actually integral organization to FSP called Radical Women for 50 years. This is not just a caucus responding to sexism in the organization but a separatist strategy of permanent standing.

For more elaboration on Red Spark positions on various issues go to RedSpark.red!

Marxism, Oppression and Identity Politics

By Kenneth G

Handling oppression is a thorny issue on the left. Some take a dismissive attitude towards demands that specifically fight oppression, calling them “divisive” and preferring demands which help the working class evenly. For an example of this dismissive attitude, take Jacobin, the flagship publication of the Democratic Socialist of America (DSA). Writing for Jacobin, Nick French calls Zohran Mamdani “savvy” for abandoning the main slogan of the Black Lives Matter movement “defund the police.”

It should be noted that Marxists indeed view the whole working class as oppressed. Workers are subjected to despotism by default upon entering the workplace, and their entire quality of life is determined at best by how much wealth they can produce for capitalists. This fundamental situation is true for all workers, even the ones who are relatively better off. However, in this article when we use the word oppression, we refer to the particular, special forms of oppression faced by subsections of the working class, such as the oppression of Black people, women, immigrants, etc. Resolving special oppression is a prerequisite for resolving the oppression faced by workers generally, since special oppression divides the working class. In this article, when we use the word oppression, we refer to the special oppression faced by particular sectors of the working class, not the general oppression faced by all workers.

This dismissive attitude by some on the left often creates distrust between those who experience oppression and those who do not. Most often, this distrust is manifested through identity politics, a political approach which uses identity as the basis of its perspective, rather than class. There are many kinds of identity politics—Black identity politics, immigrant identity politics, trans identity politics, etc.—but on the left, they center around one or more forms of oppression and the people who experience it.

The left is overall divided on how to respond to this political tendency. Some, like the DSA, take a generally dismissive attitude towards it. Some go further and reject identity politics completely. For example, Socialist Equality Party (SEP) says this about identity politics:

The [Socialist Equality Party] rejects identity politics based on race, gender or sexuality as reactionary. Such an approach to politics, which dismisses the fundamental class character of society, benefits only the privileged upper-middle class and the ruling class, while dividing the working class.[1]_

We would be remiss not to point out that SEP has also publicly defended multiple rapists in its paper, and takes an almost entirely critical attitude towards movements against oppression, such as Black Lives Matter and #MeToo. They even refer to #MeToo as a “witch hunt.” Others on the left embrace one form of identity politics or another. In fact, it is the dominant approach in most movements against oppression. Because identity politics is a step away from class politics, this means that it is only a matter of time before most movements are co-opted or quashed outright by middle-class elements or even members of the ruling class.

However, sometimes it is even embraced in socialist organizations. A good example of this is Freedom Socialist Party (FSP). FSP maintains its own socialist organization, open to everyone, but also affiliates with an all-women group called Radical Women (RW) which FSP describes as an “autonomous organization affiliated by program and aims with the Freedom Socialist Party.” This approach is confusing—if FSP and RW are bound by the same program and same aims, why have two separate organizations? Is FSP not dedicated enough to women's liberation? Or are women expected to lead every charge against sexism? Is an organization with men in it inherently untrustworthy on this question?

If it weren't clear enough, taking a blanket position on identity politics is problematic. A complete embrace of identity politics is a step away from working-class politics, which makes way for capitalist co-optation of our movements. Complete dismissal usually means dismissing fights against oppression, and sometimes even culminates in downright reactionary positions. Instead of taking a blanket position, identity politics must be assessed in each instance based on whether it helps or hinders class struggle.

In this article, we take a look at the characteristics which are common to most, if not all forms of identity politics and assess them each.

Subjective experience and the politics of deference

The most unifying characteristic of the myriad forms of identity politics is a focus on the subjective or “lived” experience of oppressed people. Oppression is seen as conferring authority about how to fight oppression upon those who experience it. The role of those outside of the oppressed community is simply to “listen” to the oppressed. As Deen Fair puts it in her piece “An Open Letter to White ‘Allies' from a White Friend,” writing for the journal Understanding and Dismantling Privilege, the role of white people in the fight against racism is to amplify the voices of the oppressed and “shut the heck up and listen.”

Fair is well-meaning, but there are several issues with this approach. Oppressed people are never a monolith; there is always a cacophony of differing and mutually contradictory voices among any group of people, oppressed or not. Listening to and adopting one oppressed person's perspective necessarily means rejecting another's. There is no way around thinking critically about one's own politics.

Fair's approach also confers the burden of leadership and critical thought onto oppressed people, regardless of whether they are ready for it or want it. At the extreme, this results in tokenization, where one or a few oppressed people come to represent the voice of their entire oppressed “community,” while those outside of it simply listen and accept orders.

Due to the focus on lived experience, adherents of identity politics tend to downplay the importance of objective knowledge about oppression. This can result in a form of anti-intellectualism which downplays the need to study the world and the effects of oppression upon it. After all, if lived experience is superior, why bother with the work of study? All that is needed is introspection if you possess lived experience, or listening to the oppressed if you don't. Alternatively, it can result in the idea that it is impossible to have objective knowledge about oppression at all.

While it is true that oppressed people have unique and personal experience, this does not necessarily make them more suited to leadership. There are many reactions one can have to oppression. In some cases, people may be radicalized; in others, they may draw deeply conservative conclusions or even reject the idea that change is possible at all.

A good example of this phenomenon is captured by the graphic novel Maus. Written by the Polish-American cartoonist and author Art Spiegelman, Maus reflects upon his Jewish father's experience at the hands of the Nazis and his emigration to the US. But Spiegelman's father doesn't necessarily come out of the experience with a complete rejection of racism; on the contrary, Spiegelman recounts a story in which his father was upset with his wife for being willing to pick up a Black hitchhiker. Reflecting on the duality of his father's victimhood and racist attitudes in MetaMaus, his subsequent book analyzing Maus, he says “Look, suffering doesn't make you better, it just makes you suffer!”

Even oppressed revolutionaries cannot be considered above reproach or critique. The example of Angela Davis is instructive. In her early years, she spent time in jail as a political prisoner. In the US left, her contributions on the issues of women's liberation and anti-racism have been canonized alongside that of figures like Assata Shakur and others. Most Marxists would assume that Davis would generally have at least the fundamentals down—but in 2024, she came out in support of the Biden-Harris campaign, and later the Harris-Walz campaign.

How could someone calling themselves a Marxist, who has contributed to the struggle for Palestinian liberation, support politicians actively engaged in bombing Palestinians? Moreover, how could she support Kamala Harris, who climbed her way into office by incarcerating Black people? The sad reality is that, no matter how educated someone is, no matter their identity, everyone remains at risk of bad ideas. For that reason, we must insist that no one be above critique, and that leadership be earned through struggle and experience, rather than given by deference.

Privilege theory and guilt politics

Another thread common in discussions around identity politics is privilege theory. Privilege theory argues that non-oppressed identities enjoy unearned privileges when compared to oppressed identities. The thinking of this approach is that men in general are privileged over women, white people are privileged over people of color, and so on. Challenging these unearned privileges forms a central part of the political approach for most practitioners of identity politics.

It is important to clearly and emphatically state here that it is absolutely true that men enjoy unearned advantages over women, white people are in general better off than people of color, and so on. These things are indisputable facts which should inform our analysis of the world. However, framing these advantages as “privileges” is not always helpful.

The essay White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack by Peggy McIntosh is generally considered the foundational text on this approach. In it, McIntosh lists 26 conditions which she uses to describe the privileges white people have over other racial groups in the US. The biggest issue with this approach is one that McIntosh herself identifies:

In unpacking this invisible knapsack of white privilege, I have listed conditions of daily experience which I once took for granted. Nor did I think of any of these prerequisites as bad for the holder. I now think that we need a more finely differentiated taxonomy of privilege, for some of these varieties are only what one would want for everyone in a just society, and others give license to be ignorant, oblivious, arrogant and destructive.

So some so-called privileges should be extended to everyone, and others should be eliminated entirely. The question is, how should this be determined? Given identity politics as a framework, this question is difficult to answer.

Take for example the 1980 article “Women and the Draft” by Constance Scott, published by Freedom Socialist Party. In it, Scott argues that, if a draft is instated, women should demand their inclusion on the basis of rejecting sexism:

But if [a draft is instated], equity demands that it comprise both sexes and all sexual orientations. Then women and sexual minorities will take their place as true equals in the draft resistance movement, inside or outside of the military.

Note that this article was written and published before the open inclusion of lesbian and gay people in the military, hence the argument for inclusion of all sexual orientations. Scott's argument here is primarily that women's exclusion from the draft is a product of sexism, and should be rejected to foster greater equality. Such a conclusion makes sense when one cannot distinguish between a lack of oppression and privilege.

However, just because one group is disadvantaged in a particular way does not mean that other groups should demand the same treatment. Rather than calling for women to be drafted also, wouldn't it make more sense to stubbornly insist that no one should be? To extend this tortured logic, should white people demand they be locked up at the same rate as people of color, or demand that no one be locked up? Should cis people demand that they also be forced to prove their gender, or that everyone's stated gender be accepted without question?

For Marxists, understanding which demands to take up, which privileges to abolish and which to convert into rights for all, is a matter of understanding which approach does most to advance the interests of the working class. In the case of the draft, roughly doubling the number of people legally subject to being conscripted into an imperialist war is not beneficial to the aims of the working class.

Aside from the conflation of a lack of oppression with privilege, there is another more fundamental issue with privilege theory: the politics of guilt. Capitalists understand the demobilizing power of guilt. That is why figures like Robin DiAngelo were deployed during the Black Lives Matter rebellion of 2020. Her book White Fragility: Why It's So Hard for White People to Talk About Racism became an overnight bestseller in the wake of George Floyd's murder. White Fragility largely builds off the same arguments made by McIntosh, but goes further, arguing that:

To say that whiteness is a location of structural advantage is to recognize that to be white is to be in a privileged position within society and its institutions—to be seen as an insider and to be granted the benefits of belonging. This position automatically bestows unearned advantages. Whites control all major institutions of society and set the policies and practices that others must live by.

To say that “whites” control all major institutions is to ignore the massive class disparity that exists between the capitalists who really do control all major institutions—and the white working class people who have no real voice in the government at all. Indeed, the famous 2014 Princeton study by Martin Gilens empirically confirms that the US is an oligarchy, not a democracy. In fact, the US has never been a democracy, not even at its foundation. Aside from the obvious undemocratic exclusion of Black people, indigenous people and women from the political system, the founding fathers sought at every turn to exclude even poor white men from any real political power. This attitude was exemplified by James Madison's famous remark in his letter arguing for a bicameral legislature, that the government needed to defend the “interests of the minority of the opulent against the majority.”

The emotion of guilt can be a useful one, when one has actually done something wrong. It is a useful way to keep each others' behavior in check and motivate people to reflect. However, in anti-oppression movements, guilt often has a demobilizing effect. This is because, regardless of the relatively privileged position of some workers, the reality is that no working class people—even white, male, heterosexual ones—have any say in whether they live in an oppressive society or not. Oppression is structural and systematic, and it is upheld by a tiny minority of capitalists. Guilt, and privilege theory by extension, encourage us to look inward—but oppression, and the solutions to it, exist outside of us.

Oppression, intersectionality, and universalism

The final part of identity politics to evaluate is its approach to describing oppression. Identity politics views oppression as a fixed status, rather than a historical reality that can be overcome. The result is that the pathway to overcoming oppression becomes unclear, and the timeline completely indeterminate.

Although adherents of identity politics want to describe oppression, they often use other words: underprivileged, disadvantaged, marginalized, etc. Describing someone as oppressed requires us to ask, who is doing the oppressing, and how? The alternative words usually serve to avoid those questions.

Furthermore, as we will see, they serve to prevent activists from realizing the commonalities in the struggle against all forms of oppression. One may be oppressed in just one way, or in multiple ways at the same time; when one is oppressed in multiple ways, identity politics describes this with the framework of intersectionality.

Intersectionality argues that if a person experiences multiple forms of oppression, they combine to form a completely unique experience. For example, Black women experience both racism and sexism simultaneously: the sexism they experience is qualitatively different from the sexism that white women experience, and the racism they experience is qualitatively different than that of Black men. This works well as a description.

So what is the issue with intersectionality? The issue is not with the framework per se, but with the underlying problem within identity politics it seeks to solve. Fundamentally, identity politics bases its perspective on a particular identity. Picking the “correct” identity is essential for developing the correct political perspective. As the Combahee River Collective put it in their statement:

This focusing upon our own oppression is embodied in the concept of identity politics. We believe that the most profound and potentially most radical politics come directly out of our own identity, as opposed to working to end somebody else's oppression.

Activists today generally understand that separatism is a failed strategy, and are searching for political perspectives that create solidarity. The problem for identity politics is that it has no real vision of how to include people outside of a particular identity in the struggle, apart from them being “allies.” The solution, in keeping with its approach, is intersectionality: instead of basing one's politics on being Black, a woman, trans, or whatever else, one should base their politics on the “most oppressed” identity. By resolving the oppression of say, Black trans women, the oppression of Black people, women and trans people are all resolved at once, so the argument goes.

One rather unfortunate side effect of this approach is the pejoratively termed “oppression olympics” in which different people, and therefore different identities, compete to determine who is most oppressed. The prize of this “competition” is being placed at the center of whichever political perspective. However, aside from the petty squabbles this approach invites, the main issue is that intersectionality does not solve the fundamental issue with identity politics. Because identity politics does not recognize the centrality of class, it has no realistic vision of ending any form of oppression whatsoever, much less all of them.

For Marxists, the relationships are much clearer. Truly understanding class requires understanding the various forms of oppression—patriarchy, racism, transphobia, xenophobia, and so on—as they all serve to uphold particular pillars of capitalist rule. Opposing oppression necessarily implies opposing its source, i.e. capitalism.

For example, the US was founded on two of the most colossal acts of racism in history: the African slave trade, and the genocide of the indigenous peoples of North America. The wealth of the US ruling class traces its historical origins to these two vicious acts of racism. Calling for reparations for these historical crimes directly threatens the wealth of the US ruling class, and undermines the foundations of US capitalism.

For another example, patriarchy originates as a system which allows a small number of ruling class families to privatize wealth on the one hand, and avoid any responsibility for raising the next generation of workers on the other. By keeping property “in the family,” ruling classes since time immemorial have managed to reproduce class relations, ensuring that a few are wealthy and the rest remain in a position of exploitation. By enforcing the concept of “your” and “my” children, and enforcing strict gender roles, they place almost the entire responsibility of raising the next generation upon working class women, getting the next generation of workers on the cheap.

The reason why the ruling class enforces sexism and represses LGBTQ+ ultimately goes back to patriarchy, which itself is a prerequisite of capitalism. If women aren't forced to do the unpaid labor of childrearing, the costs imposed on the ruling class for raising the next generation of workers increases, threatening their profits. If people are allowed to have romantic relationships outside of the patriarchal ideal of heterosexual marriage, that threatens the mythology of the family and gender roles, which again threatens the system of unpaid labor and ultimately capitalism.

If capitalism is the source of oppression, then socialism is the solution to it. The working class is capable of socialist revolution, but only if it is united—and to be united, it must resolutely stand against every form of oppression which divides it. To paraphrase Karl Marx, the working class must become “fit to rule” prior to taking power.

How Marxists handle oppression

So far, we have mostly discussed the issues with identity politics. But how do Marxists handle oppression? Marxists argue that it is necessary for all workers, regardless of their specific background, to actively oppose all forms of oppression. Being in active opposition means that they must take action, yes, but they must also critically engage with and understand issues of oppression as well, even when they do not experience a particular form of oppression. Marxists do not see themselves as “allies” trying to help oppressed people out of the goodness of their hearts—rather, they see that their own interests, the interests of the working class, and humanity in general, are connected to the fight to end oppression. In other words, Marxists adopt the attitude exemplified by the words of indigenous Australian activist Lilla Watson:

If you have come here to help me, you are wasting your time. But if you have come because your liberation is bound up with mine, then let us work together.

Marxists argue against separatism because it is less effective than integrated movements based on solidarity. However, we generally reserve the strongest criticism for those who downplay or outright uphold oppression. In order to have an integrated movement, oppressed people must be convinced that those who don't share their oppression take the issue seriously.

Accordingly, Marxists argue for measures which specifically combat oppression, even if other sections of the working class do not immediately benefit. For example, Marxists argue in favor of reparations for Black people, land-back for indigenous people and so on, even though the majority of the US working class wouldn't immediately benefit from these measures. Winning other working class people to the demands of the oppressed is essential for having an integrated movement.

All these things said, it is also important to note that all workers benefit from overcoming oppression in the long run, regardless of whether they personally experience it. For example, the more vulnerable position of immigrant workers is often used to undermine the wages, benefits, etc. of citizen workers. The less this distinction is upheld, the more that oppression against immigrants is overcome, the less employers are able to pit citizen workers against immigrant workers and lower everyone's wages.

When it comes to socialist organizations, Marxists uphold the right of oppressed people to form their own caucuses to address issues specific to them. A caucus is a specific subgroup of a larger socialist organization; examples might include a women's caucus or a caucus for people of color. The purpose of these caucuses is to allow oppressed people to push the larger organization to take up particular issues, make organizational changes, and more.

However, such caucuses are not considered the final word on issues of oppression. Obviously, issues raised by oppressed comrades should be given the proper weight. However, the rest of the organization must be convinced and allowed to debate proposals and arguments put forth by a particular caucus; the caucuses do not have any special authority on issues of oppression.

This position is best expressed by the controversy over the Bund. The Bund was an organization of Jewish workers originally within the Russian Social-Democratic Labor Party (RSDLP), the umbrella organization to which both the Mensheviks and Bolsheviks officially belonged. The Bundists, as they were called, felt that they should be given the final authority on issues of Jewish oppression in Russia. They also argued for a federated organizational model, which would have given them the ability to recruit members to their organization on a different basis from the rest of the party. The majority of the party, including V.I. Lenin and Leon Trotsky, disagreed with the Bundists and called for Jewish oppression to be addressed by the whole party. This issue came to a head in 1903, when the Bund exited the RSDLP after its demands were rejected. Lenin, for his part, said this in response to the Bundists' political arguments:

That is just how the anarchists argue: the rights of individuals are unlimited; they may conflict; every individual determines the limits of his rights for himself. The limits of autonomy should be determined not by the group [caucus] itself, but by the whole of which it forms a part. The Bund was a striking instance of the violation of this principle.[2]_

In general, measures meant to handle oppression within a Marxist organization should promote a culture of solidarity, not separatism. Marxists must insist that the responsibility for handling oppression never be handed off entirely to oppressed people, but rather that it be spread democratically across the whole organization.

Conclusions

Handling oppression and relating to identity politics is a difficult issue on the left. While the conclusions of identity politics can sometimes be correct, in general socialists should avoid adopting the logic of identity politics. Instead, each conclusion and movement must be evaluated on the basis of whether it advances working class struggle or not.

The vast majority of movements against oppression will be influenced by identity politics, if not be dominated by it entirely. This is only natural given the dominance of identity politics on the left. In general, Marxists should approach movements against oppression with the aim of participating as fellow fighters against oppression, while maintaining our own independent politics. Activists today are searching for political approaches that create solidarity, rather than promote division. It is our job to reach those activists and convince them that Marxism is the way to do that.

[1]

Niles Niemuth, “Race, class and social conflict in the United States.”

[2]

Lenin, One Step Forward, Two Steps Back: The Crisis in Our Party.